<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-07T15:59:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Coach’s Corner</title><subtitle>I am the founder of EV3Lessons</subtitle><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/07/2017-04-05-Marble-Run.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2017-08-07T15:59:01-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-07T15:59:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/07/2017-04-05-Marble-Run</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/07/2017-04-05-Marble-Run.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/Pokedragon.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn to make decisions together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn to complete a task on time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn to follow instructions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper towel/toilet paper tubes (about twice as many as the number of kids)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A ball that fits the tubes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A small box/bucket for the ball to fall into&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
On strips of paper, write out differnt things/processes your team can act out. Fold them so that the team cannot read them when picking one. Place all of them in an envelope/box or spread of a table. Place the random collection of objects in a box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Create the longest marble run using the materials provided. The ball must fall into the box/
bucket. You may try your contraption only three times before you have to present it. You have 5 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;
Watch to see what ideas they come up with to create the marble run (especially since no tape was provided). Also see how they worked together to accomplish the task. Have the team demonstrate their contraption to you at the end of five minutes.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title type="html">Act it Out V.2.0</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/05/Act-it-Out-V2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Act it Out V.2.0" /><published>2017-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/05/Act-it-Out-V2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/05/Act-it-Out-V2.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/Pokedragon.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coming to a consensus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing creativity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communicating with each other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making sure everyone has a role&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Box/hat/envelope to hold paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A random collection of objects (paper, cone, hat, bandana, ping pong ball)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
On strips of paper, write out differnt things/processes your team can act out. Fold them so that the team cannot read them when picking one. Place all of them in an envelope/box or spread of a table. Place the random collection of objects in a box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Select one piece of paper without looking at the words on it. Also select one object from the box. As a team, act out whatever is on the paper. You have 5 minutes to plan and act out whatever is one the paper and incorporate the 1 object you picked. Your time begins now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;
This Challenge is a test of the team’s imagination and creativity and decision making skills.
You can come up many different ideas: fish, airplane, carousel, car, explorer in the jungle, shoe factory, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Team Building Activities</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/03/Team-Building-Activities.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Team Building Activities" /><published>2017-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/03/Team-Building-Activities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/03/Team-Building-Activities.html">&lt;p&gt;This article was inspired by a visit to the Forge Initiative in Cary, North Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/TeamBuildingWall.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above photograph is an organized wall full of misalaneous items. There are balls, cardboard, popsicle sticks, cones, bandanas, and more, all organized alphabetically.  I love this idea of keeping a random collection of objects. While our own collection is not nearly as organized, I too like to pull random objects toghether to come up with team building activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Why practice team building?&lt;/b&gt;
Whether you are a FIRST LEGO League team, a company employee, or a member of boy scout’s troop, team building activities are pretty commonplace. They are a great way to learn to work together and appreciate each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top 5 reasons to for team building in FIRST LEGO League:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Getting to know each other better. Kids come together to make teams. Sometimes, they barely know each other. Activities are good icebreakers.
2) Team work and increasing the performance of the team. The team can learn to problem solve together and improve their overall performance during the season.
3) Increasing Fun and creativity. Through team building, teams can display their personality. They will learn to be more creative and think out-of-the-box.
4) Building communication skills.  Activities will teach the team to communicate better with each other.
5) A well-earned break. Team building activities offer a quick and fun break from the reaseach project and robot building at team meetings.
‘
&lt;b&gt; Where can I get team building activities to practice? &lt;/b&gt;
If you look at EV3Lessons.com (Resources), you will see that there are over 37 Team Building Activities. There are some that are designed as get-to-know-you activities. These are great at the start of the season.  There are some that help teams realize the role that each person plays.  No matter what activity you pick, understand that the goal is for the kids on the team to learn to work together and appreciate one another.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Asha Seshan&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html">This article was inspired by a visit to the Forge Initiative in Cary, North Carolina.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Act it Out V.1.0</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/07/05/Act-it-Out-V1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Act it Out V.1.0" /><published>2017-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/07/05/Act-it-Out-V1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/07/05/Act-it-Out-V1.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/Juggling.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coming to a consensus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing creativity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communicating with each other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making sure everyone has a role&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Box/hat/envelope to hold paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
On strips of paper, write out differnt things/processes your team can act out. Fold them so that the team cannot read them when picking one. Place all of them in an envelope/box or spread of a table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Select one piece of paper without looking at the words on it. Also select one object from the box. As a team, act out whatever is on the paper. You have 5 minutes to plan and act out whatever is one the paper. Your time begins now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;
This Challenge is a test of the team’s imagination and creativity and decision making skills.
You can come up many different ideas: fish, airplane, carousel, car, explorer in the jungle, shoe factory, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Alternative Programming Languages for the EV3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/06/14/Alternative-Programming-Languages.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alternative Programming Languages for the EV3" /><published>2017-06-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/06/14/Alternative-Programming-Languages</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/06/14/Alternative-Programming-Languages.html">&lt;p&gt;Did you know that you can use alternative programming languages on your EV3?  Here are some useful resources for getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know of other good resources we should add, let us know at team@ev3lessons.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Resources2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;EV3 Basic:&lt;/b&gt; A textual programming language that uses Microsoft Small Basic with an EV3 extension.&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.EV3Basic.com&quot;&gt; EV3 Basic Introduction by EV3Basic.com &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udemy.com/ev3-basic-getting-started/#%2F&quot;&gt; Udemy Video-based Lessons by Nigel Ward &lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3basic.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt; Teaching with Robots: &lt;/a&gt; Lecture Summary&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3basic.blogspot.com/p/materials.html&quot;&gt; Teaching with Robots: &lt;/a&gt; PPTX slides and code&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://onedrive.live.com/view.aspx?resid=B222F4E659AAFCA5!281088&amp;amp;ithint=onenote%2c&amp;amp;app=OneNote&amp;amp;authkey=!ABn7nL9tKUTChd0&quot;&gt; EV3 Programming Using Textual Languages &lt;/a&gt;: Supplemental material by Anthony Orme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Swift:&lt;/b&gt; A multi-purpose programming language created by Apple for iOS. 
&lt;br /&gt;Download App from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/swift-playgrounds/id908519492?mt=8App&quot;&gt; iTunes or App Store &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robotc.net/&quot;&gt; Robot-C &lt;/a&gt;: A C-based programming language for robotics systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ev3dev.org/&quot;&gt;EV3Dev.org&lt;/a&gt;: A Debian Linux-based operating system lets you run many programming languages including Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lejos.org/ev3.php&quot;&gt;leJOS: &lt;/a&gt; A Java virtual machine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.open-roberta.org/en/welcome/&quot;&gt;OpenRoberta: &lt;/a&gt; A free, cloud-based platform for programming EV3 robots.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html">Did you know that you can use alternative programming languages on your EV3?  Here are some useful resources for getting started.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Giant Skis</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/06/05/Giant-Skis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giant Skis" /><published>2017-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/06/05/Giant-Skis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/06/05/Giant-Skis.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/GiantSkis.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coming to a consensus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communicating with each other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning to work together and coordinate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;
Two 8’ 2x4s (or 2x6’s) for a team of 5
Ten 4-5’ lengths of rope (2 per team member) 
Drill with 1” and 3/8” drill bits&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
On strips of paper, write out differnt things/processes your team can act out. Fold them so that the team cannot read them when picking one. Place all of them in an envelope/box or spread of a table. Place the random collection of objects in a box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Let’s go skiing together. Your team has one pair of skis Move across the room or driveway using only the skis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How to construct the skis:&lt;/b&gt;
Starting at one end of each 2x4 (laid flat on the 4” side), mark 6”, 24”, 42”, 60” and 78”, each in the center of the 2x4. Make the same marks on the other 2x4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At each mark, drill halfway (3/4”) with the 1” drill bit. Then, drilling in the center of each 1” diameter hole, drill through the 2x4 with the 3/8” drill bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tie a knot at the end of each piece of rope and feed the other end through the 2x4, larger hole side first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The knots will fit inside the 1” diameter portion of the hole, but not pull through the 3/8” hole.
Flip the skis over – each team member should stand with their rope at their feet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Brickheads&lt;br&gt;Virginia</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Three Hs in FIRST LEGO League</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/05/13/The-3-Hs-in-FIRST-LEGO-League.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Three Hs in FIRST LEGO League" /><published>2017-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/05/13/The-3-Hs-in-FIRST-LEGO-League</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/05/13/The-3-Hs-in-FIRST-LEGO-League.html">&lt;p&gt;In April this year, I did a training course in Janeiro de Cima in Portugal. The course was organized by the Portuguese National Agency of Erasmus+ and, as a delegate from the Netherlands, I was given the opportunity by the Erasmus+ Youth National Agency to participate in this TC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erasmus+ is the European grant program for education, youth and sport. The underlying idea is that investment in education, training and non-formal learning is crucial to give people - regardless of their age or background - the opportunity to continuously develop, or as they say become a lifelong learner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/trophy.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the TC, I once again realized that the First Lego League program is a great program for young people to get acquainted with science and technology in a non-formal way. The program achieves all facets of learning with the Head as well as with the Hand and with the Heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But during the training, I realized that this program is much more focused on the Head and Hands and, unfortunately, far less on the Heart. Within the FLL program, the emphasis is on the teamwork and on the 7 Core Values associated with it. But with that we leave many opportunities unused. For example, the program could also promote issues such as social inclusion and equivalence (*active citizenship) and increase opportunities for peers who are in disadvantaged situations. These young people are disadvantaged because they face personal problems or obstacles that restrict or even exclude their participation in projects. For example: &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people with disabilities (specific needs) &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people with learning difficulties, educational difficulties &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people with a low standard of living and economic barriers &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people for whom language adaptation or cultural integration is a problem, such as migration, refugees, expats &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people with chronic conditions, who are seriously ill or have a psychiatric disorder &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people who are faced with discrimination and social barriers &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people from remote or rural areas or urban problem areas, thus geographical barriers &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program could also promote issues as multilingualism. Multilingualism is one of the cornerstones of the European project and also a powerful symbol of the European Union’s pursuit of unity in diversity. The FLL community makes it possible to contact teams across Europe and the rest of the world. By joining international tournaments, robotics camps or exchanges, we also increase the opportunity for team members to come into contact with foreign languages from a young age, allowing us to promote and facilitate dialogue between young people, language education and linguistic diversity. But this applies not only far way in another country also in own’s own country where it is possible to get in touch with children who speak different languages and come from different cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the FLL program and through Core Values, the importance of personal development, respect and sharing of knowledge has already been well represented, but there should be more emphasis on this. Everyone deserves the opportunity to personal development,  to broaden your horizon, to discover the potential professions and to make full use of learning. This has to be done in a safe environment where everyone is respected and protected. It is therefore that I’m convinced that we should not we exclude young people from the FLL program on the basis of learning performance or things like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now that I see this on paper, I come to the conclusion that all of the above elements that are important for the Erasmus+ program also fit seamlessly into the FIRST LEGO League program. Social integration and equivalence, multilingualism, self-development and security are all elements that fit well in the Heart of the FLL and are more or less already represented. So let us combine these two programs and thus give young people even more and better knowledge and skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I call up to all FLL teams not only to focus on the Head and Hands but also the Heart. Do not limit yourself to the team, teamwork and Core Values, but also look for the international dimension and the possibilities of active citizenship and citizenship participation. This makes the FLL program into a total program that covers a lot more than STEM, with much more to win than an Award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/FLLlogo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dutch primary and secondary schools have been legally obliged to pay attention to active citizenship and social integration since 1 February 2006. The government gives it to the schools themselves how to implement them. Article 8.3 Primary Education Act &amp;amp; Article 17 Secondary Education Act&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Wellink&lt;br&gt;NXT Generation&lt;br&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands</name></author><summary type="html">In April this year, I did a training course in Janeiro de Cima in Portugal. The course was organized by the Portuguese National Agency of Erasmus+ and, as a delegate from the Netherlands, I was given the opportunity by the Erasmus+ Youth National Agency to participate in this TC.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">De 3 Hs in FIRST LEGO League</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/05/13/De-3-Hs-in-FIRST-LEGO-League.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="De 3 Hs in FIRST LEGO League" /><published>2017-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/05/13/De-3-Hs-in-FIRST-LEGO-League</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/05/13/De-3-Hs-in-FIRST-LEGO-League.html">&lt;p&gt;In april dit jaar deed ik een trainers cursus in Janeiro de Cima in Portugal. De cursus werd georganiseerd door het Portugese Nationaal Agentschap van Erasmus+ en ik kreeg als afgevaardigde uit Nederland de kans van het Nationaal Agentschap Erasmus+ Jeugd om aan deze TC deel te nemen. 
Erasmus+ is het Europese subsidieprogramma voor onderwijs, jeugd en sport. Aan de basis staat de gedachte dat investeringen in onderwijs, opleidingen en niet-formeel leren van cruciaal belang zijn om mensen – ongeacht hun leeftijd of achtergrond – de kans te geven zich voortdurend te ontwikkelen oftewel: een leven lang te leren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/trophy.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tijdens de TC realiseerde ik mij wederom dat het First Lego League programma een geweldig programma  is waar jongeren de kans krijgen om kennis te maken met wetenschap en technologie op een non-formele manier. Het programma bereikt alle facetten van het leren zowel met het Hoofd als met het Hart en met de Handen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maar tijdens de training realiseerde ik mij ook dat er in dit programma veel focus ligt op het Hoofd en de Handen en jammer genoeg veel minder op  het Hart. Binnen het FLL programma ligt het accent bij het Hart met name op het teamwerk en de daaraan gekoppelde 7 Core Values. Maar daarmee laten we veel kansen onbenut. Het programma zou ook zaken als sociale integratie en gelijkwaardigheid (* actief burgerschap) kunnen bevorderen en de kansen kunnen vergroten voor leeftijdsgenoten die zich in kansarme achterstandssituaties bevinden. Deze jongeren worden benadeeld omdat ze kampen met persoonlijke problemen of belemmeringen die hun deelname aan projecten beperken of soms zelfs uitsluiten,  te denken valt aan:
 &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	Jongeren met een handicap of functiebeperking (specifieke behoefte) &lt;br /&gt;
•	Jongeren met leerproblemen, onderwijsmoeilijkheden &lt;br /&gt;
•	Jongeren met een lage levenstandaard en economische belemmeringen &lt;br /&gt;
•	Jongeren voor wie taalaanpassing of culturele integratie een probleem vormen, zoals migratie, vluchtelingen, expats &lt;br /&gt;
•	Jongeren met chronische beperkingen,  die ernstige ziek zijn of psychiatrische aandoening hebben &lt;br /&gt;
•	Jongeren die te maken hebben met discriminatie en sociale belemmeringen &lt;br /&gt;
•	Jongeren uit afgelegen of landelijke gebieden of stedelijke probleemwijken dus geografische belemmeringen &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Het programma zou ook zaken als meertaligheid kunnen bevorderen. 
Meertaligheid is een van de hoekstenen van het Europese project en tevens een krachtig symbool van het streven van de Europese Unie naar eenheid in verscheidenheid. De FLL community maakt het mogelijk contact te leggen met teams in heel Europa en de rest van de wereld. Ook door het  mee doen aan internationale toernooien, robotica kampen of uitwisselingen vergroten we de kans om teamleden vanaf jonge leeftijd in contact te laten komen met vreemde talen, waarmee we de dialoog tussen jongeren, het taalonderwijs en de  taalverscheidenheid kunnen bevorderen. Maar niet alleen ver weg ook in Nederland kan men in contact komen met anderstalige kinderen en culturen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Binnen het FLL programma en doormiddel van Core Values is het belang van persoonlijke ontwikkeling, respect en het delen van kennis al goed vertegenwoordigd, maar hier zou nog meer nadruk op mogen liggen. Iedereen verdient de mogelijkheid zich persoonlijk te ontplooien, een visie te ontwikkelen om de mogelijke beroepen te ontdekken en het leren  ten volle te benutten. Dit dient te gebeuren in een veilige omgeving waarbij iedereen wordt gerespecteerd en beschermd. Het is daarom naar mijn idee ook niet wenselijk of zelfs onmogelijk jongeren uit te sluiten van het FLL programma op grond van leerprestaties of anderzijds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En nu ik dit zo op papier zie kom ik tot de conclusie dat alles wat hier boven staat de belangrijkste elementen zijn van het Erasmus+ programma en dat dit naadloos past in het First Lego League programma. Sociale integratie en gelijkwaardigheid, meertaligheid, zelfontplooiing en veiligheid dit zijn allemaal elementen die prima in het Hart van de FLL passen en al een beetje zitten. Dus wat let ons om deze twee programma met elkaar te combineren en op die manier jongeren nog meer en betere kennis en vaardigheden mee te geven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mijn oproep aan alle FLL teams is daarom  om niet alleen de focus te leggen op het Hoofd en de Handen maar ook het Hart. Laat je daarbij niet beperken tot het team, het teamwork en de Core Values maar zoek het ook in de internationale dimensie en de mogelijkheden van actief burgerschap en burgerparticipatie. Hiermee maken we het FLL programma tot een totaal programma dat veel meer dekt dan STEM en waarbij veel meer te winnen valt dan een Award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/FLLlogo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nederlandse scholen voor primair en voorgezet onderwijs zijn sinds 1 februari 2006 wettelijk verplicht aandacht te besteden aan actief burgerschap en sociale integratie. De overheid laat het aan de scholen zelf over hoe ze daaraan invulling geven.
Artikel 8.3 Wet op het primair onderwijs &amp;amp; artikel 17 Wet op het voortgezet onderwijs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Wellink&lt;br&gt;NXT Generation&lt;br&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands</name></author><summary type="html">In april dit jaar deed ik een trainers cursus in Janeiro de Cima in Portugal. De cursus werd georganiseerd door het Portugese Nationaal Agentschap van Erasmus+ en ik kreeg als afgevaardigde uit Nederland de kans van het Nationaal Agentschap Erasmus+ Jeugd om aan deze TC deel te nemen. 
Erasmus+ is het Europese subsidieprogramma voor onderwijs, jeugd en sport. Aan de basis staat de gedachte dat investeringen in onderwijs, opleidingen en niet-formeel leren van cruciaal belang zijn om mensen – ongeacht hun leeftijd of achtergrond – de kans te geven zich voortdurend te ontwikkelen oftewel: een leven lang te leren.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">One Word</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/05/05/One-Word.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Word" /><published>2017-05-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/05/05/One-Word</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/05/05/One-Word.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/OneWord.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coming up with a team identity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making a decision quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large sheet of paper - Markers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
Provide teams with the materials&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
In the middle of the paper write one word that best describes your team. Decorate the rest of the page however you wish (with examples, quotes, colors, etc.). You have 5 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;
This activity is designed to help teams think about their team identity. At the end of 5 minutes, have the team present their poster and explain their choices. You might do this same activity twice in the season (once at the beginning and once at the end) to see if the team perceives itself differently.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Day in the Life of a Coach - Starting a Team</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/04/07/Starting-a-Team.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Day in the Life of a Coach - Starting a Team" /><published>2017-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/04/07/Starting-a-Team</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/04/07/Starting-a-Team.html">&lt;p&gt;I will be writing a few articles in this series. This is the first of them. It is based on my experiences and I think all parents who are coaches/ assistant coaches/mentors or just parents of kids participating in FLL can relate to various points here. Please contribute and add more points to this to make the journey of FLL easier, more fulfilling and more rewarding for kids and parents alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/RobotsandKids.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here comes the team registration day. Here are my thoughts on creating a good, balanced team this year.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team Size:&lt;/b&gt; I found that a team size of four/five is good. Not too small; they all will have enough work to do with not much pressure on any one of them. Not too big either, else it would have been a nightmare managing all of their schedules and finding a time that suits all for weekly team meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Proximity:&lt;/b&gt; It’s good they all live in same neighborhood and go to same school. They all like to play basketball too. The team will bond well. I can have some friendly basketball matches in between to help them relax and focus. I should probably look for the next Warriors game tickets too. All the families can go together, it will be a good time to enjoy as a team, the whole team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;First Steps:&lt;/b&gt; Team and parents are coming for the meeting in the evening. I will let kids come up with the team name and may be a logo as well. I should make a google group with parents and kids so that everyone can share ideas and we can decide about team meetings. Let me gather all the information I have till now so that we can see it and discuss about it when we meet. I am so excited, hope the kids are too.
&lt;br /&gt;
It is going to be a hectic yet fun season.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twelve-tips-to-ensure-you-have-a-smooth-start-to-your-season&quot;&gt;Twelve tips to ensure you have a smooth start to your season:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Make sure you are registered in VIMS and have a background check if you want to be a coach/ assistant coach/ mentor. (You will need two coaches per team.)&lt;br /&gt;
2) You need not have an exact team when you register, but it is always better if you can figure out the team members before that.  (You can add or remove members any time.) &lt;br /&gt;
3) You need to give the Team’s name and Location when you register. If the kids involved come up with that name, then they do relate better with their team entity. Team name can be anything from the game they like to the food they enjoy, the project they will like to work on or just about anything they all can agree on. (The team name can be changed later.) &lt;br /&gt;
4) It is always good to register a team early than late. Kids can acquire some building and programming skills during summer breaks. They can explore more about the theme and project for the season too. You can also order your Challenge mat in the summer if you register early. Even if you do not know the challenge, your team will have time to build the mission models in advance.&lt;br /&gt;
5) Keep all the parents informed and involved in respect to what they might have to do (construct the table, manage their kids’ activities and FLL schedule, bring a snack on team meetings day, organize a field trip etc.). Most of all be supportive and enthusiastic for the kids.&lt;br /&gt;
6) Make a google group/ yahoo group with all kids and parents as members so as to coordinate better during the season.&lt;br /&gt;
7) It is a good idea to have a shared drive (like google drive) to share all the relevant documents, programs at one place. &lt;br /&gt;
8) You can also put an excel sheet in that drive for all the shared expenses incurred by various parents during the season. You might use apps like splitwise for that too if everyone has an access to it.&lt;br /&gt;
9) Come up with a fixed day(s) and time in a week when everyone is present for the team meeting. &lt;br /&gt;
10) It is a good time to go over and discuss all the information you have regarding the season till then. &lt;br /&gt; 
11) Discuss the possible field trips for the team with kids and parents.&lt;br /&gt;
12) Give some time for the team members to enjoy, play and talk to each other besides robotics. It goes a long way in team bonding. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swati Mittal&lt;br&gt;Robotics &amp; Kids&lt;br&gt;USA</name></author><summary type="html">I will be writing a few articles in this series. This is the first of them. It is based on my experiences and I think all parents who are coaches/ assistant coaches/mentors or just parents of kids participating in FLL can relate to various points here. Please contribute and add more points to this to make the journey of FLL easier, more fulfilling and more rewarding for kids and parents alike.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry></feed>
