<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-05-13T14:39:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Coach’s Corner</title><subtitle>I am the founder of EV3Lessons</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Day in the Life of a Coach - Starting a Team</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/04/07/Starting-a-Team.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Day in the Life of a Coach - Starting a Team" /><published>2017-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/04/07/Starting-a-Team</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/04/07/Starting-a-Team.html">&lt;p&gt;I will be writing a few articles in this series. This is the first of them. It is based on my experiences and I think all parents who are coaches/ assistant coaches/mentors or just parents of kids participating in FLL can relate to various points here. Please contribute and add more points to this to make the journey of FLL easier, more fulfilling and more rewarding for kids and parents alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/RobotsandKids.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here comes the team registration day. Here are my thoughts on creating a good, balanced team this year.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team Size:&lt;/b&gt; I found that a team size of four/five is good. Not too small; they all will have enough work to do with not much pressure on any one of them. Not too big either, else it would have been a nightmare managing all of their schedules and finding a time that suits all for weekly team meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Proximity:&lt;/b&gt; It’s good they all live in same neighborhood and go to same school. They all like to play basketball too. The team will bond well. I can have some friendly basketball matches in between to help them relax and focus. I should probably look for the next Warriors game tickets too. All the families can go together, it will be a good time to enjoy as a team, the whole team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;First Steps:&lt;/b&gt; Team and parents are coming for the meeting in the evening. I will let kids come up with the team name and may be a logo as well. I should make a google group with parents and kids so that everyone can share ideas and we can decide about team meetings. Let me gather all the information I have till now so that we can see it and discuss about it when we meet. I am so excited, hope the kids are too.
&lt;br /&gt;
It is going to be a hectic yet fun season.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twelve-tips-to-ensure-you-have-a-smooth-start-to-your-season&quot;&gt;Twelve tips to ensure you have a smooth start to your season:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Make sure you are registered in VIMS and have a background check if you want to be a coach/ assistant coach/ mentor. (You will need two coaches per team.)&lt;br /&gt;
2) You need not have an exact team when you register, but it is always better if you can figure out the team members before that.  (You can add or remove members any time.) &lt;br /&gt;
3) You need to give the Team’s name and Location when you register. If the kids involved come up with that name, then they do relate better with their team entity. Team name can be anything from the game they like to the food they enjoy, the project they will like to work on or just about anything they all can agree on. (The team name can be changed later.) &lt;br /&gt;
4) It is always good to register a team early than late. Kids can acquire some building and programming skills during summer breaks. They can explore more about the theme and project for the season too. You can also order your Challenge mat in the summer if you register early. Even if you do not know the challenge, your team will have time to build the mission models in advance.&lt;br /&gt;
5) Keep all the parents informed and involved in respect to what they might have to do (construct the table, manage their kids’ activities and FLL schedule, bring a snack on team meetings day, organize a field trip etc.). Most of all be supportive and enthusiastic for the kids.&lt;br /&gt;
6) Make a google group/ yahoo group with all kids and parents as members so as to coordinate better during the season.&lt;br /&gt;
7) It is a good idea to have a shared drive (like google drive) to share all the relevant documents, programs at one place. &lt;br /&gt;
8) You can also put an excel sheet in that drive for all the shared expenses incurred by various parents during the season. You might use apps like splitwise for that too if everyone has an access to it.&lt;br /&gt;
9) Come up with a fixed day(s) and time in a week when everyone is present for the team meeting. &lt;br /&gt;
10) It is a good time to go over and discuss all the information you have regarding the season till then. &lt;br /&gt; 
11) Discuss the possible field trips for the team with kids and parents.&lt;br /&gt;
12) Give some time for the team members to enjoy, play and talk to each other besides robotics. It goes a long way in team bonding. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swati Mittal&lt;br&gt;Robotics &amp; Kids&lt;br&gt;USA</name></author><summary type="html">I will be writing a few articles in this series. This is the first of them. It is based on my experiences and I think all parents who are coaches/ assistant coaches/mentors or just parents of kids participating in FLL can relate to various points here. Please contribute and add more points to this to make the journey of FLL easier, more fulfilling and more rewarding for kids and parents alike.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">EV3Lessons - Recommendation List</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/02/22/Recommendation-List.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EV3Lessons - Recommendation List" /><published>2017-02-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/02/22/Recommendation-List</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/02/22/Recommendation-List.html">&lt;p&gt;As most of you know, we are the founders of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ev3lessons.com&quot;&gt;EV3Lessons&lt;/a&gt;. While we have a lot of resources on our site, we don’t have everything. There are lots of good resources around. We thought we would share resources other than on our own site that we think will be helpful to others. While the list is not an endorsement of any one resource over the other, we did make sure that every resource reflects our own mission and philosophy to teach without providing solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main criteria for selection was the following:&lt;br /&gt;
1) Focus: Resources must not focus on winning competitions and shortcuts to success, but on learning the concepts and inspiring.&lt;br /&gt;
2) Completeness: Resources must be somewhat organized and comprehensive &lt;br /&gt;
3) Educators: Resources that focus on educators must be included&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also other alternative lists you are welcome to refer to: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.damienkee.com/lego-mindstorms-resources/&quot;&gt;Damien Kee&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://stemrobotics.cs.pdx.edu/node/2837&quot;&gt; STEMRobotics&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legoengineering.com/online-training-courses/&quot;&gt;Lego Engineering&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will update this guide as we find and review resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Resources.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;free-curriculum-by-lego-education&quot;&gt;Free Curriculum by LEGO Education&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://education.lego.com/en-us/downloads/mindstorms-ev3&quot;&gt;LEGO Education&lt;/a&gt;: Various curriculum resources created by LEGO Education&lt;br /&gt;
Also look at the built-in lessons in the EV3 Programming Software you installed on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;free-introductory-curriculum&quot;&gt;Free Introductory Curriculum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.education.rec.ri.cmu.edu/content/lego/ev3/&quot;&gt;CMU Robotics Academy &lt;/a&gt;: Complete introductory curriculum for the EV3&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stemcentric.com/ev3-tutorial&quot;&gt;STEMCentric&lt;/a&gt;: Mostly introductory-level with a few intermediate-level topics.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wafflesrobotics.com/fll/fll-resources/&quot;&gt;WAFFLES Community Robotics&lt;/a&gt;: Comprehensive block by block introduction to programming by a FIRST team in Canada. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://stemrobotics.cs.pdx.edu/node/2643&quot;&gt;STEMRobotics&lt;/a&gt;: Organized repository for educational materials and curriculum guides for MINDSTORMS instructors by Portland State University.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legoengineering.com&quot;&gt;LEGOEngineering&lt;/a&gt;: A wide range of resources and support materials specifically for educators organized by Tufts CEEO. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;organization-and-planning-resources-for-fll-teams&quot;&gt;Organization and Planning Resources for FLL Teams&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.techbrick.com&quot;&gt;Techbrick&lt;/a&gt;: Has worksheets, images and blank templates for use by teams. Resources are updated every season. Information from previous seasons are archived so if you need access to materials from older challenges, you can find them here.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ev3lessons.com&quot;&gt;EV3Lessons&lt;/a&gt;: Has mission planning worksheets, calculators and tools for teams. The site hosts several online/interactive tools such as a Sketcher for teams to map out missions. Resources are updated every season.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-lego-league-curriculum-and-tips&quot;&gt;FIRST LEGO League Curriculum and Tips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fllblog.wordpress.com/2016/07/25/taking-your-first-steps/&quot;&gt;FIRST Steps&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3lessons.com/corevalues.html&quot;&gt;Team Building Activities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3lessons.com/coachcorner.html&quot;&gt;Coach’s Corner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3lessons.com/resources.html&quot;&gt;Current Season Planning Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;robotics-resources-for-scouts&quot;&gt;Robotics Resources for Scouts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scouting.org/filestore/Merit_Badge_ReqandRes/Robotics.pdf&quot;&gt;Robotics Merit Badge Requirements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cs2n.org/activities/courses/robot-virtual-worlds-boy-scout-robotics-merit-badge&quot;&gt;Robot Virtual Worlds Boy Scout Robotics Merit Badge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mindstorms-related-forums-and-facebook-groups&quot;&gt;MINDSTORMS-Related Forums and Facebook Groups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://forums.usfirst.org/forumdisplay.php?24-FIRST-LEGO-League&quot;&gt;FIRST LEGO League Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://listserv.jmu.edu/cgi-bin/wa?A0=VADCFLL-L&quot;&gt;VA-DC FIRST LEGO League Listserv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://community.education.lego.com/&quot;&gt;LEGO Education Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/legomindstorms/&quot;&gt;LEGO MINDSTORMS Facebook Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL Share and Learn Facebook Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stores-to-buy-additional-lego-or-mindstorms-parts&quot;&gt;Stores to buy additional LEGO or MINDSTORMS parts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lego.com&quot;&gt;LEGO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legoeducation.com&quot;&gt;LEGO Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.Bricklink.com&quot;&gt;Bricklink&lt;/a&gt;: For purchasing specific parts and complete sets&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.Brickowl.com&quot;&gt;Brickowl&lt;/a&gt;: For purchasing specific parts and complete sets&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mindsensors.com&quot;&gt;Mindsensors&lt;/a&gt;: For non-LEGO branded sensors that are compatible with the EV3&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hitechnic.com&quot;&gt;HiTechnic&lt;/a&gt;: For non-LEGO branded sensors that are compatible with the EV3&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;technic-and-mindstorms-books&quot;&gt;TECHNIC and MINDSTORMS Books&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benedettelli, Daniele. The LEGO MINDSTORMS EV3 Laboratory&lt;br /&gt;
Isogawa, Yoshihito. The LEGO MINDSTORMS EV3 Idea Book&lt;br /&gt;
Isogawa, Yoshihito. The LEGO Technic Idea Book&lt;br /&gt;
Kmiec, Pawel. The Unofficial LEGO Technic Builder’s Guide&lt;br /&gt;
Valk, Laurens. The LEGO MINDSTORMS EV3 Discovery Book&lt;br /&gt;
Kee, Damien. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.damienkee.com/classroom-activities-ev3/&quot;&gt;Classroom Activities for the Busy Teacher: EV3&lt;/a&gt;. Also includes worksheets and challenges.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;challengesprojects-for-ideas-and-inspiration&quot;&gt;Challenges/Projects for Ideas and Inspiration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theNXTstep.com&quot;&gt;The NXT Step&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mindstorms.dreschallenges.com/&quot;&gt;Dr. E’s Challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.drgraeme.org/EV3/EV3.html&quot;&gt;Dr. Graeme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nxtprograms.com&quot;&gt;NXT Projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.damienkee.com/&quot;&gt;Dr. Damien Kee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ev3dev.org/&quot;&gt;EV3Dev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mindstorms-competitions-available-to-schools&quot;&gt;MINDSTORMS Competitions available to schools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.firstlegolegue.org&quot;&gt;FIRST LEGO League&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wroboto.org&quot;&gt;World Robot Olympiad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA</name></author><summary type="html">As most of you know, we are the founders of EV3Lessons. While we have a lot of resources on our site, we don’t have everything. There are lots of good resources around. We thought we would share resources other than on our own site that we think will be helpful to others. While the list is not an endorsement of any one resource over the other, we did make sure that every resource reflects our own mission and philosophy to teach without providing solutions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">NXT and EV3 - Working Together</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/02/15/NXT-and-EV3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NXT and EV3 - Working Together" /><published>2017-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/02/15/NXT-and-EV3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/02/15/NXT-and-EV3.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Blocks.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ev3-or-nxt&quot;&gt;EV3 or NXT?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often get asked if an NXT can be used in competition. Yes, it can be used for both for FIRST LEGO League and World Robot Olympiad. If you have a choice or just starting as a team, it is probably best to purchase an EV3. The last version of the NXT came out in 2009.  The EV3 came out in 2013.  NXTs are no longer sold by LEGO. The EV3 is the most recent and most up-to-date version of MINDSTORMS available.  However, if you have an NXT, there is no reason to scrap it. While we don’t use it for competition ourselves, there are many projects where we still use an NXT or NXT parts, and there are a few teams that still use the NXT in competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the EV3 is a noticeable evolution of the NXT. The Programmable Brick (pBrick) runs Linux, has a better processor, allows the user to connect 4 motors, has a micro SD card slot and a USB port. The SD card slot allows you to expand upon the existing memory and run ev3dev. The USB slot allows the user to daisy chain up to four EV3 bricks together, allowing you build interesting robots with more sensors and motors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-the-nxt-brick-with-ev3-software&quot;&gt;Using the NXT brick with EV3 software&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have used NXT bricks programmed with EV3 software in workshops with success, but did discover some limitations that are worth mentioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Space is a challenge - the NXT has very little storage and a few programs with the new software fill it up &lt;b&gt;very&lt;/b&gt; quickly.&lt;br /&gt;
2) Some blocks don’t work as advertised. For example, Move Steering/Move Tank blocks don’t synchronize motors well, therefore, making turns difficult. &lt;br /&gt;
3) Some EV3 Programming blocks will not work on the NXT Brick (see table below),&lt;br /&gt;
4) Bluetooth with NXT to PC does not work. &lt;br /&gt;
5) Many EV3 programming blocks do not work on an NXT (see table below and image at the top of this post). &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Programming Block&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;NXT Brick running EV3 Software&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Display&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes &lt;br /&gt;(Images may not fit)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Math - Exponents&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Advanced Math&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Datalogging&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Invert Motor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Gyro Sensor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Brick Light Status&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Messaging&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bluetooth Connection&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Medium Motor Block&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No &lt;br /&gt;(Use Large Motor Block)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-nxt-peripherals-sensors-and-motors-with-the-ev3-brick&quot;&gt;Using NXT peripherals (sensors and motors) with the EV3 brick&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have experimented with using NXT peripherals on the EV3 brick. The Color Sensor and the Temperature Sensor work well with the EV3. However, there are some limitations when using other parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Auto recognition is limited - sometimes, the EV3 brick does not automatically recognize when an NXT part is connected &lt;br /&gt;
2) Sensor support is limited - you need to deal with issues such as light level calibration on your own. Some sensors use odd interfaces (e.g. To use a NXT Light sensor uses the sound block). &lt;br /&gt;
3) The NXT color sensor is not as accurate as the EV3 color sensor &lt;br /&gt;
4) To use the NXT Light Sensor in the EV3 Software, you will have to program using the Sound sensor block (use dB for reflected light and dBa for ambient light) &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Part&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;EV3 Brick &amp;amp; Software&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;NXT with EV3 Software&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EV3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Large and Medium Motors&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes &lt;br /&gt;(Use Large Motor Block to control Medium Motor)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EV3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Touch, Color, IR, Ultrasonic, Gyro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;NXT&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Motor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;NXT&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Touch, Color, Light, Ultrasonic, Temperature, Sound&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes &lt;br /&gt;(Light sensor as Color)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes &lt;br /&gt;(Light sensor as Sound)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Dozen Off-Season Ideas</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/01/27/A-Dozen-Off-Season-Ideas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Dozen Off-Season Ideas" /><published>2017-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/01/27/A-Dozen-Off-Season-Ideas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/01/27/A-Dozen-Off-Season-Ideas.html">&lt;p&gt;What can your team do in the off-season?  There is so much you CAN do….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Offseason.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-learn-a-new-programming-skill&quot;&gt;1) Learn a new	programming	skill&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps your team did not use sensors or did not use a particular sensor.  Use the off-season to learn how to use those sensors.  Or maybe you didn’t use any My Blocks. Use the FLL mat to test them out. Have you finished all the lessons on EV3Lessons.com?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-complete-more-missions&quot;&gt;2) Complete more missions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did your team not get time to complete all the missions?  Use the off-season to work on the missions some more.  You can come up with different ways of solving the missions as well. Since you would have attended several events, you might be inspired to try something new. Have an internal contest at the end of three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-purchase-an-old-fll-kit-or-register-for-the-fll-offseason&quot;&gt;3) Purchase an old FLL kit or register for the FLL offseason&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are bored of this year’s mat and missions, look on eBay or elsewhere for a previous year’s “Field Set up Kit”/Challenge”.  An experienced team might either sell or lend you an old kit. Old mats make brand new missions and can teach new skills (like colored line following)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FIRST LEGO League also launched an official off-season where teams can register and purchase the current year’s challenge and complete them at their own pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-practice-programming-skills&quot;&gt;4) Practice programming skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have the best programmer on the team write up code.  Have the rest of the team explain what the code does and how they could improve it.  Have small challenges such as “who can write the best line follower”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-practice-building-skills&quot;&gt;5) Practice building skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe your team did not use any gears or rubber bands.  Try to build small mechanisms. Or build a Technic set that might have interesting gearing that you can learn from. There are really good LEGO building books you can look at too by Yoshohito Isogawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-do-outreach&quot;&gt;6) Do outreach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have more time now to host an Open House or demo at your practice location or the library. You can simply demo your FLL robot on an FLL mat or you can even run workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Outreach.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-think-about-the-research-topic&quot;&gt;7) Think about the research topic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although you don’t know the topic, you know the broad category (senior citizens, trash, water, etc).  Look up some information about the broad category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-participate-in-an-off-season-event&quot;&gt;8) Participate in an Off-season event&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check with your local Operational Partner if there is an off-season event teams can participate in.  Or you can even organize one yourself. Local FRC teams might be willing to host one. You might even attend an Open Invitational or World Festival event as a guest for inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;9-invite-an-experienced-team-over&quot;&gt;9) Invite an experienced team over&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want feedback and ideas, invite a experienced local team to a team meeting.  Experienced teams can often be good mentors for a team all year round. Share your work and see what feedback they have to give you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;10-go-online&quot;&gt;10) Go online!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How about making the team a website or Facebook/Twitter pages? Many FIRST teams have websites and social media sites to connect with other teams and with FIRST. You can use it to collect survey data, share you work with others, and even participate in FLL Twitter Chats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;11-try-another-lego-robotics-tournament&quot;&gt;11) Try another LEGO robotics tournament&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many states and countries off other LEGO robotics programs that will enhance your FIRST LEGO League skills. Some areas offer Robot Sumo, Robocup and World Robot Olympiad. These do not usually conflict with FIRST LEGO League and still use LEGO MINDSTORMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;12-build-something-completely-new&quot;&gt;12) Build something completely new&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often times building and programming a robot for fun results in learning new skills. Can you convert your EV3 into an musical instrument, a printer, etc? Visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/MINDSTORMSMAGIC&quot;&gt;MINDSTORMS Magic page &lt;/a&gt; for many ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA</name></author><summary type="html">What can your team do in the off-season?  There is so much you CAN do….</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Home vs Education Edition</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/01/17/Home-vs-Edu.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Home vs Education Edition" /><published>2017-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/01/17/Home-vs-Edu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/01/17/Home-vs-Edu.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most common questions we receive is about the difference between the three MINDSTORMS sets available to FIRST LEGO League teams: &lt;b&gt;Home Edition&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;Education Edition&lt;/b&gt;, and the &lt;b&gt;FIRST LEGO League Bundle edition&lt;/b&gt;. We decided to put together a comparison sheet to help coaches decide what to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Versions.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;three-mindstorms-options-for-teams&quot;&gt;Three MINDSTORMS options for teams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three different versions of the MINDSTORMS set you can buy for your team. As you look through the table below, notice that the retail set has a sensor not permitted in FIRST LEGO League (infrared, IR beacon) and the Edu and FLL versions do come with a rechargeable battery, gyro and ultrasonic sensors that teams find useful. The versions also have slightly different LEGO elements in them (e.g. slightly larger wheels and a ball wheel in the Edu edition, but a ball shooter, balls, and many decorative elements in the retail edition.)  Under the “Useful Links” section below, you can find a nice comparison tool that displays what parts are in each set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also remember that in FIRST LEGO League, you can use LEGO elements beyond these three sets. All LEGO-branded elements (including motors, sensors, rubberbands, etc.) are permitted. However, you are not allowed to use the infrared sensor and the infrared beacon.  You are allowed to use LEGO elements in any Technic and LEGO sets you may own. However, you are not allowed to use Power Functions motors, windup LEGO elements, and the NXT sound sensor.  FIRST LEGO League also permits 4 motors (but only 3 come in any one set).  Therefore, keep in mind what other parts you might want to purchase for your team beyond these basic sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;all-versions-are-compatible&quot;&gt;All versions are compatible&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single biggest mistake people make is assuming that the sets and the software are very different. They are not. You are NOT limited or restricted because of the set you start with.  All components in the sets are interchangable and you can very easily purchase additional parts. The software between the sets is identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can purchase parts not in one set (e.g. charger, battery, sensors) seperately from LEGO.com, LEGOEducation.com, Bricklink, etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can change the firmware on the brick from one edition (Home or Edu) to the other. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can change the software from one edition to the other (Home or Edu) on the computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Useful Links:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To &lt;b&gt;convert one set to the other&lt;/b&gt;, use this useful &lt;a href=&quot;http://rebrickable.com/compare/31313-1/45544-1&quot;&gt; Comparison Chart by Rebrickable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To download the &lt;b&gt;Retail Software&lt;/b&gt; visit the&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lego.com/en-us/mindstorms/downloads/&quot;&gt; Retail Version Downloads Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To view the &lt;b&gt;Retail Robot Builds&lt;/b&gt; (5 main models + 12 bonus) visit the&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lego.com/en-us/mindstorms/build-a-robot&quot;&gt; Build a Robot Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To download the &lt;b&gt;Education Software&lt;/b&gt; visit the&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lego.com/en-us/mindstorms/downloads/&quot;&gt; Edu Version Downloads Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To view the &lt;b&gt;Education Robot Builds&lt;/b&gt; (5 main models + 6 expansion models), go to “Model Instructions” inside your Edu version of the software&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To install the &lt;b&gt;Retail or Education Firmware&lt;/b&gt; on the brick, go to Tools –&amp;gt; Firmware Update inside the EV3 programming software you installed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To install the &lt;b&gt;programming blocks for any new LEGO sensors you add&lt;/b&gt; (Gyro, Ultrasonic, Temperature, Sound…), visit the&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lego.com/en-us/mindstorms/downloads/&quot;&gt; Retail Version Downloads Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;comparison-table&quot;&gt;Comparison Table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Education Set&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;FLL Bundle&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Retail Set&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Availability&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Legoeducation.com&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Purchased as part of team registraion&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Lego.com and other retailers&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cost&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Core Set (5003400): $389.95 Expansion Set (45560): $101.95&lt;br /&gt; Software: Free and downloadable&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;FLL Bundle includes Edu Core and Expansion Sets: US $439&lt;br /&gt;  Software: Free and downloadable&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Retail Set (31313): $349.99 Software: Free and downloadable&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brick Firmware&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Edu Edition&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Edu Edition&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Home Edition (does not include on-brick datalogging)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Programming Software&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;EV3-G Edu Edition&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;EV3-G Edu Edition&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;EV3-G Home Edition&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Programming Tutorials&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;General EV3 programming tutorials included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;General EV3 programming tutorials included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;EV3 programming tutorials for specific missions related to each build&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Build Instructions&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5 models (EV3 Core Base, GyroBoy, Color Sorter, Puppy, Robot Arm) plus Expansion Set models&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5 models (EV3 Core Base, GyroBoy, Color Sorter, Puppy, Robot Arm) plus Expansion Set models&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5 models (TRACK3R, SPIK3R, EV3RSTORM, R3PTAR, GRIPP3R) plus bonus models&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sensor Support&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Built-in blocks/support for all LEGO manufactured sensors preinstalled.  Third-party sensor support can be downloaded&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Built-in blocks/support for all LEGO manufactured sensors preinstalled.  Third-party sensor support can be downloaded&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Supports all sensors. You will need to download the blocks for the Ultrasonic and Gyro sensors from the downloads page.  Third-party sensor support can be downloaded&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;App Version&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;For IOS/ChromeOS only&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;For IOS/ChromeOS only&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;For IOS/Android only&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Other&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Includes rechargeable battery and charger, includes ultrasonic and gyro sensors&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Includes rechargeable battery and charger, includes ultrasonic and gyro sensors&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Does not include rechargeable battery and charger&lt;br /&gt; Does not include ultrasonic and gyro&lt;br /&gt;  Includes infrared and infrared beacon&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prices and information are accurate as of January 27, 2017. If you see any errors, please email team@ev3lessons.com with corrections. Prices are in US Dollars and taken from the FIRST LEGO League, LEGO.com and LEGOEducation websites. They are subject to change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA</name></author><summary type="html">One of the most common questions we receive is about the difference between the three MINDSTORMS sets available to FIRST LEGO League teams: Home Edition, Education Edition, and the FIRST LEGO League Bundle edition. We decided to put together a comparison sheet to help coaches decide what to buy.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Coach’s Role During the Robot Game</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/01/09/Coach-s-Role-During-the-Robot-Game.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coach's Role During the Robot Game" /><published>2017-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/01/09/Coach%60s-Role-During-the-Robot-Game</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/01/09/Coach-s-Role-During-the-Robot-Game.html">&lt;p&gt;After six years of competing in FIRST LEGO League, my family had the opportunity to take in a state-level tournament from the other side. In particular, we helped to referee the robot game.  There are many observations and lessons that I hope will help other teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/ref.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;let-the-children-speak-for-themselves&quot;&gt;Let the children speak for themselves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is best illustrated through an example. Unfortunately, at our event, the exit path went behind tables while games were still in progress. The volunteer staff did their best to keep the aisle clear for the matches. Occasionally, there was a mishap and an exiting team passed right behind two robot operators. After one particular match, an upset adult walked into the game area and complained that his team should get a do-over because they were bumped from the back. The team was actually still signing off with their table referee at the time when the adult jumped in.  I said I would talk to the team. Before the team left, I went over and asked the kids on the team if they were bumped during the run and if it impacted them or their robot in any way.  All the kids unanimously said, “No”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parents and coaches, let the kids decide if something bothered them before stepping in. The referees always give the kids the benefit of the doubt and will do their best to rectify the situation. So, coaches, sit back, relax and enjoy the show. Let the kids talk to the referees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;listen-to-the-children&quot;&gt;Listen to the Children&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the team has issues with one of the mission models and wants to contest the scoring by the referee, all they have to do is politely ask to talk to the Head Referee who will rule consistently across all tables at a tournament. Accept the ruling given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, the referee can operate the model by hand to check to see if it is working correctly. There have certainly been cases when the model did not work (even by hand) and and my team was given the points. However, in majority of cases where the model works by hand, it just means the team’s solution was not robust enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, we witnessed several instances when adults on the team began arguing for points with the table referee and the head referee. Amusingly, kids on the team had to console the adult, saying, “Coach, let it go.” You know when the kids are calming the coach down that the coach is taking the event much too seriously. This reflects poorly on the team. I hope all team members have the guts to tell their coaches when they are too involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;let-the-children-make-decisions&quot;&gt;Let the children make decisions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FIRST is about the children making the decisions.  It is alarming to see the number of teams that look to their coaches (or walk up to their coaches) in the middle of the run when things don’t go right. We have even seen coaches yell out instructions to the team members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Droids have never looked at me in six years of competing. They make their own decisions to run a mission or re-run a mission.  In fact, they appear so calm and in sync that table referees and resetters have made comments to me about how independent they are. Making their own decision during tense moments is all part of the program. Let the team decide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coachs-role-during-the-robot-game&quot;&gt;Coach’s role during the robot game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what is the coach’s role?  Let them know when and where they need to be.  Take photos and video. Be the first to congratulate. Be the loudest to cheer regardless of how the run went. Be their supporter, but not the decision maker.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Asha Seshan&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA</name></author><summary type="html">After six years of competing in FIRST LEGO League, my family had the opportunity to take in a state-level tournament from the other side. In particular, we helped to referee the robot game.  There are many observations and lessons that I hope will help other teams.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIRST ®: link tussen formeel, non-formeel en informeel leren</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/27/FIRST-link-tussen-formeel,-non-formeel-en-informeel-leren.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIRST ®: link tussen formeel, non-formeel en informeel leren" /><published>2016-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/27/FIRST---link-tussen-formeel,-non-formeel-en-informeel-leren</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/27/FIRST-link-tussen-formeel,-non-formeel-en-informeel-leren.html">&lt;p&gt;Er zijn veel verschillende manieren om te leren. Als docent en coach van een FIRST® LEGO® League (FLL®) team heb ik dit de afgelopen jaren gezien en ervaren. Ook binnen het FIRST programma wordt op verschillende manieren geleerd. Niet op de laatste plaats omdat er wereldwijd veel verschillende team samenstellingen zijn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/NXTGeneration.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zo zijn er teams die worden gevormd binnen scoutinggroepen, techniekclubs, jeugdwerk (zoals Dynamo) en vrijwilligers organisatie (zoals het Groendomein Wasven). Of binnen het onderwijs zoals, basis- en middelbare scholen, naschoolse opvang of zoals in Amerika bij “home schools”. Toen ik mij ging verdiepen in de samenstelling van deze teams viel het mij op dat een aantal teams een gemeenschappelijke deler hadden namelijk: teams die een heterogene samenstelling hebben qua leeftijd, niveau en belangstelling halen vaak meer uit het programma dan teams met een homogene samenstelling. Dit komt naar mijn idee omdat de teamleden met en van elkaar leren en vaker op een informelere manier leren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zoals ik in de inleiding al stelde zijn er veel verschillende manieren van leren. Volgens “van den Dungen &amp;amp; Smit, 2010”  kan men leren onderverdelen in drie verschillende vormen, namelijk: Formeel leren, Non of niet- formeel leren en informeel leren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De termen, formeel, non-formeel en informeel leren worden gebruikt door de OESO (Organisatie voor Economische Samenwerking en Ontwikkeling), evenals onderzoekers en praktijkmensen over de hele wereld.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Formeel leren&lt;/b&gt; is georganiseerd leren dat wettelijk gereglementeerd is en voldoet aan kwaliteitseisen met vaste doelen en eisen. Het kan worden afgesloten met een landelijk erkend diploma of certificaat. De lessen worden gegeven door professionals die een hiervoor een opleiding hebben gevolgd. Een voorbeeld hiervan is het basis– en middelbaar onderwijs, MBO , HBO en Universiteit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Non of niet- formeel leren&lt;/b&gt; is min of meer georganiseerd en kan,  maar hoeft niet te passen in een  programma.  Deze manier van leren kan worden geleid door een gekwalificeerde leraar of door een begeleider met meer ervaring. Hoewel het programma vaak niet leidt tot een normering, certificering of diploma is het programma zeer verrijkend en leert de leerling individuele vaardigheden en competenties. Scouting of sportgroepen zijn hier een mooi voorbeeld van. Bij het non-formeel leren is enthousiasme, plezier en intrinsieke motivatie vaak de drijvende kracht achter de deelname.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Informeel leren staat&lt;/b&gt; voor leren dat doorgaans niet georganiseerd plaatsvindt. Het kan altijd en overal plaatsvinden in situaties in het gezin, op het werk, tijdens de vrije tijd en in de samenleving. We leren nu eenmaal veel en vaak in de praktijk, dit gaat spontaan en toevallig en veelal ook nog eens met anderen. We kijken af, vragen hulp, krijgen feedback. Informeel leren wordt steeds meer gezien als een belangrijke manier van professionaliseren naast formeel en non-formeel leren. De leraar is gewoon iemand met meer ervaring, zoals een ouder, grootouder of een vriend. Vanuit het standpunt van de leerling is dit leren in ieder geval, niet-doelgericht. De leeropbrengsten worden niet vastgelegd en zijn meestal niet direct zichtbaar voor de leerling. Een voorbeeld van informeel leren is een vader die zijn kind leert vissen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Het FLL programma zit naar mijn idee tussen het non-formeel en het informeel leren in. Het programma zelf is meer non-formeel omdat het ontwikkeld is door FIRST en in een min of meer georganiseerde setting wordt uitgevoerd.  Met het FLL programma ontwikkelen kinderen kennis en vaardigheden maar ook andere competenties zoals sociale aspecten. De teams zijn vaak tijdelijk samengesteld en worden begeleidt door een gekwalificeerde leraar of door een begeleider met meer ervaring (zoals een jeugdleider, vrijwilliger of ouder). De FLL activiteiten worden gepland maar zijn niet altijd gestructureerd met conventionele tijdsindelingen of leervakken. Deelname aan het programma is over het algemeen vrijwillig. De setting is vaak ook anders, niet de klassikale schoolse setting, maar meer informeel.  Ook worden de leeropbrengsten niet geregistreerd, gemeten of beoordeeld.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naar mate het programma verder wordt gevolgd gaan de leerlingen steeds meer informeel leren. Ze vragen hulp aan experts en deskundige uit het veld, gaan op excursie of op onderzoek uit en leren spontaan en toevallig van en met elkaar. Ze werken samen, zorgen voor elkaar en kijken met andere ogen naar hun omgeving. Ze worden assertiever, leren omgaan met tegenslagen en meningen van anderen. Leggen contacten, vergroten hun doorzettingsvermogen en ontwikkelen aandacht voor non-verbaal gedrag. Tevens gaan ze er vaker in hun vrije tijd op uit om achter zaken aan te gaan, dingen te regelen of te organiseren. Maar bovenal hebben ze het gezellig en beleven ze plezier aan datgene waarmee ze bezig zijn. De begeleider is in deze fase dan vaak alleen nog maar een toeschouwer, iemand die faciliteert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Als coach kreeg ik vaak als feedback terug dat ouders dankbaar waren dat hun kinderen hadden deelgenomen aan de FLL. Ook de kinderen zelf waren blij dat ze in een FLL team hadden gezeten. Ze gaven daarbij aan dat ze het fantastisch hadden gevonden dat ze kennis hadden gemaakt met techniek en wetenschap. Dat ze blij zijn dat ze nu weten hoe ze een robot moeten bouwen en programmeren en dat ze meer ruimtelijk inzicht hebben gekregen. Ook vonden ze het geweldig dat ze meer te weten waren gekomen over bepaalde onderwerpen en tegelijkertijd de kerndoelen van het (basis)onderwijs hebben aangetikt. Maar wat ze vaak nog veel waardevoller en belangrijker hadden vonden, was, dat wat ze op een informele manier hadden geleerd. Datgene wat vaak niet direct meetbaar of zichtbaar is. Naar mate de kinderen ouder werden realiseerden zij en hun ouders zich steeds vaker en beter wat de invloed van de FLL was geweest op hun leven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daarom ben ik na al die jaren nog steeds super enthousiast over het FIRST programma en er meer en meer van overtuigd geraakt dat dit programma niet alleen moet worden gezien of ingezet mag worden als formeel leermiddel dat begeleidt moet worden door professionals. Het is naar mijn idee geen programma waarvoor kinderen geselecteerd moeten worden op grond van hun leeftijd, niveau of bepaalde kenmerken. Het FIRST programma is voor iedereen en kan een belangrijke link tussen formeel, non-formeel en informeel leren zijn en een schakel voor het conceptuele raamwerk van een leven lang leren. Het FIRST programma is meer dan alleen maar het aanleren van een vaardigheid of bekwaamheid. Het ontwikkeld ook de motivatie, ervaring en talent en al deze competenties heb je nodig en kan je altijd blijven ontwikkelen en verbeteren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Van den Dungen, M. &amp;amp; Smit, W. (2010), Meerdere wegen naar professionalisering. Heerlen: Ruud de Moor Centrum – Open Universiteit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Wellink&lt;br&gt;NXT Generation &lt;br&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands</name></author><summary type="html">Er zijn veel verschillende manieren om te leren. Als docent en coach van een FIRST® LEGO® League (FLL®) team heb ik dit de afgelopen jaren gezien en ervaren. Ook binnen het FIRST programma wordt op verschillende manieren geleerd. Niet op de laatste plaats omdat er wereldwijd veel verschillende team samenstellingen zijn.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIRST®: The Link Between Formal, Non-Formal and Informal Learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/27/FIRST-The-Link-Between-Formal,-Non-Formal-and-Informal-Learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIRST®: The Link Between Formal, Non-Formal and Informal Learning" /><published>2016-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/27/FIRST---The-Link-Between-Formal,-Non-Formal-and-Informal-Learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/27/FIRST-The-Link-Between-Formal,-Non-Formal-and-Informal-Learning.html">&lt;p&gt;There are different ways to learn. As a teacher and coach of a FIRST LEGO ® League (FLL®) team, I’ve seen and experienced this over the past several years. Even within the FIRST ® program you can learn in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/NXTGeneration.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FLL® teams are formed within scout programs, technology clubs, youth organizations and voluntary organizations. However, most commonly, they are formed as part of schools, after school programs and home schools. I discovered that diverse teams (in terms of age, level and interest) often get more out the FLL® program than teams with a homogeneous composition. Perhaps this is because team members learn with and from each other, and often learn in a more informal way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I stated in the introduction there are many different ways of learning. According to “van den Dungen &amp;amp; Smith, 2010” one can divide learning into three different types, namely: formal, non- formal and informal learning. The terms, formal, non-formal and informal learning are used by the OECD (Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development), as well as researchers and practitioners around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Formal Learning&lt;/b&gt; is organized learning which is legally regulated and meets quality requirements with fixed targets. It ends with a nationally recognized diploma or
certificate. Professionals who have received training teach the
classes. Schools, colleges and universities fall in this category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Non-formal Learning&lt;/b&gt; is often less organized, and does not have to fit in a program. A qualified teacher or a coach with more experience can guide this type of learning. Although the program is not standardized, and has no certification or a diploma, the program is very rewarding and the student learns individual skills and competencies. Scouting or sports groups are a good example. In non- formal learning, enthusiasm, fun and intrinsic motivation are often the driving force behind participation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Informal Learning&lt;/b&gt; is learning which is generally not organized. It occurs anywhere including in the family, at work, during leisure time, and in society. We learn a lot and frequently. It is spontaneous and casual, and often the learning happens together with others. We pick up ideas from peers, we ask for help, and we get feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Informal learning is increasingly seen as an important way of realizing formal and non-formal learning. The teacher is just someone with more experience like a parent, grandparent or a friend. From the student’s point of view, this learning is non-targeted. The learning outcomes are not recorded and are not usually visible to the student. An example of informal learning is a father who teaches his child fishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FLL® program fits, in my opinion, between non-formal and informal learning. The program itself is more non-formal because it has been developed and carried out by FIRST ® in a more or less organized setting. With the FLL® program, children develop knowledge and skills, but also other skills such as individual and social competencies. The team members are often inexperienced, and are accompanied by a qualified teacher or a coach with more experience (such as a youth leader, volunteer or parent). The FLL® activities are planned, but are not always structured within conventional time formats or school subjects. Participation in the program is generally voluntary. The setting is mostly outside the classroom, and more informal. The learning outcomes are not recorded, measured or assessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the program further proceeds, the students are learning more in an informal way. They get help from
professionals and experts in the field; they go on excursions or investigate and learn spontaneously and accidentally from one another. They work together, care for each other and look with different eyes at their environment. They are assertive; learn to deal with setbacks and opinions of others. They learn to establish contacts; enhance their perseverance and give attention to non-verbal behavior. They also devote more of their free time to this project to find material, and arrange or organize things. But above all, they have a good time and they enjoy what they are doing. They have FUN. The coach or mentor is at this stage often only a spectator, someone who facilitates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a coach, I often got feedback from parents saying that they were grateful that their children had participated in FLL®. The children themselves were glad they had been a member of an FLL® team. They said that they found it fantastic that they had been introduced to engineering and science. They were happy that they now knew how to build a robot and program one.They also developed more spatial awareness. They also loved that they had come to know more about certain subjects, and at the same time had explored the core objectives of primary education. But what they often found even more valuable and important was what they had learned in an informal way. The things they learned are not directly measurable or visible. As the children grew older they and their parents realized increasingly what they had learned and what the impact that FLL® had on their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I’m still excited about the FIRST ® program. I’m more and more convinced after all these years that this program should not be seen or used as a formal learning tool that must be guided by professionals. It is in my opinion that it is not a program that should be restricted by age, level, or certain characteristics. The FIRST ® program is for everyone and is an important link between formal, non-formal and informal learning. It is also a connection to the conceptual framework of life long learning. The FIRST ® program is more than just learning skills or abilities. It also develops motivation, experience and talent. As a person you need all of these competencies and you need to always continue to develop and improve them, not only as a team member, but also as a coach/mentor, expert, professional, volunteer, parent, teacher, CEO, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note:
Van den Dungen, M. &amp;amp; Smith, W. (2010), Multiple paths to professionalization. Heerlen: Ruud de Moor Centre - Open University.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Wellink&lt;br&gt;NXT Generation &lt;br&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands</name></author><summary type="html">There are different ways to learn. As a teacher and coach of a FIRST LEGO ® League (FLL®) team, I’ve seen and experienced this over the past several years. Even within the FIRST ® program you can learn in different ways.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Coöperatief leren en FIRST® LEGO® League</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/20/Coo-peratief-leren-en-FLLmarkdown.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coöperatief leren en FIRST® LEGO® League" /><published>2016-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/20/Co%C3%B6peratief-leren-en-FLLmarkdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/20/Coo-peratief-leren-en-FLLmarkdown.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Binnen het FLL programma zit voor ieder wat wils, voor doeners, denkers, dromers en beslissers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/NXTGeneration2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ik merk dat het geweldige FIRST® LEGO® League programma steeds vaker wordt ingezet op het basis-en voorgezet onderwijs. Helaas valt het mij ook op dat dit ook meer en meer wordt ingezet als “makkelijk” en snel te implementeren programma voor A+ kinderen, ofwel kinderen die een extra uitdaging nodig hebben.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dit vindt ik erg jammer. Want heeft niet elk kind een extra uitdaging nodig en is een team net als een klas  juist niet gebaat bij de diversiteit aan talenten?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kinderen die moeite hebben met taal en rekenen krijgen vaak extra aandacht op deze gebieden en dat is goed maar ze worden op die manier ook elke keer weer geconfronteerd met iets waar ze niet zo goed in zijn. Soms vraagt deze extra aandacht voor taal en rekenen zoveel tijd dat deze kinderen worden buiten gesloten van leerzame, leuke  en uitdagende programma’s zoals FLL®.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coöperatief-leren&quot;&gt;Coöperatief leren&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Als FLL® coach heb ik  gemerkt dat kinderen binnen een FLL® team juist heel veel van de interactie met elkaar kunnen leren. De gedachte achter samenwerkend leren is dat zowel de zwakke als de sterke kinderen hiervan leren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kinderen die sociaal niet zo sterk zijn leren assertiever te zijn en kinderen die misschien niet zo goed zijn met taal blijken geweldige robotbouwers te zijn die alles weten over lego of fantastisch te kunnen presenteren. Kinderen die verlegen zijn leren hun grenzen te verleggen en kinderen die het moeilijk vinden om samen te werken merken dat wanneer  je samen aan iets werkt je veel meer kan bereiken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Binnen het FLL® programma zit voor ieder wat wils, voor doeners, denkers, dromers en beslissers. Ze hebben elkaar nodig, ze vullen elkaar aan en leren met en van elkaars talenten, passie, moed, creativiteit en nieuwsgierigheid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nxt-generation&quot;&gt;NXT Generation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Het team NXT generation was vele jaren zeer succesvol. Niet omdat er 10 bollebozen in zaten maar 10 kinderen met dezelfde passie en moed. Ze hadden de moed om elkaar om hulp te vragen op de gebieden waarin ze zelf minder goed in waren, ze durfde elkaar te verbeteren en elkaar te stimuleren. Ze waren  creatief en konden buiten de lijntjes denken omdat elk teamlid waardevol was op zijn/haar eigen manier met zijn/haar eigen talenten. De teamleden hadden geen (voor)oordeel, daarom voelde iedereen zich veilig en welkom. Ze waren nieuwsgierig naar alles wat er op hun pad kwam en zo trots op wat ze keer op keer weer met elkaar hadden bereikt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FLL® is daarom in mijn ogen meer dan een A+ project of uitdaging voor slimme kinderen. Bij FLL® mag je zijn wie je bent en iedereen respecteert, waardeert en accepteert elkaar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leren doe je samen, FIRST® LEGO® League doe je samen, daarbij sluit je niemand uit!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Wellink&lt;br&gt;NXT Generation &lt;br&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands</name></author><summary type="html">Binnen het FLL programma zit voor ieder wat wils, voor doeners, denkers, dromers en beslissers.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cooperative Learning in FIRST® LEGO® League</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/20/Cooperative-Learning-in-FIRST.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cooperative Learning in FIRST® LEGO® League" /><published>2016-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/20/Cooperative-Learning-in-FIRST</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2016/12/20/Cooperative-Learning-in-FIRST.html">&lt;p&gt;NXT Generation competed in FIRST® LEGO® League for many years in the Netherlands. They were invited to partcipate in many international level events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The FLL program is for everyone: for doers, thinkers, dreamers and decision makers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/NXTGeneration2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-is-first-lego-league-for&quot;&gt;Who is FIRST® LEGO® League for?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, I have started to notice that the First Lego League program is increasingly being used in Elementary and Junior High school. Unfortunately, however, I also notice that this program is more and more being used as an quick and easy way to implement a program for academically advanced students - those who need an extra challenge, the so called “smart kids”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doesn’t every child need an additional challenge? Is it not so that a team, just like a class, can benefit from having a diversity of talents?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Children who have language and mathematics difficulties are often given extra attention in these areas, which is good. As a result, those same children are confronted with something they’re not so good at over and over again. Sometimes these extra lessons take up so much time that those kids are denied opportunities for of educational, entertaining, and challenging programs such as FLL®.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-cooperative-learning&quot;&gt;What is Cooperative Learning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a FIRST® LEGO® League coach, I noticed that children can learn a lot from each other and from the interactions within an FLL team. The idea behind cooperative learning is that both academically weak and strong children can benefit from the interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, children whose social skills are not so strong can learn to be more assertive, and children who may not be so good with language prove to be great robot builders or prove to be fantastic motivational speakers. Children who are shy learn to push their limits and children who Kind it difficult to work together will experience that when you work together you can achieve much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FLL® program is for everyone, for doers, thinkers, dreamers and decision makers. They need each other, they complement each other, and they learn with and from each other’s talents, passion, courage, creativity and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nxt-generation&quot;&gt;NXT Generation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NXT Generation team was successful, not because the team had ten very smart brains, but because they were ten children with the same passion and courage. They had the courage to ask each other for help in the areas in which they themselves were not as good, they dared to correct each other, and encourage each other. They were creative and able to think outside the box because each team member was valued for his/her own style and for his/her own talents. The team did not have preconceptions, therefore everyone felt safe and welcome. They were curious about everything that came down their path and they were so proud of what they had with each other over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FLL® is, therefore, in my eyes more than a program only for the “gifted” or “smart” kids. In&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FLL® you can be who you are and everyone In FIRST® LEGO® League you work together and learn together, thereby leaving no one out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Wellink&lt;br&gt;NXT Generation &lt;br&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands</name></author><summary type="html">NXT Generation competed in FIRST® LEGO® League for many years in the Netherlands. They were invited to partcipate in many international level events.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry></feed>
