<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-07T09:43:50-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Coach’s Corner</title><subtitle>I am the founder of EV3Lessons</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What is in a Logo?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/07/What-is-in-a-Logo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is in a Logo?" /><published>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/07/What-is-in-a-Logo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/07/What-is-in-a-Logo.html">&lt;p&gt;Team names and logos represent who you are.  They are fun to come up with and a great way of representing the team. They are inspired by where you live, what you enjoy, schools and organizations you are affiliated with, and more.  Read below to learn about some FIRST-related logos and their origins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/TeamLogo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ev3lessons-logo-more-than-what-it-seems&quot;&gt;EV3Lessons Logo: More than what it seems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EV3Lessons was founded by FIRST team, Not the Droids You Are Looking For. We came up with the EV3Lessons logo early in the 2014 World Class Season.  The EV3 was made to look like to faces looking at each other and learning from each other to match our tag line. One face is green and the other is purple to represent us (Sanjay and Arvind) as it is our favorite colors. We made the “L” in Lessons into a road because learning is journey/path you take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/ev3lessonslogo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-logo&quot;&gt;FIRST Logo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does the FIRST logo mean anything? Yes, it does. This image linked was shared with us by Alex Stout, mentor to the MARS FRC team in West Virginia.  The FIRST Logo is inspired by the Olympics logo as well as Archimedes’ study of the cone, sphere and cylinder. Thus, it combines both elements of sports and mathematics.  Click to read all about the &lt;a href=&quot;/images/coachcorner/FIRSTLogo.jpg&quot;&gt;FIRST Logo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xanterra-fll-making-you-think&quot;&gt;Xanterra FLL: Making you think&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team Xanterra FLL has roots in a local elementary where the mascot is a raccoon. When they competed there they called themselves Procyon Lotor, which is the scientific name for a raccoon. They enjoyed the way the name was a conversation starter &amp;amp; when they left elementary school &amp;amp; became a community team, they wanted a name that people had to think about. After looking up many words &amp;amp; roots in many languages, they landed on Xanterra. Xan comes from Greek, Alexander, meaning protector. Terra is Latin, meaning Earth. Their logo shows a string of children, hand in hand, around the Earth, protecting it. The team wears collared shirts over their team t-shirts &amp;amp; have capes to represent themselves as undercover superheroes, protecting the earth with their smarts &amp;amp; innovative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;robosquids-inspired-by-a-passion&quot;&gt;Robosquids: Inspired by a passion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team is Robosquids. When we started the team two years ago, we asked the boys what they wanted to name it. My son came up with Robosquids since he is obsessed with fishing and squids. His friend and team mate liked it so it stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thingaling-inspired-by-girl-scouts&quot;&gt;Thingaling: Inspired by Girl Scouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a brand new team of 6 Girl Scouts ages 11-14, who came together (from 4 different troops plus 2 girls new to GS altogether!) to form a team! No previous robotics experience including the coach! The girls came up with suggestions for a team name, voted, then one of the girls designed the logo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pink-piranhas-inspired-by-an-frc-team&quot;&gt;Pink Piranhas: Inspired by an FRC team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big sister was on an FRC team called The Pink Team … she mentored our brand new FLL team so I asked the kids to come up with a name that was “Pink &lt;strong&gt;__&lt;/strong&gt;”. We live in FL and there was a flock of giant pelicans that had taken up residence in the pond next to the school during a cold snap and the kids were fascinated with them. So my son and his team picked Pink Pelicans. Little sister started a FLL team the next year they picked Pink Piranhas and several members have younger siblings that started a FLL Jr team and they are Pink Pythons. 😊💕 Big sis is an artist so she designed the logo/mascots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brainiacs-maniacs-inspired-by-girl-scouts&quot;&gt;Brainiacs Maniacs: Inspired by Girl Scouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name was voted on by the original team 5 years ago amongst various contenders. They decided to keep the name to build the “brand” and it has become well known locally, along with their use of various pink accessories which change very year (e.g. bows, hats, capes, suspenders, etc.). The logo was designed by one of the original team members and incorporates the Girl Scout trefoil as they are a Girl Scout sponsored team and also represent the brain growing due to FIRST. This year they modified to include the first name of each team member, which was a great addition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;edisonian-bots-inspired-by-a-famous-person&quot;&gt;Edisonian Bots: Inspired by a famous person&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Team 24731, Edisonian Bots. We are a team of homeschoolers, inspired by Thomas Edison who was also homeschooled. We also live in Fort Myers, FL where Edison spent many winters. Our logo incorporates the EV3 (as the robot’s body) and features several lightbulbs as a nod to Edison. The logo was designed by two of our teammates last season. 💡&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;robowarrior-inspired-by-a-local-sports-team&quot;&gt;Robowarrior: Inspired by a local sports team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First meeting of the team, kids decided upon the name Robo Warriors, the main reason at that time: It was basketball season and home team Golden State Warriors was doing pretty good. All of them were fans and following the team. The name grew on them and they wanted an identity beyond GSW, they decided upon a warrior robot. Kids designed a basic design and then we got it designed from a professional on fiverr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chicks-with-bricks-inspired-by-the-girl-scouts&quot;&gt;Chicks with Bricks: Inspired by the Girl Scouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team is an all girl team of Girl Scouts. The girls all brainstormed ideas for team names and voted to select the winner “Chicks with Bricks”! Once we had a name, we had the kids all sketch up their ideas for logos and then the girls voted on the winner. Their team identity is all about GIRL POWER!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hot-squad-inspired-by-superheros&quot;&gt;H.O.T. Squad: Inspired by superheros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are the H.O.T. Squad (heroes of tomorrow). This has been our team name for two years. Kids picked it and designed the logo. They are good role models and do a lot of outreach as individuals and as a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nerds-inspired-by-a-school-name&quot;&gt;NERDS: Inspired by a school name&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a school based team (well, collection of teams). Our school is named North, so the kids our first year came up with North Nerds. Then we decided to make NERDS an acronym, so we became the “North Engineering Robotics Design Squad” . We field 3 teams each year, and the kids shift around (again, school team) so each year the teams come up with their own spin on NERDS. Some of my favorites have been “NERDS who say Ni!”, “NERDS in Shining Armor”, “Despicable NERDS” and “NERDS Sharknado”. Some teams choose to go with something project related- so this year we had the “Salty NERDS”. Our logo was designed our first year and is our robotics room mascot: a little robot with a wrench in hand and a star-cut out on its belly (our school “mascot” is Stars).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;21st-century-space-guys-inspired-by-an-interest-in-space&quot;&gt;21st Century Space Guys: Inspired by an interest in space&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a neighbourhood team in Kentville, Nova Scotia, Canada. Our team name started with a discussion of being the 1980s something space guys, but then it was pointed out that no one in the room had been born in the 80s. So… they shifted to the 21st Century Space Guys. At the time the team was all male, but even last year when a young lady joined our team she didn’t mind. Our robot’s name is Hadfield who is named after Col. Chris Hadfield - a real 21st Century Space Guy for Canada. Our logo was done by one of our team members. It is a take off of the Lego classic space guys logo. He redrew it a bit so it wasn’t copying it. We have had pins made and we have a banner too. Our t-shirts add to our team identity in that each member is a colour of a classic space minifigure. I, as the coach, get to wear green.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA</name></author><summary type="html">Team names and logos represent who you are.  They are fun to come up with and a great way of representing the team. They are inspired by where you live, what you enjoy, schools and organizations you are affiliated with, and more.  Read below to learn about some FIRST-related logos and their origins.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIRST LEGO League Deliverables</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/05/FIRST-LEGO-League-Deliverables.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIRST LEGO League Deliverables" /><published>2018-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/05/FIRST-LEGO-League-Deliverables</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/05/FIRST-LEGO-League-Deliverables.html">&lt;p&gt;This article provides one coach’s view of what a team needs to accomplish in one season of FIRST LEGO League. It is intended to provide a new coach a high-level view of what their team needs to work on during the season. Check with your tournament director for any region-specific requirements. Some regions give more or less time for presentations. Others do not require or have presentations at all. The most important deliverable for any team is to HAVE FUN!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Deliverables.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list started with my packing list for a tournament. I then expanded it to include the things we do throughout the season. The kids will do the work, but the coaches (that’s you!) will do the organization, scheduling, facilitation, and teaching of specific needed skills. The skills include mechanical design and programming of robots of course, but also writing a coherent presentation, talking to experts, sharing information with judges and other interested parties, teamwork, effective negotiation and communication within the team, strategy, time management, and how to have fun while doing all of that. Some things on a single line will take up enormous amounts of time, like the robot game, and the research project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;core-values&quot;&gt;Core Values:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;over-the-season&quot;&gt;Over the season:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Come up with a team cheer / chant (Team cheers are not required, but can be a great way to show spirit)
2) Learn the Core Values
3) Practice Core Values while executing Project and Robot game
4) Do specific Core Values activities and improve communication
5) If possible, meet with / help / collaborate with another team or a Jr. FLL team
6) Develop a 2 min presentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-to-event&quot;&gt;Take to event:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Core Values poster (optional in some regions)
2) Team core values summary to leave with judges
3) Props / scripts / presentation materials
4) Giveaways to share with other teams
5) Team spirit / cheering items (balloons, megaphones, pennants, whatever)
6) Pit decorations
7) Banner / flag for the parade (Some regions have team parades)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;project&quot;&gt;Project:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;over-the-season-1&quot;&gt;Over the season:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Learn about theme
2) Meet with experts
3) Choose a problem
4) Develop an innovative solution
5) Meet with experts for feedback and sharing
6) Develop a 5 min presentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-to-event-1&quot;&gt;Take to event:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Project poster board
2) Team project summary to leave with the judges
3) Props / scripts / presentation
4) Solution prototype (if your team has one)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;robot-game&quot;&gt;Robot Game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;over-the-season-2&quot;&gt;Over the season:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Maintain an engineering notebook – the story of our robot (This is not required and does not have to be as detailed as those created in FTC or FRC, but documenting your design is helpful)
2) Think about strategy – how does the game board shape our solutions?
3) Solve robot game missions
4) Develop a 4min presentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-to-event-2&quot;&gt;Take to event:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Robot design executive summary (RDES) to leave with judges
2) Code to share (printed or on computer)
3) Short presentation – the story of our robot (Some regions require a 4 minute RDES presentation)
4) Robot / attachments / charger / download cable
5) Computer / power supply (have mission model build instructions on computer)
6) Extra LEGO elements
7) Backup of programs
8) Power strip / extension cord
9) Printed Challenge document
10) Small table (Some regions ask teams to bring their own table for keeping parts during the robot runs)
11) Have photographs of robot and attachments in case of damage along the way&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other&quot;&gt;Other&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-to-event-3&quot;&gt;Take to event:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Snacks for the team
2) Pens / paper / tape / scissors / clipboard
3) Consider food – is it available at tournament? Bag lunch? Go get pizza?
4) Presentation skills!
5) Card games or small activities to pass the time
6) Bring your social skills - go talk to other teams and make new friends&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;year-end-party&quot;&gt;Year-end party&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Trophies or other items for each team member (choose, design, purchase, build)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stephanie Ozenne&lt;br&gt;Rejecting Reality&lt;br&gt;Utah, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">This article provides one coach’s view of what a team needs to accomplish in one season of FIRST LEGO League. It is intended to provide a new coach a high-level view of what their team needs to work on during the season. Check with your tournament director for any region-specific requirements. Some regions give more or less time for presentations. Others do not require or have presentations at all. The most important deliverable for any team is to HAVE FUN!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Segue From FLL to FRC</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/01/16/Segue-From-FLL-to-FRC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Segue From FLL to FRC" /><published>2018-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/01/16/Segue-From-FLL-to-FRC</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/01/16/Segue-From-FLL-to-FRC.html">&lt;p&gt;“Combining the excitement of sport with the rigors of science and technology, FIRST Robotics Competition is the ultimate Sport for the Mind(TM), where imagination and innovation come together! By combining the excitement of sport and beauty of art with the rigors of science and technology, teams of high school students (ages 14 - 18/grades 9 - 12) are challenged to design a team ‘brand,’ hone teamwork skills, and build and program robots to perform tasks against a field of competitors.  Participants call it the ‘hardest fun you’ll ever have.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time we saw a FIRST Robotics Competition (FRC) robot up close and personal was at the World Championship in St. Louis, April 2017. It was love at first sight. The robots’ speed and finesse was impressive. FRC pits were abuzz with focused team members wearing Nascar-type shirts using all sorts of power tools. And the fast-paced, spontaneous nature of the Steamworks game had us mesmerized. Making the segue from FLL to FRC was a natural next step. The really cool thing about FRC is all skill levels are welcome and needed, technical and non-technical. If you are thinking about transitioning from FLL to FRC, here’s what you need to know and consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Worldchangers2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When transitioning from FLL to FRC, the first year will be the toughest. You may use some of the same strategies you used in FLL, but you will have to learn about a new program, challenge, building system and game aspects.  Programming changes from visual programming to text programming.  By no means is our list exhaustive.  Consider interviewing FRC teams at a nearby FRC Regional Tournament to know what may be ahead and how to prepare. It’s normal to sometimes feel overwhelmed, frustrated and even lost. Coopertition is the essence of FIRST. As you learn and grow, be sure to glean knowledge and insights from other teams. Know that with each year of experience things will make more sense and you will be better equipped to handle the challenges that come your way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FRC teams operate like a business.  Team members are expected to conduct themselves like professionals, knowledgeable in aspects of their team.  Presentations are formal like business proposals.  FRC tournaments are competitive, fast-paced and fun! Retain your FLL Core Values and you’ll have a great season!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;required-skills&quot;&gt;Required Skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All students welcome to participate in FRC, with or without special skills. Both technical and non-tecnical skills are needed. Whatever you are good at – there is a place for you. Whatever you are willing to learn – there is a place for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible sub-teams include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing/digital prototyping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strategists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electronics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Metalworking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scouting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Graphic design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Website creation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aptitude for science, technology, engineering, math, physics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knack for problem-solving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appreciation for power tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public speaking/presenting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photography/videography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marketing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creative writing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social media&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Event planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fundraising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Branding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project managers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cheerleaders and even Glitter Captains (a.k.a. Team spirit)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘This is the only sport where if you show up, you can play.’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;committment&quot;&gt;Committment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team members complete from January through April. Mentors and adult volunteers lend their time and talent to provide guidance to the team. They meet several times per week. There is a six-week build time from early January through mid-February. After this, teams bag and tag the robot and do not touch it again until the first competition. Each season culminates with district and regional events where qualifying teams compete for awards and a spot at the FIRST Championship in Houston, TX or Detroit, MI. Seasoned teams actually meet throughout the school year. They use the summer for fundraising and outreach. There are also several off-season optional competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tips:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be prepared to spend some nights and weekends helping your team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You, your family, and your schedule will determine how much time you can devote&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Like any school activity, the more time you invest, the better you will become.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;team-basics&quot;&gt;Team Basics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A team is composed of ten or more high school-aged students willing to put in time to do any job the team needs to succeed. There are lots of important jobs available for all skill levels and interests. You will need to find a suitable meeting place that includes adequate space to design and build an industrial-sized robot (about 150 lbs.). You will need access to a variety of machine shop power tools, a standard kit of parts and a common set of rules issued by FIRST. Many teams fabricate their own parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two or more adult Mentors are needed for each team, with both technical and non-technical expertise. They must be willing and motivated to coach the team through the build and competition season, and beyond. Community sponsors will be needed to help fund your efforts and provide other support. You will also need to have the desire to learn, explore, strategize, build camaraderie, share ideas and talents, make new friends, be accepted, and HAVE FUN!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-frame&quot;&gt;Time Frame&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FIRST Robotics Competition teams register in the fall. However, the official season begins when the season’s Challenge is announced at a Kickoff ceremony the first Saturday in January. Teams are given six weeks to create their robot. District and Regional competition events start in late February and continue through April. Teams that qualify are invited to FIRST Championship one of the last two weeks of April. Off-season events to strategize, hone skills, learn new technology, meet other teams, and have fun are common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cost&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost varies from team to team and region to region depending on what level of participation the team chooses. The annual fees for team registration, a robot kit of parts, and event participation are $5,000 - $6,000. Additional costs for travel, food, team shirts and other optional items will vary. FIRST offers many fundraising opportunities and teams are encouraged to create their own. Grants are also available, as well as sponsorships provided locally, regionally and nationally by many corporations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>World Changers&lt;br&gt;Iowa, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">“Combining the excitement of sport with the rigors of science and technology, FIRST Robotics Competition is the ultimate Sport for the Mind(TM), where imagination and innovation come together! By combining the excitement of sport and beauty of art with the rigors of science and technology, teams of high school students (ages 14 - 18/grades 9 - 12) are challenged to design a team ‘brand,’ hone teamwork skills, and build and program robots to perform tasks against a field of competitors.  Participants call it the ‘hardest fun you’ll ever have.’”</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy Holidays</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/12/16/Happy-Holidays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy Holidays" /><published>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/12/16/Happy-Holidays</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/12/16/Happy-Holidays.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/Gifts.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaborating on a physical task&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coordinating movements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Boxes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wrapping Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scissors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tape&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
Leave items on table jumbled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Your team has to wrap as many gifts as possible in 10 minutes. Each member of the team can only do one task (and only touch that one item - paper, scissors, tape, box).  Work together to wrap as many presents as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;
1) If you have a larger team, add some more items such as ribbons, name on the gift, etc.
2) Make the task longer if you need to.
2) Variations: Wrap the present but everyone can only use one hand, one blindfolded is the only one allowed to wrap (everyone else can see), wrap without talking.  (Credit for alternative ideas: Karla Stevens)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tools for Teams</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Tools-For-Teams.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tools for Teams" /><published>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Tools-For-Teams</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Tools-For-Teams.html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I asked teams about what tools they would recommend for other teams. Here are the results of the discussion on Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.  If you would like to share any more, send an email to team@ev3lessons.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Tools.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Calendar - Team Scheduling &lt;br /&gt;
Google Group - Team Mailing Lists &lt;br /&gt;
Google Drive - Shared Team Files &lt;br /&gt;
Trello - Team organization &lt;br /&gt;
Redbooth - Taking Notes &lt;br /&gt;
OneNote and OneDrive - Notes and Shared Documents &lt;br /&gt;
Slack - Tracking Progress, Documenting &lt;br /&gt;
EV3Lessons Robot Game Scorer - Tracking Scores &lt;br /&gt;
Basecamp - Project Management &lt;br /&gt;
Fleep - Messaging &lt;br /&gt;
Whatapp - Team communication &lt;br /&gt;
iMovie&lt;br /&gt;
iBrainstorm&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Asha Seshan&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">A few weeks ago, I asked teams about what tools they would recommend for other teams. Here are the results of the discussion on Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .  If you would like to share any more, send an email to team@ev3lessons.com.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Number of Hours</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Number-of-Hours.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Number of Hours" /><published>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Number-of-Hours</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Number-of-Hours.html">&lt;p&gt;FIRST LEGO League teams come in all shapes and sizes. Some are school teams that can meet only for a couple of hours each week. Some are community teams or homeschool teams that invest a lot of more time. Regardless of how many hours a team spends, they will learn. It is up to the team to decide the number of hours to spend and their goals for the season. However, to get an idea for how much time teams spend, below are the results of a survey of 120 FIRST LEGO League Teams conducted on the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;bar-graph&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;bar-graph-axis&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bar-graph-label&quot;&gt;35%&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bar-graph-label&quot;&gt;28%&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bar-graph-label&quot;&gt;21%&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bar-graph-label&quot;&gt;14%&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bar-graph-label&quot;&gt;7%&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bar-graph-label&quot;&gt;0%&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;bar warning&quot; style=&quot;height: 21%;&quot; title=&quot;75&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;percent&quot;&gt;9&lt;span&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;1-2hrs&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;bar secondary&quot; style=&quot;height: 63%;&quot; title=&quot;90&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;percent&quot;&gt;24&lt;span&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;3-4hrs&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;bar primary&quot; style=&quot;height: 100%;&quot; title=&quot;95&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;percent&quot;&gt;40&lt;span&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;5-6hrs&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;bar success&quot; style=&quot;height: 44%;&quot; title=&quot;80&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;percent&quot;&gt;17&lt;span&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;7-9hrs&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li class=&quot;bar alert&quot; style=&quot;height: 19%;&quot; title=&quot;40&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;percent&quot;&gt;7&lt;span&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;10-14hrs&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;bar warning&quot; style=&quot;height: 15%;&quot; title=&quot;40&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;percent&quot;&gt;3&lt;span&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;15+hrs&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.bar-graph {
padding: 0;
width: 100%;
display: -webkit-flex;
display: -ms-flexbox;
display: flex;
-webkit-align-items: flex-end;
-ms-flex-align: end;
align-items: flex-end;
height: 425px;
margin: 0;
}

.bar-graph li {
display: block;
padding: 1.5625rem 0;
position: relative;
text-align: center;
vertical-align: bottom;
border-radius: 4px 4px 0 0;
max-width: 20%;
height: 100%;
margin: 0 1.8% 0 0;
-webkit-flex: 1 1 15%;
-ms-flex: 1 1 15%;
flex: 1 1 15%;
}

.bar-graph .bar-graph-axis {
-webkit-flex: 1 1 8%;
-ms-flex: 1 1 8%;
flex: 1 1 8%;
display: -webkit-flex;
display: -ms-flexbox;
display: flex;
-webkit-flex-direction: column;
-ms-flex-direction: column;
flex-direction: column;
-webkit-justify-content: space-between;
-ms-flex-pack: justify;
justify-content: space-between;
}

.bar-graph .bar-graph-label {
margin: 0;
background-color: none;
color: #8a8a8a;
position: relative;
}

@media print, screen and (min-width: 40em) {
.bar-graph .bar-graph-label:before, .bar-graph .bar-graph-label:after {
content: &quot;&quot;;
position: absolute;
border-bottom: 1px dashed #8a8a8a;
top: 0;
left: 0;
height: 50%;
width: 20%;
}
}

@media print, screen and (min-width: 40em) and (min-width: 64em) {
.bar-graph .bar-graph-label:before, .bar-graph .bar-graph-label:after {
width: 30%;
}
}

@media print, screen and (min-width: 40em) {
.bar-graph .bar-graph-label:after {
left: auto;
right: 0;
}
}

.bar-graph .percent {
letter-spacing: -3px;
opacity: 0.4;
width: 100%;
font-size: 1.875rem;
position: absolute;
}

@media print, screen and (min-width: 40em) {
.bar-graph .percent {
//font-size: 3.875rem;
font-size: 2rem;
}
}

.bar-graph .percent span {
font-size: 1.875rem;
}

.bar-graph .description {
font-weight: 800;
opacity: 0.5;
text-transform: uppercase;
width: 100%;
font-size: 14px;
bottom: 20px;
position: absolute;
font-size: 1rem;
overflow: hidden;
}

.bar-graph .bar.primary {
border: 1px solid #1779ba;
background: linear-gradient(#2196e3, #1779ba 70%);
}

.bar-graph .bar.secondary {
border: 1px solid #767676;
background: linear-gradient(#909090, #767676 70%);
}

.bar-graph .bar.success {
border: 1px solid #3adb76;
background: linear-gradient(#65e394, #3adb76 70%);
}

.bar-graph .bar.warning {
border: 1px solid #ffae00;
background: linear-gradient(#ffbe33, #ffae00 70%);
}

.bar-graph .bar.alert {
border: 1px solid #cc4b37;
background: linear-gradient(#d67060, #cc4b37 70%);
}


&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruth Ann Francis&lt;/strong&gt;
My team meets 4.5 hours/week (1.5 hours one evening during the week and 3 hours on either Friday or Saturday depending on my work schedule and kids’ availability. We’re a home school team, so that makes scheduling meetings a little more flexible).
 I have a co-coach who takes care of all of the administrative stuff. She also works with the parents to work with the kids to do most of the Project work. I come in at the end and ask all the annoying questions that cause them to need/want to do more research. And I handle Core Values and Robot Design/Game coaching pretty much all myself. It’s a lot, but it actually works pretty well as it allows me to incorporate more Core Values activities in with the robot stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Michael Graffin&lt;/strong&gt;
 I’ve been running two teams pretty much solo, with some extra assitance for the past two years. With the amount of hours we put in, I’d definitely recommend extra pairs of hands. I don’t want to go through this again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evonne Reynolds&lt;/strong&gt;
I’m estimating about 40 hours total with the kids. I’m really the only coach (a parent is listed as assistant coach with FIRST but she really just orders tshirts). My parents are great about helping with displays/posters at the end but I do the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jason Koop&lt;/strong&gt;
My team of 8 (4th &amp;amp; 5th graders) met 11 times for a total of 16.5 hours before our qualifier this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jennifer Langston Saylor&lt;/strong&gt;
I meet with my team twice a week from 3:30-5pm. The last two weeks however we have had extended practices due to our upcoming qualifying competition. We went m-f same hours last week and this week we met Monday and Tuesday 3:30-6pm. I am the head coach with an assistant. We also have a parent that helps out on occasion too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Michael Graffin&lt;/strong&gt;
We did nearly 60, once you factored in the extra lunchtime, before school sessions, and weekends. I hope to do it a bit smarter next season - as this one almost killed me. Most of the time, both teams trained and prepared alongside eachother. That, I would do again - it was beneficial for our new members&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asha Seshan&lt;/strong&gt;
 In answer to your other question - 2 coaches are a requirement to register a team these days…and honestly, is probably needed. Parents pitching in here and there is very useful too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ryan Evans&lt;/strong&gt;
Totally an average. I had kids that spent every lunch time in my room and took home programming books and researched ev3lessons in their own time. I had other kids I had to motivate daily!
Jeff Hagan We (a community team) normally do 2 practices a week of 2 hours each, but with a few extra sessions leading up to the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Melanie Somogie&lt;/strong&gt;
We are a parent led at school group. We met 2x/wk for 2 hrs, some longer Saturdays. Honestly, Saturday meetings were much more productive because after school the kids were less focused and part of the time was spent unwinding and getting a snack before work actually started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don Tippet&lt;/strong&gt;
We practice twice a week, two hours each time. Add to that two or three prop building parties along with volunteering for local FLL events, helping other teams, etc…Our qualifier is always the second or third Saturday in December. The one thing I always look at the week before qualifiers is health of the kids. Typically during this week we are sharing our project once or twice, helping set up the qualifier, etc…. And on top of all that, flu season is kicking into full gear. I have noticed sickness creeping in to the team in years past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Catherine Sarisky&lt;/strong&gt;
We had one at-school meeting that had nearly 100% attendance, 2 hrs/week. Then we had a two-hour weekend meeting at my house, where attendance ran about 50% most weeks, mostly the same kids.  Some weeks some of them did an hour or two of other work. If it was very very specific exactly what they should do, sometimes the parents would nudge them to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laila Qn&lt;/strong&gt;
In the lead up to our National Competition we practiced Monday and Thursday 4-6pm and on Saturday and Sunday 9-3pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asha Seshan&lt;/strong&gt;
For my team, the Droids, the hours changed over the years. Year one was 2 hrs on a Friday…and then 4 added on a Saturday a month into the season. The number of hours has steadily increased each year in the program. For the Droids, FLL became year-round many years ago. My kids invest a lot of time into the program as a whole (beyond their own competition work) which is what accounts for the large number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Karla Stevens&lt;/strong&gt;
We meet once a week for 2.5 hours. We have some extra meetings - but those are optional as all of the kids have lots of other activities too. Extra meetings are usually only attended by a few kids - but they get more done with fewer kids so it works out&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Angelica G. Salazar&lt;/strong&gt;
We meet twice a week for two hours. The last two weeks one of those meetings becomes a 3hr meeting. And usually we add a third meeting the last week before qualifier, just for extra practice and poster making.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Asha Seshan&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">FIRST LEGO League teams come in all shapes and sizes. Some are school teams that can meet only for a couple of hours each week. Some are community teams or homeschool teams that invest a lot of more time. Regardless of how many hours a team spends, they will learn. It is up to the team to decide the number of hours to spend and their goals for the season. However, to get an idea for how much time teams spend, below are the results of a survey of 120 FIRST LEGO League Teams conducted on the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Team Member awards</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Awards-For-Team-Members.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Team Member awards" /><published>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Awards-For-Team-Members</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Awards-For-Team-Members.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-you-give-out-individual-awards-to-team-members-after-the-season-is-over-what-awards-do-you-give-out-team-spirit-ingenuity-rising-star&quot;&gt;Do you give out individual awards to team members after the season is over? What awards do you give out? Team spirit? Ingenuity? Rising Star?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some teams give out individual awards at the the end of the season. This might be to recognized the students’ contributions or because the team only receives one trophy. Below are such suggestions for creating your own trophies/recognizing team members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Trophies.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;
Photo Credit: Annie Drennan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Want to create a replica of a FIRST LEGO League trophy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ortop.org/Documents/SS_LRG_Trophy.pdf&quot;&gt;Large Trophy Build Instructions by Ortop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ortop.org/Documents/2000422_Pokal_Medium_US%20(1).pdf&quot;&gt;Medium Trophy Build Instructions by Ortop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ortop.org/Documents/SS_Sm_Trophy.pdf&quot;&gt;Small Trophy Build Instructions by Ortop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bricklink.com/catalogItemInv.asp?S=2000422-1&quot;&gt;Trophy Parts List&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Lauren Bierman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great idea! How about Master Builder?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Layne Kirk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I custom make certificates each year. The certificate includes: the team photo with names underneath, photos and descriptions of trophies (if any), season logo, FLL logo, and a custom picture of a minifigure that looks like the recipient (with his/her name underneath). I’ll include a photo of them in costume with props from their presentation, too, if that applies. It’s more of a keepsake (photo collage) for memory’s sake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Angelica G. Salazar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We usually have a little award ceremony, and each member receives an award for something they did during the tournament that was above and beyond the expected. I can easily find something for each child. They also get one of those blind mini figures packs. And we eat ice cream Sundays while we read our rubric results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think is nice to be recognized as a team member who supports and helps the team. Specially for those kids who feel they are the lazy ones and aren’t as good as the rest of the team. Or for those who have been pushed out of their comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That child whose mission only worked once or maybe not at all during the tournament, even though it worked most of the time during practice, might already be feeling like they don’t offer much support to the team, but maybe that child never lost their enthusiasm, and kept a good spirit and handled the pressure like a champ. I think that deserves some recognition. Or that very shy child that finds strength and their voice during project presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not about getting a prize at the end, is about finding out that you helped the team, in ways that you didn’t even think you were helping. After all the award is just a piece of paper. But I think it improves team morale, specially when things don’t go as planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I have been able to find something good for everyone on the team. During the season I encourage the lazy one to find something they are passionate about. No child joins a team thinking they are going to freeload an experience. There is a motivation there, you just have to find it. Sometimes that lazy kid might be an intimidated child or a bored child in need of something. I had a reluctant programmer, turned out that child was just worried about not being able to do a good job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Ruth Ann Francis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After each tournament, we have ice cream with various toppings while we go over the rubrics and make plans for what’s next. If that’s the next tournament, we talk about what where we want to improve and how we’re going to do that. If our competition season is done I explain what I’m thinking for how we will spend the remaining meetings of the year (we continue to meet for about 90 minutes weekly through the end of April), hear what the kids want to do and we figure out how best to spend the remaining time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Jennifer Langston Saylor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Brick Engravers. I came up with a unique award for each kid. I will do it again too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Fll Telgenborch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope, it has been a team effort. We do celebrate though. We eat cake, laugh and party as a team and celebrate the awesome season we had together. Throughout the season we compliment eachother, every teammember tells another what their talent is and how they contributed to the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Ryan Evans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does everything have to result in a material item or some kind of personal reward? The whole point of FLL is the team effort - the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think you’ll find tokens are appreciated but totally and wholly unnecessary. My kids are stoked to simply keep their t-shirts that they helped make… And they’re still on cloud 9. Even the two teams that didn’t win an award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value the journey - not the prize at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Dari Quirk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the season - I always give each team member the official FLL certificate provided on the website each season - here is the link for this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Michael Graffin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I give out Spirit of FLL awards recognising students’ who have gone above and beyond in their demonstration of core values during the season. It is a personal thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Annie Drennan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure that what works for your team will be as individual as the kids that make up the team, but one thing that my kids really liked that we did a few years ago was when we made the mission models into trophies. We haven’t done that the last couple of years (it doesn’t work for all situations), but we gave each team member a trophy created from the mission model they had worked on the most from the robot game. Three of the team members were my children and I have to say, that even years later, they still look at those trophies far more than any other participation type trophies they’ve received because it reflected their own work and as I collected the trophies from their rooms to give you an example, I couldn’t help but go down memory road about what they named an attachment or how they overcame a major challenge. I know the robot game isn’t nearly all that FLL is all about, but it certainly is the most visible part at competitions and often the most time consuming and frustrating (&amp;amp; hopefully rewarding) for team members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Asha Seshan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not as creative as other ideas, but this one is from way back…I had plaques made for each member (and the team’s senior citizen partner). Cost me $5 or so each. It was my gift to the kids. I had them made before the championship so I had no idea what they would or would not win. They were all winners to me and so I actually gave them out before the Championships that year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our third season, I gave out patches for skills learned during the season (having bright ideas, learning from mistakes, teamwork, etc). At the end of the season, each kid got a large FLL patch to add to the collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Joanne Sterk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We make certificates of participation. Then we also recognize individual efforts like helping others program, graciousness, parent volunteers, etc at a potluck style gathering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Rod Collins&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After our qualifier, we reviewed how we did. Spontaneously, the kids started complimenting each other for what went on in the event and then broke out laughing as they all gave out nicknames for each other. They loved it so much, they are adding the nicknames across the back of the team shirts for state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Catherine Sarisky&lt;/strong&gt;
I sourced parts for brick-built rhinos (since my team is the Robotic Rhinos) and we built them as a fun activity after the qualifier. I contemplated pedestals, but decided against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also lots of cute opportunities here: http://www.brickengraver.com/ (Not affiliated and haven’t ordered - just looked cute!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Korey Atterberry&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t find the plans just yet, but last year I made a tiny one out of bricks. It cost about $5 each for parts from bricklink. We won a team trophy, but since they don’t all get to have it I wanted them to have a little something for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIRST LEGO League Budget</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/06/FIRST-LEGO-League-Budget.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIRST LEGO League Budget" /><published>2017-12-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/06/FIRST-LEGO-League-Budget</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/06/FIRST-LEGO-League-Budget.html">&lt;p&gt;When starting a FIRST LEGO League team, it is important to keep costs in mind. This is especially true if you are a school-based team and need to apply for grant money ahead of time. Here is a typical budget. The amounts are listed in US Dollars and based on expenses in the United States. There might be variation in other countries. It is good to check with your local organizer to see how much registration and equipment costs in your country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following summary is based on a discussion from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Budget.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Image Credit: Nick Youngson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Start-up Costs&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;National Registration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$225&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Varies by county&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Local Competition Registration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$120-$320&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Varies by region&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FLL Table&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$75-$100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MINDSTORMS FLL Set&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cost saving: Buy retail set and supplement parts, buy used sets&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FLL Challenge Set&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$85&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Can vary by country. Can be shared across teams.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Laptop/Computer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$0-$1000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cost saving: Reuse existing laptop, use tablet, use a desktop&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Supplies&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tri-fold, Markers, Glue, Binders&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Printing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Recurring Costs&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;National Registration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$225&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Local Competition Registration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$120-$320&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Varies by region&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FLL Challenge Set&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$85&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Can vary by country&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Supplies&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tri-fold, Markers, Glue, Binders&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Printing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Yearly Optional Expenses&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Team T-Shirts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$150&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Additional LEGO Parts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sensors, Motors, LEGO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Travel to Events&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$0-$100+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Varies by location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fieldtrips&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$0-$150&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Varies greatly&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Giveaways&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$100+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Books/Resources&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Supplies for Prototpes/Props&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$0-$50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Snacks/Food&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$10+/meeting&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Support Materials&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$50-$200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Storage boxes, utility carts, team banner/sign&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">When starting a FIRST LEGO League team, it is important to keep costs in mind. This is especially true if you are a school-based team and need to apply for grant money ahead of time. Here is a typical budget. The amounts are listed in US Dollars and based on expenses in the United States. There might be variation in other countries. It is good to check with your local organizer to see how much registration and equipment costs in your country.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Preparing for Qualifiers: Bringing Your Best</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/04/Getting-Ready-For-Qualifiers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Preparing for Qualifiers: Bringing Your Best" /><published>2017-12-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/04/Getting-Ready-For-Qualifiers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/04/Getting-Ready-For-Qualifiers.html">&lt;p&gt;I’d like to share a thought that might help calm new teams as we approach qualifiers. It’s also a question at the heart of Core Values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Hyperbolics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Image Credit: Hyperbolics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask teams, “Are you ever directly competing with anyone or any team in FIRST LEGO League?” The answer is no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your competition is the obstacle on the board. Your competition is the real-world problem you are trying to solve. All you do on the day of a qualifier is bring your best. Your best robot. Your best explanations. Your best examples. Your best teamwork. You are COMPETING with no one. You are just offering the best you have, in the best way you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can that best be improved? ALWAYS. But that’s not the issue. You do the best you can on that day, and then you look at how you did, and you learn from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best team can freeze up. The least organized team can have everything work perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the qualifier is the last event you attend this year, look at all that you learned! You stretched your knowledge of robots. You practiced presentations. You worked on a project MANY degrees of difficulty higher than your grade level, and you expanded your (and others’!) knowledge of a problem facing the modern world! YOU ARE A HERO!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-trophy-is-a-piece-of-plastic-the-knowledge-tools-and-skills-you-build-in-fll-are-a-lever-that-you-can-use-to-move-the-world&quot;&gt;A trophy is a piece of plastic. The knowledge, tools and skills you build in FLL are a lever that YOU can use to move the world.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article has been reposted on EV3Lessons with permission from Amy Heider Brown.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amy Heider Brown&lt;br&gt;Hyperbolics&lt;br&gt;Greenville, SC, USA,</name></author><summary type="html">I’d like to share a thought that might help calm new teams as we approach qualifiers. It’s also a question at the heart of Core Values.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Master Scribe, Piecekeeper and More</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/01/Team-Roles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Master Scribe, Piecekeeper and More" /><published>2017-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/01/Team-Roles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/01/Team-Roles.html">&lt;p&gt;Every team is different, but every student on a team should have a role to play. Some kids are good writers, some kids are good speakers, and some kids are good actors. It is important to remember that not everyone enjoys building and programming MINDSTORMS. In FIRST LEGO League, there is a place for everyone. Getting to do what you enjoy the most is a big part of having fun in the FIRST LEGO League program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a personal reflection from Kaia, a fifth year FIRST LEGO League veteran, about her place on an FLL team. This article has been reposted on EV3Lessons with permission from Kaia and Team Xanterra. To learn more about Xanterra, visit their &lt;a href=&quot;http://nirostem.org&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Xanterra.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xanterra---job-descriptions&quot;&gt;Xanterra - Job Descriptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my 5 years of FLL, I have learned many things including the fact that some people succeed at and enjoy certain parts of the program more than others. This is part of what inspired us to create jobs for all of the team members to allow them to focus a little more of their time on what they enjoy. For example, my passion is writing so the job ‘Master Scribe’ is the perfect fit for me. This give me the chance to focus on writing while also being part of the project, robot game, and the core values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first started implementing jobs mid-season last year. To come up with jobs, we brainstormed with our team until we had more than enough ideas and a wide variety to allow everyone to have multiple ones to pick from. After that we said which one we wanted the most and then compromised in places where more than one person thought they would be a good fit for the title. In the end, we all got a job that we were happy with and could all contribute something unique to the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time we have defined our jobs in more detail. This is a list of our current job descriptions and how we contribute our specialties to the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caleigh – Core Values Lead: Leading team building activities. Making sure everyone is being included in activities &amp;amp; that core values are being followed in day-to-day activities. Leading the production of core values posters &amp;amp; presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaia – Master Scribe: Keeps the team organized in both note taking &amp;amp; record keeping, and gets us prepared for competitions. She creates &amp;amp; maintains a blog with the purpose of sharing our experiences &amp;amp; ideas with others in FLL &amp;amp; in our community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carol Lin – Robot Design Lead: Her job is to have knowledge of general and complex concepts of robot building to assist the rest of the team in keeping the robot in working condition, in good maintenance &amp;amp; to assist them when they need help with their design ideas or troubleshooting problems. She copies our attachments into the Lego Digital Designer program and works with teammates to have at least a general knowledge of how their attachments work in case of their absence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma – Spirit: She keeps the morale of the team up by helping anyone having a tough time by being positive &amp;amp; making sure everyone is being included. She leads the team in coming together at the end of meetings to do a team chant to celebrate our progress &amp;amp; encourage unity. She also creates team cheers and teaches them to the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dalton – Piecekeeper: He organizes and puts pieces away that aren’t being used.  He also keeps the robot building area clean and encourages others on the team to keep pieces picked up. He puts the robot &amp;amp; the attachments away in the storage room at the end of meetings and checks the robot tables at the beginning of each meeting as well as of at competition to make sure they are set up properly. He also communicates any issues found on the table to the refs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Austin – Project Lead: He takes the lead on the project research and leads the team in ideas and development of the project. He helps create a creative project presentation and documents all the project research to create a project research binder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caleb – Programming Lead: Goes through everyone’s programs with them and makes notes about what each part of the program does. For the competition, he makes sure the programs being used are downloaded on the robot, are in order, and are ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cody – Timekeeper: At the competition, he keeps track of time and makes sure we are where we need to be on time. He overlooks our Kanban organizational chart that helps us keep track of our team goals in a “to do, doing &amp;amp; done” fashion throughout the season to ensure everything gets done by competition. He also times the robot rounds during practices to make sure we do not go over the time limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conner – Robot Manager: At competition, he makes sure that the robot is monitored and cared for properly at all times. He helps design the robot &amp;amp; attachments in LEGO Digital Designer along with the Robot Design Lead. At each meeting, he checks for challenge updates and prints copies of any updates for all team members to place in their binders. He leads the team in writing the RDES.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kaia&lt;br&gt;Xanterra&lt;br&gt;Coeur d'Alene, Idaho</name></author><summary type="html">Every team is different, but every student on a team should have a role to play. Some kids are good writers, some kids are good speakers, and some kids are good actors. It is important to remember that not everyone enjoys building and programming MINDSTORMS. In FIRST LEGO League, there is a place for everyone. Getting to do what you enjoy the most is a big part of having fun in the FIRST LEGO League program.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry></feed>
