<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-08T13:39:15-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Coach’s Corner</title><subtitle>I am the founder of EV3Lessons</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Selecting Team Members</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/08/Selecting-Team-Members.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selecting Team Members" /><published>2017-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/08/Selecting-Team-Members</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/08/Selecting-Team-Members.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from Mic Lowne:&lt;/b&gt; I’ve been running teams in schools since food factor and the biggest problem I face each year is selecting the 10 students out of 20-30 that want to be a part of the the team. How do other school based coaches deal with this? Usually I select based on 1st-attitude/willingness to learn, 2nd-attendance, 3rd-skill, 4th-an “application letter”. Thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/SelectingTeam.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Layne Kirk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Realizing this might not apply because we have a school site willing to fund us, but we have as many teams as we have willing coaches (2 per team). When we do recruitment, we make it clear that no student will be turned away, so long as we have enough coaches. And the only way to be guaranteed a spot is to have your parent coach. It’s not perfect - we’ve had some near coaching fails, but it’s a start for us and allows us to accommodate 48 students for next season (in addition to the youth protection screening for FIRST, our coaches are also fingerprinted and background checked locally). I also realize not all communities have participation of parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may take a season or two to build and work out the kinks, but it has worked for us. We, as coordinators, assign the teams, but allow requests to be made. We do our best to accommodate requests without any promises. We hold coaches meetings and equip our coaches to succeed, being readily available to assist them. And we have a total blast doing it! As a side note, we use Google forms for registration. That has worked extremely well for us. My husband and I love the program and are willing to be a resource if you’d like to pick our brains ☺. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Celina McGinnis:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use a variation of the “if you really want your kid to do this, coaching guarantees them a spot”. This year, we are going to try signing up ADULTS first, and supporting them in signing up children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Roy Nelson:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have teachers recommend specific kids. Balance your team with leaders, tech skills, research and presentations, and spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Mic Lowne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely agree (with Roy Nelson’s comment above’), it’s like picking a sports team sometimes, finding a team member that you know will fill a role within the team but still work as a team and help others out. In the student’s application letter I ask them to name the role they think they will be best suited for. This year I also asked students to nominate others they think will be well suited to each role. I got some interesting results, specifically who they nominated for leadership roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jean Findley-Williams:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I coach a community based team in Louisiana. Our team currently ranges in age from “almost 9” to 13 years old. This is the first year that we have not had anyone “graduate” from the team due to age. Next season, however, we will have at least 3 members moving on to high school. Two of those members will move on to our local FRC team and return to us as mentors. The third team member has expressed an interest to join our new community based FTC team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have very few options for FLL teams currently in our area. This means that we have constantly have parents who are contacting us inquiring how to ensure their child joins. When we do have openings, we hold recruitment camps where our returning team members are able to work directly with possible “candidates.” They develop all kinds of activities that involve not just building and programming a basic bot, but also involve team building challenges and very brief presentations. Returning team members rotate among the “candidate” groups so that they can meet everyone. We have also developed an application which involves students writing a short essay about why they would like to be on the team, what would they like to contribute and what they would like to learn. The team also has a few questions about the FLL Core Values included. At the end of each recruitment camp, returning team members submit a list of who they think would be a good fit to myself and my husband. We also all review the submitted essays together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As coaches, my husband and I develop an initial list of potential candidates that takes into account team member feedback, our observations and the essays. We then invite those students back for another meeting in which all of our returning team members and mentors (former team members) are present. During that meeting, my husband and I run the team building activities, present different programming and fun presentation challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following that meeting, our team then votes on who they would like to invite to the team. It can sometimes be a long process, but it works for us. It can sometimes be a leap of faith on our part, but I love the ownership it has instilled. It’s still a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Mark Nicolussi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I coach a school sponsored team, so I try and get the school to select a prioritised list of candidates based on primarily on interest and dedication, and then I invite from the top of the list until the slots are filled. It’s not the greatest system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Managing Your Team in a Shared Space</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/07/Shared-Spaces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Managing Your Team in a Shared Space" /><published>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/07/Shared-Spaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/07/Shared-Spaces.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from Simon Ward:&lt;/b&gt; How do teams manage the table and models between meetings? I’m guessing “leave it set up” is the best option. But what if space is limited, or it’s a shared room? We have this space (my classroom), but it’s a shared room. How practical is continually setting up/putting away models? I’m trying to weigh up time spent setting up / putting away vs. risk of other classes tampering with the set up of models, and putting the table out of action for the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/SharedRoom.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo Credit: Simon Ward&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Stephanie Ozenne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a permanent setup in my basement, and the primary challenge is that neighborhood kids regularly play there when I’m not present. Telling them not to touch the models didn’t help much, but laying a bed sheet over the whole table actually helped quite a bit - out of sight, out of mind, and it’s really obvious to others if someone is messing with the table. Maybe that would help?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jeff Hagan:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the setup that John from FastCats rigged up: he built a false top for his game table that stands a few inches above the top of the walls. He just has to tip over the taller models, put the false top on top, and suddenly the table can be used for other things between practices.   I can’t remember exactly how tall his was, but the general idea was to make it tall enough that most of the models every year wouldn’t have to be moved to put the false top on… but every year, there were generally a couple that are a bit too tall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Evonne Reynolds:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we get our own rooms but previously we had to set up and take down every time we met. The kids got really good at it and any of them that got there a couple minutes early would go ahead and get the models out to set it up. Taking it down at the end of the meeting wasn’t too time consuming either once they all learned where each model needed to go (we had a couple deep totes and a long shallow tote and certain models fit in each one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Mark Nicolussi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our room is shared - the table stays up but we have to tear down the field pieces and lock them away after every practice. After a while it becomes a pretty quick process - 10 minutes for set up, 5 minutes for tear down&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jason Baber:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting it up and taking it down is actually a plus: the kids will be faster at spotting things that may not be reset correctly in a tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jean Findley-Williams:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have always had to share a space so we have always had to set up and take down. Our team members are quick with it and it helps them to become well aware of spotting any inconsistencies. When they go into robot design judging in our state, there are often models not set up right or pieces out of place on purpose to see if the kids will notice. Our team is always quite quick with this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, because of the constant storing of the mat, it does show wear after awhile and will eventually begin to have lots of nice curves and bends. The team has to program around this which puts them at an advantage when it comes to the variability we sometimes see with challenge sets at competitions. We appreciate the familiarity the constant set up and take down affords the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/SharedRoom2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Carrie Koepke:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet at a gaming store. Our table is hidden under a false top/lid that is placed directly on the walls. Every meeting the boys reassemble the table to begin and remove anything that breaches wall height at the end. It has been an extremely good way to begin/end meetings and encourage some mega-table-familiaritiy. The models travel to and from with the robot and spare parts (also good team building as they load and unload the car).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/SharedRoom3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Debugging Tips</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/06/Debugging-Tips.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Debugging Tips" /><published>2017-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/06/Debugging-Tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/06/Debugging-Tips.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;. One of the participants asked a great question about how teams debug programs. Lots of great ideas shared below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from 
Francis Cariño Belizario:&lt;/b&gt; How do you all debug programs? I think collecting some of our teams’ favorite techniques in one place could be really helpful to new teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Debugging.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Stephanie Ozenne&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when the robot is behaving badly, the first thing my kids would do is inspect the program carefully - it can be easy to enter “12” under motor rotations instead of “1.2” and that makes the program look very different than you expect!
After that inspection, they would make sure they have the correct program downloaded and that they’re not using the “recently run” menu on the bot, which can sometimes throw you off (especially if you’ve recently changed the name of the program!).
After that, they’d check all the wiring and make sure the connections are tight. If a sensor is misbehaving, looking to see if it’s working in “port view” can be helpful.
If the program is &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; not working, they would insert “wait” blocks or sometimes insert a sound block just before or after the part of the program they suspect is doing something strange. Warning: Once my team used this method to make sure a sensor was seeing a line and stopping on it correctly to follow that line. They left the sound block in for a few weeks. When they went to take it out, the robot no longer would stop and find the line correctly! They determined that in the time the sound was playing, the robot had “settled” after it’s stop. Inserting a wait block for the same amount of time that the sound had played restored the expected behavior.
I think once or twice, we have disconnected large chunks of the program “off the beam” to see earlier parts of the program run alone and then add blocks back if the behavior goes back to what we expect.
That’s what I can think of off the top of my head. What do your teams do when the robot is suddenly behaving strangely to find the problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Joseph Gillen:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I insist our programmers label each section of a program with a comment text box–ex, “this block robot turns 90 degrees towards the weight machine”. They can also use it as a “scratch pad” to jot down changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the first question they ask if something goes wonky is, Is it a hardware problem or a software problem? What changes were made?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battery level is also big. Last year they had a heavy bot, which they noticed was a big drag on the battery and the robot would act differently on a full charge vs. a nearly depleted battery. They now check the battery charge often and make sure they ALWAYS charge it when not in use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Sara Hart Chisholm:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most times it’s a hardware problem for us - loose connection, to a loose wheel. Our team has learned to inspect the robot well before jumping to the conclusion that it is the program - especially if they have only been tweaking the program&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Ruth Ann Francis:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My team’s first step is to run the program again so see if the behavior is repeatable. If it’s not, it’s likely something mechanical (wire rubbing on tire or something dragging on the mat) or something with the set-up. If the issue is repeatable, it’s more likely to be a software/programming issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they check to make sure that everything is correct with the robot - right program run, all sensors and motors properly connected and reading correctly, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they check the program. What was the last thing changed? We try to make only one change at a time so that the debugging is easier. Were the correct ports selected? Are the motors going the right direction? Do the values make sense…like the 1.2 vs 12. Are the units correct? (Always check your units! If my structures professor in college taught me anything, it was that once your units are correct, you’re more than likely over halfway there….but, ya know, with something of a Brooklyn/Indian accent.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we still can’t identify the problem, we undo the last change and try it again. If it works, it’s something in the change we made. If not, it’s something with the robot that we missed and it might be time for a reset/reboot (If I’ve learned anything from the programming alpha geek at work it’s that many problems can be solved by rebooting…I also sometimes wonder if he’s not taking that time to fix the thing he realized he screwed up with the last update someone asked him to make. In any event, it often works.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we still can’t figure out what’s wrong, then we start pulling big chunks of code off the beam and adding them back, one or a few at a time until we can figure out what’s wrong (almost always it’s that someone wasn’t paying enough attention when they did one of the troubleshooting steps above). Often times I relate a trouble shooting story from work. More often than not the issue could have been solved by better documentation. (One of these seasons my team is going to trust me that everything is easier when it’s properly documented and actually do it. Until then, I’ll keep telling my stories and sighing exasperatedly and they’ll keep rolling their eyes and promising to update the documentation right away and keep it current and then get distracted talking about the latest super hero movie or video game.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Swati Gupta:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Battery level check&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wire connections check/verify in Port View,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check program: run the myblocks only , select and run specific blocks: tell kids to comment and keep it modular (My Blocks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Travis Smith:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travis Smith A lot of people don’t know this, but if you connect via bluetooth and press the “play” button at the beginning of the program (instead of on the brick) then each block will be highlighted as the robot executes the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Francis Cariño Belizario:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We go to our program, divide the program into the first block and the rest, run the program, add the next block, and so on until we see which part is wrong, fix it, continue coding and testing step by step&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn . One of the participants asked a great question about how teams debug programs. Lots of great ideas shared below.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Act it Out V.2.0</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/05/Act-it-Out-V2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Act it Out V.2.0" /><published>2017-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/05/Act-it-Out-V2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/05/Act-it-Out-V2.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/Pokedragon.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coming to a consensus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing creativity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communicating with each other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making sure everyone has a role&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Box/hat/envelope to hold paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A random collection of objects (paper, cone, hat, bandana, ping pong ball)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
On strips of paper, write out differnt things/processes your team can act out. Fold them so that the team cannot read them when picking one. Place all of them in an envelope/box or spread of a table. Place the random collection of objects in a box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Select one piece of paper without looking at the words on it. Also select one object from the box. As a team, act out whatever is on the paper. You have 5 minutes to plan and act out whatever is one the paper and incorporate the 1 object you picked. Your time begins now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;
This Challenge is a test of the team’s imagination and creativity and decision making skills.
You can come up many different ideas: fish, airplane, carousel, car, explorer in the jungle, shoe factory, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Family LEGO Night: Fundraising Tips</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/05/Family-LEGO-Night-Fundraising-Tips.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Family LEGO Night: Fundraising Tips" /><published>2017-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/05/Family-LEGO-Night-Fundraising-Tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/05/Family-LEGO-Night-Fundraising-Tips.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from 
Jennifer Francis:&lt;/b&gt; Our team is looking at hosting a family Lego night as a fundraiser to buy an extra team robot/computer. Where would we find or how could we get a large amount of Legos to sustain such an event? Does anyone have any suggestions or has anyone done something like this that can offer some tips?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/FamilyLEGONight.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Michael Risch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you near a LEGO store at all? The lego club used to involve builds with giant boxes of LEGO. They might be willing to let you host your night there, using their LEGO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the PTO idea. The problem is that if you are mixing people’s LEGO, folks will be unhappy. Do you have a Barnes &amp;amp; Noble near you? I’m assuming not, but they also have builds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depends on how many kids. At the LEGO Club, 20 or so kids would each build using a single 30x30x30 box (no idea how many pieces fit in there)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Seshan Brothers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the local AFOL (Adult Fan of LEGO) group/LUG (LEGO User Group) in your area might let you borrow LEGO for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Shelby Davis:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also buy bulk Lego on eBay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Katie McCann Kelley:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FYI: The LEGO Store will sell you cases of LEGO Bricks. For example: A case of 2x4 bricks in one color. They also can have single simple machine motors and a battery packs to sell. They are not on the floor- you have to ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Swati Gupta:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think beyond Lego for a Lego night. For example there are Lego candy , Lego moulds with which you can make Lego chocolates , play dough Lego and much more… give them moulds and play dough and let them make lego bricks and then stuff out of it… you can order Lego complaint bricks may be, they will be cheaper.. ppl can bring in some model made out of Lego from their home based on Hydrodynamics theme and you can have a contest of that. Have a big piñata of Lego shape…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Maureen Reilly:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a family night at school with “pocket LEGO” and gave each participant a small bag with 6 bricks and a tiny baseplate and did different timed challenges “build a rocket” “build a dream city” “build an amusement park ride” etc. Yes you can combine with friends… LEGO crayons are great to make and take too w/LEGO molds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Scott Mengle:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also try Craigslist. I know someone who got 40 lb of mixed stuff for $50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jean Findley-William:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past three years each team member researches and develops their own Lego game or challenge and supplies their own Legos as needed. When a child participates in one of the challenges, we give them tickets that they can then redeem at the end of the night for trinkets that we get donated. At this year’s FLN they had a lot of fun with several buildings challenges, a Lego brain puzzle, some Lego minute to win it challenges, remote control soccer bots, an art bot, a cookie icing bot, and Duplo Bridge weight challenge. Everyone kept with their own Legos that they brought for the event. Here is a link to images from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.family-lego-night.bayoubuilders.org/page&quot;&gt;Bayou Builders’ Family LEGO Nights.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Janet Goff Glaze:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try Toys R Us. They host Lego building days and get thousands of small kits in for kids to build, they always have hundreds of left over kits! You can ask them to donate them to your group?? My husband is a manager there &amp;amp; his store always gives away the extra kits!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Erica Morrill:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some good ideas for additional activities &lt;a href=&quot;https://sunflowerstorytime.com/2014/03/07/lego-family-night-2/&quot;&gt; here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really liked the idea of a Lego Family night! I thought we may include a bake sale with ours. Here is my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pinterest.com/ericaannem/lego-family-night/&quot;&gt;Pintrest site&lt;/a&gt; with some of the ideas I found for food items and activities that didn’t require a lot of LEGO.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Transitioning From FIRST LEGO League to other FIRST Programs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/04/Transitioning-From-FIRST-LEGO-League.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transitioning From FIRST LEGO League to other FIRST Programs" /><published>2017-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/04/Transitioning-From-FIRST-LEGO-League</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/04/Transitioning-From-FIRST-LEGO-League.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from 
Francis Cariño Belizario:&lt;/b&gt; Any of your FLL team members also part of an FTC team? Any transition stories?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Transition.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Gloria Gibson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No–although my 4 team members on FTC are all under 14 yrs. old and could be doing FLL–they choose to move up and challenge themselves. It’s not something I recommend for everyone, but when you have some kids that have succeeded in FLL it makes sense to take the next step sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Joseph Gillen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have our FLL teams up until 8th grade, then start FTC in high school. We’re only in our second year of FTC, but the kids with FLL experience are clearly the leaders. We have done it no other way, but this has worked perfectly for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Faith Knudsen Bongiorno&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Double check, students can only be on one roster per season is my understanding from FIRST. We ran into this question of students doing both FLL and FTC last year in SC. My son just transition to FRC for next season. He did FLL from 3rd-8th grades. He looked at both FRC and FTC. He choose FRC because of the mechanical design opportunities. His new team is working on STEM outreach over the summer and fall. It is clear who are former FLL members versus students who have never involved in a FIRST program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Charles Angel:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are in the process of our first transition. Our team of 10 FLL kids won state and advanced to Worlds last season. Only one officially aged out, but we decided to move 7 of them up. We did a three week Summer training with them and saw great interest and motivation / excitement with the new set of challenges. Some of our rookie FLLers this year are old enough to do FTC, however, you can see a difference between those with FLL experience…so we want them to gain some confidence and experience in FLL. This is our first FTC team, so it is a work in progress and we will have more information about the transition in the future. I will be curious to hear and see others input on this topic&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Francis Cariño Belizario:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all replies. I asked because when we did this three years ago, not only was the scheduling a major issue due to conflicts but the biggest problem for us was the transition from “visual programming” to “text programming”. And although we were one of only two middle school teams against 14 high schools, we still won an award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was just introduced to Blockly and highly recommend it as an aid to help FLL kids transition to FTC with regards to proramming.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Act it Out V.1.0</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/07/05/Act-it-Out-V1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Act it Out V.1.0" /><published>2017-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/07/05/Act-it-Out-V1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/07/05/Act-it-Out-V1.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/Juggling.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coming to a consensus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing creativity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communicating with each other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making sure everyone has a role&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Box/hat/envelope to hold paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
On strips of paper, write out differnt things/processes your team can act out. Fold them so that the team cannot read them when picking one. Place all of them in an envelope/box or spread of a table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Select one piece of paper without looking at the words on it. Also select one object from the box. As a team, act out whatever is on the paper. You have 5 minutes to plan and act out whatever is one the paper. Your time begins now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;
This Challenge is a test of the team’s imagination and creativity and decision making skills.
You can come up many different ideas: fish, airplane, carousel, car, explorer in the jungle, shoe factory, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Alternative Programming Languages for the EV3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/06/14/Alternative-Programming-Languages.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alternative Programming Languages for the EV3" /><published>2017-06-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/06/14/Alternative-Programming-Languages</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/06/14/Alternative-Programming-Languages.html">&lt;p&gt;Did you know that you can use alternative programming languages on your EV3?  Here are some useful resources for getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know of other good resources we should add, let us know at team@ev3lessons.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Resources2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;EV3 Basic:&lt;/b&gt; A textual programming language that uses Microsoft Small Basic with an EV3 extension.&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.EV3Basic.com&quot;&gt; EV3 Basic Introduction by EV3Basic.com &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udemy.com/ev3-basic-getting-started/#%2F&quot;&gt; Udemy Video-based Lessons by Nigel Ward &lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3basic.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt; Teaching with Robots: &lt;/a&gt; Lecture Summary&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3basic.blogspot.com/p/materials.html&quot;&gt; Teaching with Robots: &lt;/a&gt; PPTX slides and code&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://onedrive.live.com/view.aspx?resid=B222F4E659AAFCA5!281088&amp;amp;ithint=onenote%2c&amp;amp;app=OneNote&amp;amp;authkey=!ABn7nL9tKUTChd0&quot;&gt; EV3 Programming Using Textual Languages &lt;/a&gt;: Supplemental material by Anthony Orme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Swift:&lt;/b&gt; A multi-purpose programming language created by Apple for iOS. 
&lt;br /&gt;Download App from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/swift-playgrounds/id908519492?mt=8App&quot;&gt; iTunes or App Store &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robotc.net/&quot;&gt; Robot-C &lt;/a&gt;: A C-based programming language for robotics systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ev3dev.org/&quot;&gt;EV3Dev.org&lt;/a&gt;: A Debian Linux-based operating system lets you run many programming languages including Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lejos.org/ev3.php&quot;&gt;leJOS: &lt;/a&gt; A Java virtual machine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.open-roberta.org/en/welcome/&quot;&gt;OpenRoberta: &lt;/a&gt; A free, cloud-based platform for programming EV3 robots.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html">Did you know that you can use alternative programming languages on your EV3?  Here are some useful resources for getting started.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Giant Skis</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/06/05/Giant-Skis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giant Skis" /><published>2017-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/06/05/Giant-Skis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/06/05/Giant-Skis.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/GiantSkis.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coming to a consensus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communicating with each other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning to work together and coordinate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;
Two 8’ 2x4s (or 2x6’s) for a team of 5
Ten 4-5’ lengths of rope (2 per team member) 
Drill with 1” and 3/8” drill bits&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
On strips of paper, write out differnt things/processes your team can act out. Fold them so that the team cannot read them when picking one. Place all of them in an envelope/box or spread of a table. Place the random collection of objects in a box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Let’s go skiing together. Your team has one pair of skis Move across the room or driveway using only the skis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How to construct the skis:&lt;/b&gt;
Starting at one end of each 2x4 (laid flat on the 4” side), mark 6”, 24”, 42”, 60” and 78”, each in the center of the 2x4. Make the same marks on the other 2x4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At each mark, drill halfway (3/4”) with the 1” drill bit. Then, drilling in the center of each 1” diameter hole, drill through the 2x4 with the 3/8” drill bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tie a knot at the end of each piece of rope and feed the other end through the 2x4, larger hole side first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The knots will fit inside the 1” diameter portion of the hole, but not pull through the 3/8” hole.
Flip the skis over – each team member should stand with their rope at their feet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Brickheads&lt;br&gt;Virginia</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Three Hs in FIRST LEGO League</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/05/13/The-3-Hs-in-FIRST-LEGO-League.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Three Hs in FIRST LEGO League" /><published>2017-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/05/13/The-3-Hs-in-FIRST-LEGO-League</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/05/13/The-3-Hs-in-FIRST-LEGO-League.html">&lt;p&gt;In April this year, I did a training course in Janeiro de Cima in Portugal. The course was organized by the Portuguese National Agency of Erasmus+ and, as a delegate from the Netherlands, I was given the opportunity by the Erasmus+ Youth National Agency to participate in this TC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erasmus+ is the European grant program for education, youth and sport. The underlying idea is that investment in education, training and non-formal learning is crucial to give people - regardless of their age or background - the opportunity to continuously develop, or as they say become a lifelong learner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/trophy.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the TC, I once again realized that the First Lego League program is a great program for young people to get acquainted with science and technology in a non-formal way. The program achieves all facets of learning with the Head as well as with the Hand and with the Heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But during the training, I realized that this program is much more focused on the Head and Hands and, unfortunately, far less on the Heart. Within the FLL program, the emphasis is on the teamwork and on the 7 Core Values associated with it. But with that we leave many opportunities unused. For example, the program could also promote issues such as social inclusion and equivalence (*active citizenship) and increase opportunities for peers who are in disadvantaged situations. These young people are disadvantaged because they face personal problems or obstacles that restrict or even exclude their participation in projects. For example: &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people with disabilities (specific needs) &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people with learning difficulties, educational difficulties &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people with a low standard of living and economic barriers &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people for whom language adaptation or cultural integration is a problem, such as migration, refugees, expats &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people with chronic conditions, who are seriously ill or have a psychiatric disorder &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people who are faced with discrimination and social barriers &lt;br /&gt;
• Young people from remote or rural areas or urban problem areas, thus geographical barriers &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program could also promote issues as multilingualism. Multilingualism is one of the cornerstones of the European project and also a powerful symbol of the European Union’s pursuit of unity in diversity. The FLL community makes it possible to contact teams across Europe and the rest of the world. By joining international tournaments, robotics camps or exchanges, we also increase the opportunity for team members to come into contact with foreign languages from a young age, allowing us to promote and facilitate dialogue between young people, language education and linguistic diversity. But this applies not only far way in another country also in own’s own country where it is possible to get in touch with children who speak different languages and come from different cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the FLL program and through Core Values, the importance of personal development, respect and sharing of knowledge has already been well represented, but there should be more emphasis on this. Everyone deserves the opportunity to personal development,  to broaden your horizon, to discover the potential professions and to make full use of learning. This has to be done in a safe environment where everyone is respected and protected. It is therefore that I’m convinced that we should not we exclude young people from the FLL program on the basis of learning performance or things like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now that I see this on paper, I come to the conclusion that all of the above elements that are important for the Erasmus+ program also fit seamlessly into the FIRST LEGO League program. Social integration and equivalence, multilingualism, self-development and security are all elements that fit well in the Heart of the FLL and are more or less already represented. So let us combine these two programs and thus give young people even more and better knowledge and skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I call up to all FLL teams not only to focus on the Head and Hands but also the Heart. Do not limit yourself to the team, teamwork and Core Values, but also look for the international dimension and the possibilities of active citizenship and citizenship participation. This makes the FLL program into a total program that covers a lot more than STEM, with much more to win than an Award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/FLLlogo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dutch primary and secondary schools have been legally obliged to pay attention to active citizenship and social integration since 1 February 2006. The government gives it to the schools themselves how to implement them. Article 8.3 Primary Education Act &amp;amp; Article 17 Secondary Education Act&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Wellink&lt;br&gt;NXT Generation&lt;br&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands</name></author><summary type="html">In April this year, I did a training course in Janeiro de Cima in Portugal. The course was organized by the Portuguese National Agency of Erasmus+ and, as a delegate from the Netherlands, I was given the opportunity by the Erasmus+ Youth National Agency to participate in this TC.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry></feed>
