<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-03-31T19:33:20-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Coach’s Corner</title><subtitle>I am the founder of EV3Lessons</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Weekly Guide: The Preseason</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/03/12/Weekly-Guide-Preseason.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weekly Guide: The Preseason" /><published>2018-03-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/03/12/Weekly-Guide-Preseason</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/03/12/Weekly-Guide-Preseason.html">&lt;p&gt;Many years ago, Norm Kerman, former FIRST LEGO League Tournament Director and FIRST-supporter in Western PA developed a great series of newsletters for teams. When I started out as a rookie coach, I found these immensely helpful for keeping my team on task (more-or-less).  Inspired by Norm’s orignal work, our plan is to create an updated weekly guide. This article is the first in a series. Each week, we will have some advice for where you should be with regards to the Robot, Project and Core Values.  Every team is different and you should feel free to adjust the timelines and activities as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;week-0-the-preseason&quot;&gt;Week 0: The Preseason&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the preseason of FIRST LEGO League. Typically, the theme for the season is announced in late November of the previous calendar year; team registration begins in May of the competition challenge year; and the challenge details are released in August. While starting before the challenge release is not required, taking advantage of the time between seasons can make your team more productive and reduce the stress associated with the season. Overall, the time can be used to learn to program, get a jumpstart on research ideas, and become a better team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good place to start is to start to think about team goals for the coming year. These goals can drive what you want to work on in the pre-season. For instance, perhaps your team would like to learn to use sensors (or a new sensor) this season. Perhaps your team did not do any outreach last season and would like to do something this season. Below, we provide some typical goals and activities in each of the three parts of FIRST LEGO League that teams can work on in the pre-season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;robot&quot;&gt;Robot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rookie teams can start to learn to program and build with MINDSTORMS in the pre-season. This will help save a lot of time during the season as you will not have to work on the challenge at the same time. Experienced teams can use the preseason to develop some new programming skills. A good way to begin is to take a quick survey of what the team knows and does not know. Work with the kids to create a list of must-do programming lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve your building skills, try building some challenging Technic sets together and learn some of the unusual building techniques used in the sets. Purchase some Technic books and have your students build some of those models to gain experience. You can even build some FIRST LEGO League robots and test them out in the summer before the challenge is released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;project&quot;&gt;Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By November of the previous challenge season, FIRST LEGO League has already released a teaser and a brief description of the challenge theme. Since you know what the general topic will be (water, trash, space, etc.), the team can brainstorm about some general problems that might fit the topic. They can also do some preliminary research on those topics. You might even go on some fieldtrips, which are much easier to schedule in the summer while the students are not in school. You may not want to identity a final project topic and create a solution before the challenge is released since the challenge may include constraints on project topics or approach. For example, the Nature’s Fury season specified which natural disasters may be studied and the Senior Solution season required working with a senior citizen as part of the project solution. The goal for the preseason should be to build up some general knowledge about the theme and get an idea of what types of problems might exist. This way, when the challenge is released on August 1st, your team is ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;core-values&quot;&gt;Core Values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help the kids get to know one another.  Do a fun activity together or go on an outing together. Help them start to see each other’s strengths and weaknesses. Introduce the FIRST Core Values early and set up some team rules as well for how the students should interact with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preseason is also a great time to start setting up some outreach events in the community. For example, your team might be able to create a workshop on robotics, FIRST LEGO League or STEM and have it included in a library’s summer program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.firstlegoleague.org/about-fll&quot;&gt;FIRST Core Values&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3lessons.com/corevalues.html?lang=en-us&quot;&gt;Core Value Activities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Asha, Sanjay, Arvind&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA</name></author><summary type="html">Many years ago, Norm Kerman, former FIRST LEGO League Tournament Director and FIRST-supporter in Western PA developed a great series of newsletters for teams. When I started out as a rookie coach, I found these immensely helpful for keeping my team on task (more-or-less).  Inspired by Norm’s orignal work, our plan is to create an updated weekly guide. This article is the first in a series. Each week, we will have some advice for where you should be with regards to the Robot, Project and Core Values.  Every team is different and you should feel free to adjust the timelines and activities as necessary.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Coaching Research Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/03/06/Coaching-Research-Project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coaching Research Project" /><published>2018-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/03/06/Coaching-Research-Project</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/03/06/Coaching-Research-Project.html">&lt;p&gt;In addition to the Robot Game, teams also compete with their research projects. For the Project, teams will choose a problem related to the theme for that year and come up with an “innovative solution” to that problem. Some teams just dream up the idea, others meet with experts and try to get some kind of simple prototype built or designed. It is all welcome in the Project judging room!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/CoachingProject.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;
Image Credit: Razorback Open Invitational&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-to-expect-in-project-judging&quot;&gt;What to expect in Project Judging&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team will have 10 minutes with the Project judges. The first 5 minutes is for the team to present their project to the judges. The five minutes includes any set-up time. During the next 5 minutes, the judges will ask questions. FLL tournaments are designed to celebrate what teams have accomplished – the judges will not be trying to poke holes in your team’s project, they will be trying to assess all that they have accomplished. Teams generally leave the judging sessions feeling like it went great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do your best to make sure the presentation does not run over 5 minutes, including any setup. Practice many times before hte event! Time starts when the team enters the room. The presentation should cover each item on the rubric if possible (rubrics are provided by FIRST each year, definitely refer to them and share them with your team). There are spots on the rubric for creativity, and having a creative presentation is great! It can help the judges to remember you. Communication is essential, though, so make sure your team doesn’t sacrifice clearly communicating what the team has done for being clever or silly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though each team will have a unique project, after seeing 10+ teams over the course of a morning, it can get difficult for judges to remember details about each team. Leaving a 1-page printout with the judges can be helpful. A simplified version of the project poster works well as a summary of the project, and may help remind the judges of your team’s poster, too. Consider having a picture of the team dressed in the tee shirts they will wear at the competition on the page as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-prepare&quot;&gt;How to prepare:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can start in the summer!&lt;/strong&gt;
The project topics are open-ended by design. FIRST wants the kids to be able to follow their interests and find a problem that they are excited about solving! You may read the teaser and think “They’ve got to give us more to go on than this!” only to find that the full challenge really doesn’t specify much more. You can definitely get a head start with your team by researching the topic and looking for problems and solutions just based on the info you get from the “teaser” that FIRST releases in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experts really help!&lt;/strong&gt;
Contact with experts really helps the kids get excited about the topic! Look into your network and the networks of parents on your team and try to find experts that will talk to your team. Even without a network connection, experts are often willing to help teams so be sure to ask. Experts are great at the start, when the team is trying to narrow down the problems they want to try to solve, and later on for feedback on the solution and sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prototypes aren’t required&lt;/strong&gt;
Read the rubric – high performing teams try to develop their project and determine it’s feasibility as much as possible. Do not worry that your team needs a startup-worthy idea for their project! It’s more important that they are excited about the problem they want to solve, and excited about the solution they are developing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presentation skills are important&lt;/strong&gt;
Your team does not need to memorize their presentation, but eye contact is nice so kids should be very familiar with what they are saying so they can look up! The most important thing is that the team should be knowledgeable and excited about the problem and solution that they are working on so they are comfortable explaining and discussing it with adults they don’t know. Be sure the presentation doesn’t go over the 5 minute time limit – some judges will cut them off to preserve time for asking questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;project-deliverables&quot;&gt;Project Deliverables:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over the season:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Learn about theme&lt;br /&gt;
Meet with experts&lt;br /&gt;
Choose a problem&lt;br /&gt;
Develop an innovative solution&lt;br /&gt;
Meet with experts for feedback and sharing&lt;br /&gt;
Develop a 5 minute presentation of our solution for the judges&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take to event:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Project poster (if you make one)&lt;br /&gt;
Team project summary to leave with the judges (a booklet is a good example)&lt;br /&gt;
Props for thepresentation&lt;br /&gt;
Scripts to practice with&lt;br /&gt;
Prototype (if you have one)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stephanie Ozenne&lt;br&gt;Rejecting Reality&lt;br&gt;Utah, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">In addition to the Robot Game, teams also compete with their research projects. For the Project, teams will choose a problem related to the theme for that year and come up with an “innovative solution” to that problem. Some teams just dream up the idea, others meet with experts and try to get some kind of simple prototype built or designed. It is all welcome in the Project judging room!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Coaching Robot Game</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/28/Coaching-Robot-Game.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coaching Robot Game" /><published>2018-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/28/Coaching-Robot-Game</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/28/Coaching-Robot-Game.html">&lt;p&gt;The Robot Game is what most people think of when they think of FIRST LEGO League. The good news about coaching the robot game is that “the kids do the work.” There is plenty for a coach to help with, though!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/CoachingRobot.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-to-expect-in-robot-design-judging&quot;&gt;What to expect in Robot Design Judging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, the team will have 10 minutes with the Robot Design judges, in a room with a robot game table. Some regions do not provide a robot game table. The judges will ask the team to show them some missions that they have solved, and ask questions about their strategy for the robot game and how their programs work. Many regions require a “Robot Design Executive Summary” (RDES) - our team typically makes this on paper to leave with the judges, and sometimes brings in a poster sized version to refer to during their short 4 minute presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seeing 10+ robots over the course of a morning, it can get difficult for judges to remember details about each team, even though they are taking notes! Having a very short (4 minute is the general RDES time limit) presentation that is memorable, and a RDES document to leave behind can help. Consider putting a photo of the team in the shirts they’ll wear at the competition on the sheet you leave with the judges. Tell the judges what you named the robot and why, or pick another short, but memorable story to tell. Be sure that every team member talks to the judges – you don’t want the discussion to be dominated by just one or two team members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the rubric that is provided by FIRST each year to help design your presentation and to let your team know what the judges want to hear about. The judges can’t score you on software if they don’t have anything to see, so bring a computer with the software on it to show them, or print a program or two to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-to-expect-during-the-robot-game-matches&quot;&gt;What to expect during the Robot Game matches&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your team will have three chances to run their robot at the game table. They have 2 minutes and 30 seconds to score as many points as they can. There will also be practice tables at the tournament that your team can sign up for. It is always a goal of mine for there to be no programming at the tournament, but the kids usually find something they want to tune up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the official game table, the kids will have a minute or so to prepare for their run to start. After their run, the referee will score the table, making notes on a score sheet of which missions were done and which were not, and touch or junk penalties if any. The referee will then share this sheet with a team member, walking them through what they have marked. In the unlikely event that your team disagrees with something that the referee has marked, now is the only time they have to make their case. They should know the rules well enough to explain to the referee without you helping (and you shouldn’t help, except perhaps to hand a team member a copy of the rules). Once a member from your team signs the score sheet, it becomes official and no changes can be made. If your team is unsure if a strategy they are using is allowed or not, they can ask the referees in the morning before the robot game even starts and find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If something at the table happens to be set up incorrectly, tournament officials are happy to fix it once you show them in the rules or mission descriptions what the correct setup is. Having the kids inspect the official game tables early in the day is a good idea, as well as looking them over carefully as they prepare for each run. Any time your team needs to communicate with judges or referees, it is best if a team member handles it. It’s good practice for them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-prepare&quot;&gt;How to prepare:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;minimize-direct-suggestions&quot;&gt;Minimize Direct Suggestions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is the most important part of coaching the robot game.&lt;/strong&gt; The kids will learn the best by struggling with and solving problems themselves. Try to ask questions that help them define exactly what the problem is and ask the kids how they think they might solve it, rather than jumping in with a solution that you have seen. This is hard sometimes! There is plenty of room for direct instruction – you can give lessons (or find them online online) about how sensors work, line following, switches and loops in the program, etc. The role of a coach is to give kids tools and then push them to find solutions themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;divide-and-conquer&quot;&gt;Divide and conquer&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easiest for the kids to work in small groups (2-3) and divide up tasks. (We mix the groups for other team tasks so everyone works with everyone else.) On our team that usually means that each set will be working on a different mission run from base, both the programming and attachments for that mission. Sometimes kids will trade missions, though – it’s fluid. It is wonderful if you can have an adult mentor for each small group on the team, but not completely necessary. For our team, the adults do quite a bit of keeping-the-kids-on-task. This is also a good opportunity to support the kids by reminding them of the core values while they are making hard decisions and negotiating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning-the-basics-of-moving-and-sensors&quot;&gt;Learning the Basics of moving and sensors&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Build a basic rover. There are several examples on &lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3lessons.com/robots.html&quot;&gt;EV3Lessons Robot Design.&lt;/a&gt;. It’s perfectly acceptable to start with a basic build and modify with attachments / bumpers as needed for competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, go through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3lessons.com/lessons.html&quot;&gt; programming lessons &lt;/a&gt;on EV3Lessons.com – they are fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go through as many lessons as you can, but soon the team will want to start working on the challenges on the board. That’s great! They can return to EV3Lessons.com when they find skills they wish they had to solve the problems they encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;read-the-rules-and-read-them-again-and-again&quot;&gt;Read the rules (and read them again, and again!):&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Challenge documents are essential. Many teams have a “rules kid” with the job of knowing them inside and out. Print at least one copy of the challenge documents and have them in a binder where the team can refer to them easily. Mark important parts to refer to at an event if they need to. Be sure to keep up with the robot game updates that are released through the season. Some things change every year. Which walls will the mat be pushed against? How tall is base? Is there a junk penalty? How big is the touch penalty? Know the rules and refer to them often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;designing-your-competition-robot&quot;&gt;Designing Your Competition Robot&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluate the board – where are the areas with least clearance that you will want to drive through? Put some constraints on the dimensions of your robot. What kinds of movement will you need from attachments (lifting, pulling, pushing), will your robot be facing the model directly or will the side (or back) of the robot be towards the model? What lines on the board can you use for navigation and/or squaring with light sensors? What other sensors will help you the most? (the limit is usually 4, check the rules every year!) What is another way you can accomplish that task? And another? Come up with enough crazy ideas and one of them may turn out to be brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;begin-with-the-end-in-mind&quot;&gt;Begin with the end in mind:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider starting positions – the more you can rely on sensors, the less your starting position will matter, but usually you’ll need a very consistent starting location for your robot. You only have 2 minutes and 30 seconds for a robot run and time spent lining the robot up and changing attachments eats away at that quickly. Using a jig can help (but remember variation in the tables will change where your jig is exactly located by a few millimeters). Remember that the defined position of the mat can change year to year (centered E/W, docked N or S for the past couple years). Make sure more than one kid on the team knows where the robot starts for each mission!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;work-for-consistency&quot;&gt;Work for consistency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the team (finally!) solves a mission once, we say they have had “an accident.” When that success is repeated, we call it “a coincidence.” When the mission has worked three times in a row, we start to think that we may have a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;choreograph-and-practice-230-robot-runs&quot;&gt;Choreograph and practice 2:30 robot runs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decide what order your missions should be done in. Consider the points each mission will score, but also how difficult the line up is and how difficult attachments are to add or remove – whatever is the most complicated is a good candidate for the first mission, because you have time at the table before the run starts to set it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can only be two kids at the robot table at a time, but they can swap out. Who will be holding what? Do you have attachments that need to be changed? My team regularly takes over 5 minutes the first time they try running all the missions together, but with practice it comes down to under 2:30. Practice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dont-disassemble-important-things&quot;&gt;Don’t disassemble important things!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kids will often build “art” pieces with the LEGO bricks – this tinkering is actually good exploration in my opinion! It’s important to regularly disassemble them, though, to keep pieces in stock for building the main robot. Have a solid method for distinguishing art pieces from attachments that are still a work-in-progress, or you may find something important has been disassembled! (A “Do Not Take Apart” shelf or bin should work, or a “For disassembly” bin.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;troubleshooting&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Troubleshooting is a huge part of the robot game! Whenever someone was having trouble on our team, we’d call out “All eyes on the robot” and get everyone watching – you never know who will see something that helps solve your problem. Your team will develop their own style and methods, but here are some ideas to start with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What changed last? Is this likely to be a software problem or a hardware problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspect the program carefully - it can be easy to enter “12” under motor rotations instead of “1.2” and that makes the program look very different than you expect!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you have the most recent program downloaded and are not using the “recently run” menu on the robot – that can sometimes throw you off (especially if you’ve recently changed the name of the program!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check all the wiring and make sure the connections are tight. If a sensor is misbehaving, looking to see if it’s working in “port view.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insert “wait” blocks or even a sound block just before or after the part of the program suspected of having a problem. Warning: Once my team used this method to make sure a sensor was seeing a line and stopping on it correctly to follow that line. They left the sound block in for a few weeks. When they went to take it out, the robot no longer would stop and find the line correctly! They determined that in the time the sound was playing, the robot had “settled” after it’s stop. Inserting a wait block for the same amount of time that the sound had played restored the expected behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disconnect large chunks of the program “off the beam” to see earlier parts of the program run alone and then add blocks back one by one if the behavior goes back to what we expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battery level can cause changes in behavior. Keep the robot on a charger when it’s not in use, and if you see strange behavior, make sure you have a full battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;online-resources&quot;&gt;Online resources:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share and Learn on Facebook &lt;/a&gt;to get help from other coaches, or use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.usfirst.org/&quot;&gt;FIRST national forums&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources in your area:&lt;/strong&gt;
Some areas have coach training sessions and / or scrimmages for teams. Be sure to connect with your local operational partner to find out what is available in your area. A more experienced team might also be willing to mentor your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;robot-game-deliverables&quot;&gt;Robot Game Deliverables:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over the season:&lt;/strong&gt;
maintain an engineering notebook – the story of our robot&lt;br /&gt;
think about strategy – how does the game board shape our solutions?&lt;br /&gt;
solve robot game missions&lt;br /&gt;
develop a short presentation with the “story of our robot” for the robot design judges&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take to event:­&lt;/strong&gt;
robot design executive summary to leave with judges&lt;br /&gt;
code to share (printed or on computer)&lt;br /&gt;
short presentation – the story of our robot&lt;br /&gt;
robot / attachments / charger / download cable / backup robot / battery&lt;br /&gt;
computer / power supply (have mission model build instructions on computer)&lt;br /&gt;
extra LEGO pieces&lt;br /&gt;
backup of programs&lt;br /&gt;
power strip / extension cord&lt;br /&gt;
printed Challenge document&lt;br /&gt;
photos of robot / attachments in case of damage&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stephanie Ozenne&lt;br&gt;Rejecting Reality&lt;br&gt;Utah, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">The Robot Game is what most people think of when they think of FIRST LEGO League. The good news about coaching the robot game is that “the kids do the work.” There is plenty for a coach to help with, though!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Coaching Core Values</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/23/Coaching-Core-Values.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coaching Core Values" /><published>2018-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/23/Coaching-Core-Values</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/23/Coaching-Core-Values.html">&lt;p&gt;Here is my summary of what I think is essential to coaching Core Values. There is information that may be specific to my region (Utah) as well as some information that may be specific to my team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/CoachingCV.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FIRST LEGO League Core Values set FLL apart from many other competitions. They embody a set of skills that are essential for life and require attention throughout the season. You may hear “the project and the robot game are what we do, the core values are how we do it.” Because of this, working on the Core Values shouldn’t be entirely separated from the other parts of FLL. Coaches should aim to help the kids practice and improve their Core Values skills through all of their work. Coaches should also set a good example for the team by acting in accordance with the Core Values during meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-lego-league-core-values&quot;&gt;FIRST LEGO League Core Values:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a team.&lt;br /&gt;
We do the work to find solutions with guidance from our coaches and mentors.&lt;br /&gt;
We know our coaches and mentors don’t have all the answers; we learn together. &lt;br /&gt;
We honor the spirit of friendly competition.&lt;br /&gt;
What we discover is more important than what we win.&lt;br /&gt;
We share our experiences with others&lt;br /&gt;
We display Gracious Professionalism® and Coopertition® in everything we do.&lt;br /&gt;
We have FUN!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;core-values-judging&quot;&gt;Core Values Judging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About half of their 10 minutes with the Core Values judges will be spent on a team challenge. “Solving” the challenge is not the point – the judges are observing how the team works together. Many teams complete the challenges fairly quietly, which makes it hard for the judges to understand how the team actually works together! Part of Core Values coaching is to help the kids learn to talk more about what they are doing as they go through the challenges, so that an observer will understand how they work together. The team will also make a Core Values Poster to share with the judges and answer questions about how the Core Values are practiced by the team both inside and outside of FLL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, tournament volunteers who observe a team exhibiting positive or negative Core Values throughout the day may relay that information to the judges. Core Values are to be internalized and “lived” by a team, not practiced only in the judging room! This is one of the best elements of FLL, and it makes the atmosphere at tournaments a truly enjoyable place to be. Despite the fact that they are engaged in competition, the teams are looking for opportunities to help each other and share what they’ve learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;team-spirit&quot;&gt;Team Spirit:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are a team” and “We have fun” lead straight into team identity and team spirit. Coaches should help foster this by encouraging team chants and silly “inside jokes” and whatever else arises naturally in the course of meetings. Tee shirts, funny hats or other “costume” ideas, and silly titles can play into this as well. Coaches should follow the kids’ lead while encouraging them to come up with things that encourage team identity and fun. For the event, it’s nice to have a banner or flag or something similar to carry during the parade and decorate the table in the pits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teaching-core-values-directly&quot;&gt;Teaching Core Values Directly:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a week, the team should do a team building activity. Ideally, the activity should be recorded and immediately played back for the team so that they can critique their own performance. It is much more impactful for them to see directly how they are interacting than any feedback you can provide them. There are tons of team building activities online – they don’t need to be fancy or require much in the way of materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teaching-core-values-indirectly-but-kind-of-directly&quot;&gt;Teaching Core Values Indirectly (but kind of directly!):&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All coaches should stay aware of how the team is interacting with one another as they work, and should be ready to help mediate any disagreement with an emphasis on the Core Values. Disagreements will come up in the Project or Robot Game work fairly often. It is by practicing the Core Values at meetings as they navigate the challenges of FLL that the team will really be able to internalize them. Expect slip ups! That’s ok. The point is to continue learning and improving throughout the whole season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;core-values-deliverables&quot;&gt;Core Values Deliverables:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team does the work, the coach reminds them a million times to get it done. If the team has older / more mature members, you could assign some of these items to a team leader. Then the coach would only have to remind that team member and see if they need help with something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the season:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn the Core Values&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practice Core Values while executing Project and Robot game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do specific Core Values activities and improve communication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If possible, meet with / help / collaborate with another team or a Jr. FLL team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop a 2 min Core Values presentation (optional, depends on your region)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop a team cheer / chant, come up with a team tshirt/hat (optional, depends on your team)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take to event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Core Values poster&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Team core values summary to leave with judges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Props / scripts / presentation materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giveaways to share with other teams­&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Team spirit / cheering items (balloons, megaphones, pennants, whatever)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pit decorations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Banner / flag for the parade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;websites&quot;&gt;Websites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3lessons.com/corevalues.html&quot;&gt;EV3Lessons.com Core Values Activities by many FLL teams&lt;a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.startingpoints.com/fll&quot;&gt;FLL Starting Point Core Values Activities by the Judge Advisor from VA-DC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ventureteambuilding.co.uk/team-building-activities/&quot;&gt;Venture Team Building&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.odysseyofthemind.com/practice/&quot;&gt;Odyssey of the Mind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://usscouts.org/games/game_t.asp&quot;&gt;Boy Scout Team Building Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://smallbiztrends.com/2015/09/team-building-exercises-and-games.html&quot;&gt;24 Team Buiding Games and Exercises&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://yfcu.org/uploads/file/Games%2520booklet%25202007.pdf&quot;&gt;Young Farmers Games &amp;amp; Activity Booklet&lt;a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other: Anonobots FLL team has activities shared on their Facebook page, Cadmes Creators shares 29 activities in Dutch on their team page&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stephanie Ozenne&lt;br&gt;Rejecting Reality&lt;br&gt;Utah, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">Here is my summary of what I think is essential to coaching Core Values. There is information that may be specific to my region (Utah) as well as some information that may be specific to my team.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Benefits of FIRST LEGO League</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/21/Benefits-of-FIRST-LEGO-League.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Benefits of FIRST LEGO League" /><published>2018-02-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/21/Benefits-of-FIRST-LEGO-League</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/21/Benefits-of-FIRST-LEGO-League.html">&lt;p&gt;What are the benefits of particiating in FIRST LEGO League? What skills witll the children learn? How can we, as coaches, help them achieve these skills? These are the questions that I tackle in this Coach’s Corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Benefits.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FIRST LEGO League teams spend a lot of time in the program. So the first question that comes to mind is Why do we spend so much time doing this? What are the benefits?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through FIRST LEGO League, team members will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) learn about robotics&lt;br /&gt;
2) learn to build and program&lt;br /&gt;
3) learn engineering skills&lt;br /&gt;
3) learn to work as a team&lt;br /&gt;
4) develop research skills&lt;br /&gt;
5) develop presentation skills&lt;br /&gt;
6) learn to negotiate&lt;br /&gt;
7) learn the importance of cooperation (Coopertition and Gracious Professionalism)&lt;br /&gt;
8) learn how to communicate with experts, judges, and each other&lt;br /&gt;
9) learn to set goals&lt;br /&gt;
10) learn to deal with deadines and cruch time&lt;br /&gt;
11) learn to cope with failure&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our job as coaches is to support and guide the team so they can make progress on all of these things in a fun environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coach-goals&quot;&gt;Coach Goals:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;keep-the-fll-experience-positive-and-fun&quot;&gt;Keep the FLL experience positive and FUN!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of pressure and frustration built into the challenges of FLL – it is by design, to teach the kids to make hard trade offs and to keep working even though things will never be “perfect.” Keeping things fun in the pressure-cooker that is FLL is not always easy, but we can try!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;support-each-of-the-learning-opportunities-listed-above&quot;&gt;Support each of the learning opportunities listed above.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coaches can provide instruction in general towards each goal and then the team will apply that knowledge to their FLL work. For example, we will teach them presentation and communication skills, and let them apply those skills when they create their FLL presentations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;prepare-the-team-with-an-eye-towards-advancement-because-tournaments-are-fun&quot;&gt;Prepare the team with an eye towards advancement, because tournaments are fun!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communication with the judges is possibly the most important part of meeting this goal, so learning communication and presentation skills is essential. It is easy for the presentations to get left to the last minute, but they are too important to let that happen. The judges can’t know how much your team has accomplished unless your team is effective in communicating that with them!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stephanie Ozenne&lt;br&gt;Rejecting Reality&lt;br&gt;Utah, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">What are the benefits of particiating in FIRST LEGO League? What skills witll the children learn? How can we, as coaches, help them achieve these skills? These are the questions that I tackle in this Coach’s Corner.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is in a Logo?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/07/What-is-in-a-Logo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is in a Logo?" /><published>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/07/What-is-in-a-Logo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/07/What-is-in-a-Logo.html">&lt;p&gt;Team names and logos represent who you are.  They are fun to come up with and a great way of representing the team. They are inspired by where you live, what you enjoy, schools and organizations you are affiliated with, and more.  Read below to learn about some FIRST-related logos and their origins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/TeamLogo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ev3lessons-logo-more-than-what-it-seems&quot;&gt;EV3Lessons Logo: More than what it seems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EV3Lessons was founded by FIRST team, Not the Droids You Are Looking For. We came up with the EV3Lessons logo early in the 2014 World Class Season.  The EV3 was made to look like to faces looking at each other and learning from each other to match our tag line. One face is green and the other is purple to represent us (Sanjay and Arvind) as it is our favorite colors. We made the “L” in Lessons into a road because learning is journey/path you take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/ev3lessonslogo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-logo&quot;&gt;FIRST Logo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does the FIRST logo mean anything? Yes, it does. This image linked was shared with us by Alex Stout, mentor to the MARS FRC team in West Virginia.  The FIRST Logo is inspired by the Olympics logo as well as Archimedes’ study of the cone, sphere and cylinder. Thus, it combines both elements of sports and mathematics.  Click to read all about the &lt;a href=&quot;/images/coachcorner/FIRSTLogo.jpg&quot;&gt;FIRST Logo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xanterra-fll-making-you-think&quot;&gt;Xanterra FLL: Making you think&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team Xanterra FLL has roots in a local elementary where the mascot is a raccoon. When they competed there they called themselves Procyon Lotor, which is the scientific name for a raccoon. They enjoyed the way the name was a conversation starter &amp;amp; when they left elementary school &amp;amp; became a community team, they wanted a name that people had to think about. After looking up many words &amp;amp; roots in many languages, they landed on Xanterra. Xan comes from Greek, Alexander, meaning protector. Terra is Latin, meaning Earth. Their logo shows a string of children, hand in hand, around the Earth, protecting it. The team wears collared shirts over their team t-shirts &amp;amp; have capes to represent themselves as undercover superheroes, protecting the earth with their smarts &amp;amp; innovative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;robosquids-inspired-by-a-passion&quot;&gt;Robosquids: Inspired by a passion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team is Robosquids. When we started the team two years ago, we asked the boys what they wanted to name it. My son came up with Robosquids since he is obsessed with fishing and squids. His friend and team mate liked it so it stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thingaling-inspired-by-girl-scouts&quot;&gt;Thingaling: Inspired by Girl Scouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a brand new team of 6 Girl Scouts ages 11-14, who came together (from 4 different troops plus 2 girls new to GS altogether!) to form a team! No previous robotics experience including the coach! The girls came up with suggestions for a team name, voted, then one of the girls designed the logo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pink-piranhas-inspired-by-an-frc-team&quot;&gt;Pink Piranhas: Inspired by an FRC team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big sister was on an FRC team called The Pink Team … she mentored our brand new FLL team so I asked the kids to come up with a name that was “Pink &lt;strong&gt;__&lt;/strong&gt;”. We live in FL and there was a flock of giant pelicans that had taken up residence in the pond next to the school during a cold snap and the kids were fascinated with them. So my son and his team picked Pink Pelicans. Little sister started a FLL team the next year they picked Pink Piranhas and several members have younger siblings that started a FLL Jr team and they are Pink Pythons. 😊💕 Big sis is an artist so she designed the logo/mascots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brainiacs-maniacs-inspired-by-girl-scouts&quot;&gt;Brainiacs Maniacs: Inspired by Girl Scouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name was voted on by the original team 5 years ago amongst various contenders. They decided to keep the name to build the “brand” and it has become well known locally, along with their use of various pink accessories which change very year (e.g. bows, hats, capes, suspenders, etc.). The logo was designed by one of the original team members and incorporates the Girl Scout trefoil as they are a Girl Scout sponsored team and also represent the brain growing due to FIRST. This year they modified to include the first name of each team member, which was a great addition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;edisonian-bots-inspired-by-a-famous-person&quot;&gt;Edisonian Bots: Inspired by a famous person&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Team 24731, Edisonian Bots. We are a team of homeschoolers, inspired by Thomas Edison who was also homeschooled. We also live in Fort Myers, FL where Edison spent many winters. Our logo incorporates the EV3 (as the robot’s body) and features several lightbulbs as a nod to Edison. The logo was designed by two of our teammates last season. 💡&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;robowarrior-inspired-by-a-local-sports-team&quot;&gt;Robowarrior: Inspired by a local sports team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First meeting of the team, kids decided upon the name Robo Warriors, the main reason at that time: It was basketball season and home team Golden State Warriors was doing pretty good. All of them were fans and following the team. The name grew on them and they wanted an identity beyond GSW, they decided upon a warrior robot. Kids designed a basic design and then we got it designed from a professional on fiverr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chicks-with-bricks-inspired-by-the-girl-scouts&quot;&gt;Chicks with Bricks: Inspired by the Girl Scouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team is an all girl team of Girl Scouts. The girls all brainstormed ideas for team names and voted to select the winner “Chicks with Bricks”! Once we had a name, we had the kids all sketch up their ideas for logos and then the girls voted on the winner. Their team identity is all about GIRL POWER!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hot-squad-inspired-by-superheros&quot;&gt;H.O.T. Squad: Inspired by superheros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are the H.O.T. Squad (heroes of tomorrow). This has been our team name for two years. Kids picked it and designed the logo. They are good role models and do a lot of outreach as individuals and as a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nerds-inspired-by-a-school-name&quot;&gt;NERDS: Inspired by a school name&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a school based team (well, collection of teams). Our school is named North, so the kids our first year came up with North Nerds. Then we decided to make NERDS an acronym, so we became the “North Engineering Robotics Design Squad” . We field 3 teams each year, and the kids shift around (again, school team) so each year the teams come up with their own spin on NERDS. Some of my favorites have been “NERDS who say Ni!”, “NERDS in Shining Armor”, “Despicable NERDS” and “NERDS Sharknado”. Some teams choose to go with something project related- so this year we had the “Salty NERDS”. Our logo was designed our first year and is our robotics room mascot: a little robot with a wrench in hand and a star-cut out on its belly (our school “mascot” is Stars).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;21st-century-space-guys-inspired-by-an-interest-in-space&quot;&gt;21st Century Space Guys: Inspired by an interest in space&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a neighbourhood team in Kentville, Nova Scotia, Canada. Our team name started with a discussion of being the 1980s something space guys, but then it was pointed out that no one in the room had been born in the 80s. So… they shifted to the 21st Century Space Guys. At the time the team was all male, but even last year when a young lady joined our team she didn’t mind. Our robot’s name is Hadfield who is named after Col. Chris Hadfield - a real 21st Century Space Guy for Canada. Our logo was done by one of our team members. It is a take off of the Lego classic space guys logo. He redrew it a bit so it wasn’t copying it. We have had pins made and we have a banner too. Our t-shirts add to our team identity in that each member is a colour of a classic space minifigure. I, as the coach, get to wear green.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA</name></author><summary type="html">Team names and logos represent who you are.  They are fun to come up with and a great way of representing the team. They are inspired by where you live, what you enjoy, schools and organizations you are affiliated with, and more.  Read below to learn about some FIRST-related logos and their origins.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIRST LEGO League Deliverables</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/05/FIRST-LEGO-League-Deliverables.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIRST LEGO League Deliverables" /><published>2018-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/05/FIRST-LEGO-League-Deliverables</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/02/05/FIRST-LEGO-League-Deliverables.html">&lt;p&gt;This article provides one coach’s view of what a team needs to accomplish in one season of FIRST LEGO League. It is intended to provide a new coach a high-level view of what their team needs to work on during the season. Check with your tournament director for any region-specific requirements. Some regions give more or less time for presentations. Others do not require or have presentations at all. The most important deliverable for any team is to HAVE FUN!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Deliverables.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list started with my packing list for a tournament. I then expanded it to include the things we do throughout the season. The kids will do the work, but the coaches (that’s you!) will do the organization, scheduling, facilitation, and teaching of specific needed skills. The skills include mechanical design and programming of robots of course, but also writing a coherent presentation, talking to experts, sharing information with judges and other interested parties, teamwork, effective negotiation and communication within the team, strategy, time management, and how to have fun while doing all of that. Some things on a single line will take up enormous amounts of time, like the robot game, and the research project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;core-values&quot;&gt;Core Values:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;over-the-season&quot;&gt;Over the season:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Come up with a team cheer / chant (Team cheers are not required, but can be a great way to show spirit)
2) Learn the Core Values
3) Practice Core Values while executing Project and Robot game
4) Do specific Core Values activities and improve communication
5) If possible, meet with / help / collaborate with another team or a Jr. FLL team
6) Develop a 2 min presentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-to-event&quot;&gt;Take to event:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Core Values poster (optional in some regions)
2) Team core values summary to leave with judges
3) Props / scripts / presentation materials
4) Giveaways to share with other teams
5) Team spirit / cheering items (balloons, megaphones, pennants, whatever)
6) Pit decorations
7) Banner / flag for the parade (Some regions have team parades)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;project&quot;&gt;Project:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;over-the-season-1&quot;&gt;Over the season:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Learn about theme
2) Meet with experts
3) Choose a problem
4) Develop an innovative solution
5) Meet with experts for feedback and sharing
6) Develop a 5 min presentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-to-event-1&quot;&gt;Take to event:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Project poster board
2) Team project summary to leave with the judges
3) Props / scripts / presentation
4) Solution prototype (if your team has one)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;robot-game&quot;&gt;Robot Game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;over-the-season-2&quot;&gt;Over the season:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Maintain an engineering notebook – the story of our robot (This is not required and does not have to be as detailed as those created in FTC or FRC, but documenting your design is helpful)
2) Think about strategy – how does the game board shape our solutions?
3) Solve robot game missions
4) Develop a 4min presentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-to-event-2&quot;&gt;Take to event:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Robot design executive summary (RDES) to leave with judges
2) Code to share (printed or on computer)
3) Short presentation – the story of our robot (Some regions require a 4 minute RDES presentation)
4) Robot / attachments / charger / download cable
5) Computer / power supply (have mission model build instructions on computer)
6) Extra LEGO elements
7) Backup of programs
8) Power strip / extension cord
9) Printed Challenge document
10) Small table (Some regions ask teams to bring their own table for keeping parts during the robot runs)
11) Have photographs of robot and attachments in case of damage along the way&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other&quot;&gt;Other&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-to-event-3&quot;&gt;Take to event:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Snacks for the team
2) Pens / paper / tape / scissors / clipboard
3) Consider food – is it available at tournament? Bag lunch? Go get pizza?
4) Presentation skills!
5) Card games or small activities to pass the time
6) Bring your social skills - go talk to other teams and make new friends&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;year-end-party&quot;&gt;Year-end party&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Trophies or other items for each team member (choose, design, purchase, build)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stephanie Ozenne&lt;br&gt;Rejecting Reality&lt;br&gt;Utah, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">This article provides one coach’s view of what a team needs to accomplish in one season of FIRST LEGO League. It is intended to provide a new coach a high-level view of what their team needs to work on during the season. Check with your tournament director for any region-specific requirements. Some regions give more or less time for presentations. Others do not require or have presentations at all. The most important deliverable for any team is to HAVE FUN!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Segue From FLL to FRC</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/01/16/Segue-From-FLL-to-FRC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Segue From FLL to FRC" /><published>2018-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/01/16/Segue-From-FLL-to-FRC</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2018/01/16/Segue-From-FLL-to-FRC.html">&lt;p&gt;“Combining the excitement of sport with the rigors of science and technology, FIRST Robotics Competition is the ultimate Sport for the Mind(TM), where imagination and innovation come together! By combining the excitement of sport and beauty of art with the rigors of science and technology, teams of high school students (ages 14 - 18/grades 9 - 12) are challenged to design a team ‘brand,’ hone teamwork skills, and build and program robots to perform tasks against a field of competitors.  Participants call it the ‘hardest fun you’ll ever have.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time we saw a FIRST Robotics Competition (FRC) robot up close and personal was at the World Championship in St. Louis, April 2017. It was love at first sight. The robots’ speed and finesse was impressive. FRC pits were abuzz with focused team members wearing Nascar-type shirts using all sorts of power tools. And the fast-paced, spontaneous nature of the Steamworks game had us mesmerized. Making the segue from FLL to FRC was a natural next step. The really cool thing about FRC is all skill levels are welcome and needed, technical and non-technical. If you are thinking about transitioning from FLL to FRC, here’s what you need to know and consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Worldchangers2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When transitioning from FLL to FRC, the first year will be the toughest. You may use some of the same strategies you used in FLL, but you will have to learn about a new program, challenge, building system and game aspects.  Programming changes from visual programming to text programming.  By no means is our list exhaustive.  Consider interviewing FRC teams at a nearby FRC Regional Tournament to know what may be ahead and how to prepare. It’s normal to sometimes feel overwhelmed, frustrated and even lost. Coopertition is the essence of FIRST. As you learn and grow, be sure to glean knowledge and insights from other teams. Know that with each year of experience things will make more sense and you will be better equipped to handle the challenges that come your way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FRC teams operate like a business.  Team members are expected to conduct themselves like professionals, knowledgeable in aspects of their team.  Presentations are formal like business proposals.  FRC tournaments are competitive, fast-paced and fun! Retain your FLL Core Values and you’ll have a great season!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;required-skills&quot;&gt;Required Skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All students welcome to participate in FRC, with or without special skills. Both technical and non-tecnical skills are needed. Whatever you are good at – there is a place for you. Whatever you are willing to learn – there is a place for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible sub-teams include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing/digital prototyping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strategists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electronics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Metalworking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scouting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Graphic design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Website creation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aptitude for science, technology, engineering, math, physics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knack for problem-solving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appreciation for power tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public speaking/presenting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photography/videography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marketing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creative writing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social media&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Event planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fundraising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Branding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project managers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cheerleaders and even Glitter Captains (a.k.a. Team spirit)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘This is the only sport where if you show up, you can play.’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;committment&quot;&gt;Committment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team members complete from January through April. Mentors and adult volunteers lend their time and talent to provide guidance to the team. They meet several times per week. There is a six-week build time from early January through mid-February. After this, teams bag and tag the robot and do not touch it again until the first competition. Each season culminates with district and regional events where qualifying teams compete for awards and a spot at the FIRST Championship in Houston, TX or Detroit, MI. Seasoned teams actually meet throughout the school year. They use the summer for fundraising and outreach. There are also several off-season optional competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tips:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be prepared to spend some nights and weekends helping your team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You, your family, and your schedule will determine how much time you can devote&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Like any school activity, the more time you invest, the better you will become.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;team-basics&quot;&gt;Team Basics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A team is composed of ten or more high school-aged students willing to put in time to do any job the team needs to succeed. There are lots of important jobs available for all skill levels and interests. You will need to find a suitable meeting place that includes adequate space to design and build an industrial-sized robot (about 150 lbs.). You will need access to a variety of machine shop power tools, a standard kit of parts and a common set of rules issued by FIRST. Many teams fabricate their own parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two or more adult Mentors are needed for each team, with both technical and non-technical expertise. They must be willing and motivated to coach the team through the build and competition season, and beyond. Community sponsors will be needed to help fund your efforts and provide other support. You will also need to have the desire to learn, explore, strategize, build camaraderie, share ideas and talents, make new friends, be accepted, and HAVE FUN!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-frame&quot;&gt;Time Frame&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FIRST Robotics Competition teams register in the fall. However, the official season begins when the season’s Challenge is announced at a Kickoff ceremony the first Saturday in January. Teams are given six weeks to create their robot. District and Regional competition events start in late February and continue through April. Teams that qualify are invited to FIRST Championship one of the last two weeks of April. Off-season events to strategize, hone skills, learn new technology, meet other teams, and have fun are common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cost&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost varies from team to team and region to region depending on what level of participation the team chooses. The annual fees for team registration, a robot kit of parts, and event participation are $5,000 - $6,000. Additional costs for travel, food, team shirts and other optional items will vary. FIRST offers many fundraising opportunities and teams are encouraged to create their own. Grants are also available, as well as sponsorships provided locally, regionally and nationally by many corporations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>World Changers&lt;br&gt;Iowa, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">“Combining the excitement of sport with the rigors of science and technology, FIRST Robotics Competition is the ultimate Sport for the Mind(TM), where imagination and innovation come together! By combining the excitement of sport and beauty of art with the rigors of science and technology, teams of high school students (ages 14 - 18/grades 9 - 12) are challenged to design a team ‘brand,’ hone teamwork skills, and build and program robots to perform tasks against a field of competitors.  Participants call it the ‘hardest fun you’ll ever have.’”</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy Holidays</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/12/16/Happy-Holidays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy Holidays" /><published>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/12/16/Happy-Holidays</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/12/16/Happy-Holidays.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/Gifts.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaborating on a physical task&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coordinating movements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Boxes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wrapping Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scissors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tape&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
Leave items on table jumbled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Your team has to wrap as many gifts as possible in 10 minutes. Each member of the team can only do one task (and only touch that one item - paper, scissors, tape, box).  Work together to wrap as many presents as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;
1) If you have a larger team, add some more items such as ribbons, name on the gift, etc.
2) Make the task longer if you need to.
2) Variations: Wrap the present but everyone can only use one hand, one blindfolded is the only one allowed to wrap (everyone else can see), wrap without talking.  (Credit for alternative ideas: Karla Stevens)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Seshan Brothers&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tools for Teams</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Tools-For-Teams.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tools for Teams" /><published>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Tools-For-Teams</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/12/16/Tools-For-Teams.html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I asked teams about what tools they would recommend for other teams. Here are the results of the discussion on Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.  If you would like to share any more, send an email to team@ev3lessons.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Tools.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Calendar - Team Scheduling &lt;br /&gt;
Google Group - Team Mailing Lists &lt;br /&gt;
Google Drive - Shared Team Files &lt;br /&gt;
Trello - Team organization &lt;br /&gt;
Redbooth - Taking Notes &lt;br /&gt;
OneNote and OneDrive - Notes and Shared Documents &lt;br /&gt;
Slack - Tracking Progress, Documenting &lt;br /&gt;
EV3Lessons Robot Game Scorer - Tracking Scores &lt;br /&gt;
Basecamp - Project Management &lt;br /&gt;
Fleep - Messaging &lt;br /&gt;
Whatapp - Team communication &lt;br /&gt;
iMovie&lt;br /&gt;
iBrainstorm&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Asha Seshan&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, USA&lt;br&gt;</name></author><summary type="html">A few weeks ago, I asked teams about what tools they would recommend for other teams. Here are the results of the discussion on Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .  If you would like to share any more, send an email to team@ev3lessons.com.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry></feed>
