<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-18T14:38:34-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Coach’s Corner</title><subtitle>I am the founder of EV3Lessons</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Straw Transfer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/12/Straw-Transfer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Straw Transfer" /><published>2017-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/12/Straw-Transfer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/corevalues/2017/08/12/Straw-Transfer.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CoreValues/StrawTransfer.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coordinating a physical activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Materials:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bendable straws (one per team member)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A cardboard ring (4-5cm diameter) (or lightweight ring of any type)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Setup:&lt;/b&gt;
Leave items on table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instructions to Team:&lt;/b&gt;
Each student should take a straw and bend it. Place the long end in your mouth. One student should add the ring to theirs. Now transfer the ring to each person without the use of any hands&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;
How did the team communicate and coordinate to move the ring from person to person.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Cadmes Creators&lt;br&gt;The Netherlands</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Record Keeping in FIRST LEGO League</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/12/Engineering-Journal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Record Keeping in FIRST LEGO League" /><published>2017-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/12/Engineering-Journal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/12/Engineering-Journal.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions from Amanda Espy Barbulescu: Do any teams use a form to record what’s been done during their meetings, in terms of robot design/building/programming/missions? If so, would you mind sharing it? Do you do it electronically or on paper?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineering Journals are not required in FIRST LEGO League, but some for of record keeping can be useful.  Take a look at some of the examples and ideas below. Some teams type up their notes and some teams hand write them. Some teams will print them out and place in a binder, while others will use a school notebook. There is no right or wrong way. Do what is best for your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/EngineeringJournal.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image Credit: Bayou Builders from Louisiana&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Francis Cariño Belizario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both our teams used both an engineering book (which we simply call diary) to be less intimidating. They are supposed to write anything they did/thought to do. They take pics as well with ipads/phones, choose a few, print them out and attach them to the diary. They also made a video diary of how they designed and built the base robot and the attachments. This served as training before they went to classrooms to present both the missions and their research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Jessi Scott&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are pictures from the BinaryMcBrickBots’ logs. Taking these pictures is the first time I’ve touched them.
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/EngineeringJournal2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Faith Knudsen Bongiorno&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams I work with are required to keep written log, in pen, and needs to have date, members present, goals for meeting, and what was achieved. Any notes for next meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Gloria Gibson (Florida)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have copy here–they are at school but what we do for technical is lots of drawings, prototyping etc and pictures to document. Prior to programming, we use photo maps to layout robot paths, which missions to combine and what sensors they would use–this helps with robot build to make sure we put sensors in correct places and sizing of robot for spaces they want to travel. Once robot is built for programming, I have a form that has blocks for each move robot makes–any changes are logged in the blocks……some are simple like charting how many rotations for turns (rookie team) or degrees for gyro turns. This allows team to pick up next meeting and if something isn’t correct–they already know what worked/didn’t work. I feel that documentation is one of the best tools we can teach future engineers–it’s also worth noting that the team has been recognized many times by judges for their extensive documentation–one team even received Judges Award at Legoland California for their engineer notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Seshan Brothers (Pennsylvania)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encourage teams to keep to some form of documentation (whatever works best for the team). Sometimes, it is a notebook or binder. It can be handwritten or printed. Here is an example of what we give out to teams we mentor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/EngineeringJournal3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Asha Seshan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bayou Builders from Louisiana provide great examples for an Engineering Notebook on their Facebook page. These ideas are shared here with their permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/EngineeringJournal4.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/EngineeringJournal5.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">To Rebuild or Not to Rebuild</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/11/To-Rebuild-or-Not-to-Rebuild.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Rebuild or Not to Rebuild" /><published>2017-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/11/To-Rebuild-or-Not-to-Rebuild</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/11/To-Rebuild-or-Not-to-Rebuild.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;should-you-keep-your-robot-from-year-to-year-or-should-you-redesign-each-year&quot;&gt;Should you keep your robot from year to year, or should you redesign each year?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/DroidBot.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Layne Kirk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New one each year. They might use some of the same concepts or attachments, but they start from scratch on the base. We think it’s valuable from a robot design standpoint, too - that they aren’t just piggybacking last season’s successes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Don Tippet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all depends. Some years, the mat requires a more compact robot to move around mission models. One year, there was a guide wire you had to go under, so we designed a shorter robot. Last year, we took the robot from the previous year and made minor modifications so that it could go over the railroad tracks. I’ve done this six years, and I think last year was the first time we used a majority of the previous year’s bot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Noah J Revoy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of a season I have the kids sort the robots back into the box. Next year we start again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Ryan Evans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often we refine our base robot. We look at what was good about last year’s robot and what we found annoying or felt was lacking. We only had a front mount motor these past two years, which makes any motorised attachments hang out front or need a complex gearing system to connect to side and rear mounted contraptions. This year’s will have a second motor up back and possibly a different mounting system, subject to what the kids pick up on from our design discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Ben Stanley&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned lessons from last year’s robot and designed a new one. Then compared side by side. We try to retain the strengths of the old one, and improve the weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Gloria Gibson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We keep past years for demo and build new for season. I would think that it would depend on who your returning team is–if it’s the same team, then the robot is their creation, if not, I think it’s very important for team members to rebuild and create their own ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Faith Knudsen Bongiorno&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very important because in judging the team may get a judge who ask where the design came from, which members of the team participated, etc. Another perspective to remember is teams need to give credit, and let’s the judges know they were inspired by previous year’s team, ev3lessons, fllcast, etc. specially when they use the information off the internet. We have access to plethora of design information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Seshan Brothers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new robot every year…even different wheels every year. It’s important and fun to explore and test new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Jean Findley-Williams&lt;/strong&gt; We have to use the previous season’s robot to create a base robot for our summer camps each year. Last year, we had the team start using Lego Digital Designer to document their robot build and attachments. This adds a great planning element…especially most of the team would tell you that they prefer not to draw. Since many of our team members also want to move on to FTC and FRC, we thought having them start to think their builds out in this way would help them transition. It’s also a great way to look back at different builds (both the successes and not so much) and improve on different components. The team really seems to appreciate the purpose behind this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Mark Nicolussi&lt;/strong&gt; 
Same with different attachments - we are a school group that only meets in the fall - last year we had less than 2 months to prepare for our local competition - it would not be feasible to build from scratch each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Carrie Koepke&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They analyze the robot post-season, test new from scratch theories over the summer, and build new again when they see the new needs for mission models. They have saved some arms or design features each season, but they tend to be reference instead of reuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Celina McGinnis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tear down every year. There are always a few new kids on my teams, and this makes it theirs from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Shena Leonard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New and improved each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Riley Mathiasen&lt;/strong&gt; 
 I would recommend keeping the elements of the design that you like, while re-designing the parts that you think need improvement. Also, always take pictures of your robot for future reference before you take apart your bot. After all, pictures are free nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Useful Parts and Where to Get Them</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/10/Useful-Parts-to-Own.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Useful Parts and Where to Get Them" /><published>2017-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/10/Useful-Parts-to-Own</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/10/Useful-Parts-to-Own.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-some-useful-extra-parts-a-team-should-have-where-can-these-be-bought&quot;&gt;What are some useful extra parts a team should have? Where can these be bought?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of great ideas about what individual parts to buy, which Technic sets can be useful and where to buy them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/bucketwheel.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image Credit: LEGO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Asha Seshan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coaches have often asked me what parts I buy my team. I keep an eye out on the sorted bins. The ones that seem to be depleted the most are the parts I replace first - different length beams, Ls, Ts are common. As your team gets more experienced, you might notice that they are looking for different parts. Most of our extra parts were purchased from Bricklink. A select few parts were from Lego Education. People also use Brickowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Erin Kendall&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been looking on Craigslist and ebay for bulk purchases. Would love to hear other options as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Swati Gupta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till now, I also look at Bricklink first, then eBay. Sensors from Lego Education. In hurry, Amazon Prime comes in handy. I ordered universal joints, panel plates, and 5M beams . We ran out of them last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Shelby Davis&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lego.com/en-us/service/replacementparts/sale&quot;&gt;LEGO’s Bricks and Pieces&lt;/a&gt; also works well when there are no good vendors on Bricklink: 5x7 frames, half width beams, 3 length combo pins / axles, knob wheels (for 90 degree power delivery on axles). Pieces not in the kits that I’m stocking up on soon: LEGO Axle Pin 3 (11214) (1 length axle, 2 length pin) and LEGO Axle 2m with Pin with Friction (18651) (2 length axle, 1 length pin)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Ryan Evans&lt;/strong&gt; 
The Bucket Wheel Excavator (LEGO set 42055) represents EXCELLENT value for money. Some of the parts in it can go for as much as $5 a piece (5*7 frames, panels) and there are a bucket load of them (pun intended). I worked out that the frames alone worked out at AUD $250, so the rest of that pack for $150??? Bargain. Other large technic sets are great also. Panels, larger wheels, newer universal joints…. Lotd&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Mic Lowne&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes bricklink all the way but if you’re after a massive influx of pieces consider buying a kit like the bucket excavator. Sometimes having a range of strange pieces inspires the students to think differently about how they can solve a problem (plus you get to build a cool model first as a team building session)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Ian Woods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We bought the Bucket Excavator kit. Part for part, it seemed a really inexpensive (although big-kit-pricey) way of getting a load of useful parts. linear actuators, 50 O-frames, 75 -15M beams, panels, etc. A stupid number of pegs. Great fun to build in the off-season too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Angela Wellink&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used a lot of parts from the old mission sets, we hardly ever bought extra parts. In The Netherlands it is very hard to find a good store for extra individual parts. Most teams buy them from over seas, witch make them even more expensive. Over the 10 years we participated we now have a lot of stuff also some extraordinary parts!the internet. We have access to plethora of design information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Catherine Sarisky&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon and Target have it on sale pretty substantially, for folks in the US at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response by Chad Houck&lt;/strong&gt; 
Bricklink in general, but in our kit a must have part is the weighted brick. We used 6 total between bot and attachments last season. #73090. Bricklink has a few, but for specific and expensive parts we have done better on eBay. Found 6 of these for $20 shipped last season.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Team Building Activities</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/09/Team-Building-Activities.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Team Building Activities" /><published>2017-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/09/Team-Building-Activities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/09/Team-Building-Activities.html">&lt;p&gt;This article was inspired by a visit to the Forge Initiative in Cary, North Carolina. &lt;a href=&quot;http://theforgeinitiative.org/&quot;&gt;The Forge Initiative &lt;/a&gt; is a STEM/Makerspace for kids, adults and several FIRST teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/TeamBuildingWall.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above photograph is an organized wall full of misalaneous items. There are balls and bells, cardboard and foamboard, popsicle sticks and cones, bandanas and more. All the items were neatly organized alphabetically.  I love this idea of keeping a random collection of objects. While our own collection is not nearly as organized, I too like to pull random objects toghether to come up with team building activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-practice-team-building&quot;&gt;Why practice team building?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you are a FIRST LEGO League team, a company employee, or a member of boy scout’s troop, team building activities are pretty commonplace. They are a great way to learn to work together and appreciate each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;top-5-reasons-to-for-team-building-in-first-lego-league&quot;&gt;Top 5 reasons to for team building in FIRST LEGO League:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting to know each other better.&lt;/strong&gt; Kids from all over often come together to make teams. Sometimes, they barely know each other. Such activities are good icebreakers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team work and increasing the performance of the team.&lt;/strong&gt;  The team can learn to problem solve together and improve their overall performance during the season.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increasing Fun and creativity.&lt;/strong&gt;  Through team building, teams can display their personality. They will learn to be more creative and think out-of-the-box.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building communication skills.&lt;/strong&gt;   Activities will teach the team to communicate better with each other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A well-earned break.&lt;/strong&gt;  Team building activities offer a quick and fun break from the reaseach project and robot building at team meetings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-can-i-get-team-building-activities-to-practice&quot;&gt;Where can I get team building activities to practice?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just google team building on the Internet. If you look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ev3lessons.com/corevalues.html&quot;&gt;EV3Lessons.com (Resources)&lt;/a&gt;, you will see that there are over 37 Team Building Activities. These are various activities actually done by FIRST LEGO League teams. There are some that are designed as get-to-know-you activities. These are great at the start of the season.  There are some that help teams realize the role that each person plays.  No matter what activity you pick, understand that the goal is for the kids on the team to learn to work together and appreciate one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NOTE: As of August 8, 2017, the Core Values/Team Building section of EV3Lessons is being redesigned.  All the 37 activities will be put back as they get reformatted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Asha Seshan&lt;br&gt;Droids Robotics&lt;br&gt;Pittsburgh, PA</name></author><summary type="html">This article was inspired by a visit to the Forge Initiative in Cary, North Carolina. The Forge Initiative  is a STEM/Makerspace for kids, adults and several FIRST teams.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Selecting Team Members</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/08/Selecting-Team-Members.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selecting Team Members" /><published>2017-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/08/Selecting-Team-Members</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/08/Selecting-Team-Members.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from Mic Lowne:&lt;/b&gt; I’ve been running teams in schools since food factor and the biggest problem I face each year is selecting the 10 students out of 20-30 that want to be a part of the the team. How do other school based coaches deal with this? Usually I select based on 1st-attitude/willingness to learn, 2nd-attendance, 3rd-skill, 4th-an “application letter”. Thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/SelectingTeam.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Layne Kirk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Realizing this might not apply because we have a school site willing to fund us, but we have as many teams as we have willing coaches (2 per team). When we do recruitment, we make it clear that no student will be turned away, so long as we have enough coaches. And the only way to be guaranteed a spot is to have your parent coach. It’s not perfect - we’ve had some near coaching fails, but it’s a start for us and allows us to accommodate 48 students for next season (in addition to the youth protection screening for FIRST, our coaches are also fingerprinted and background checked locally). I also realize not all communities have participation of parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may take a season or two to build and work out the kinks, but it has worked for us. We, as coordinators, assign the teams, but allow requests to be made. We do our best to accommodate requests without any promises. We hold coaches meetings and equip our coaches to succeed, being readily available to assist them. And we have a total blast doing it! As a side note, we use Google forms for registration. That has worked extremely well for us. My husband and I love the program and are willing to be a resource if you’d like to pick our brains ☺. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Celina McGinnis:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use a variation of the “if you really want your kid to do this, coaching guarantees them a spot”. This year, we are going to try signing up ADULTS first, and supporting them in signing up children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Roy Nelson:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have teachers recommend specific kids. Balance your team with leaders, tech skills, research and presentations, and spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Mic Lowne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely agree (with Roy Nelson’s comment above’), it’s like picking a sports team sometimes, finding a team member that you know will fill a role within the team but still work as a team and help others out. In the student’s application letter I ask them to name the role they think they will be best suited for. This year I also asked students to nominate others they think will be well suited to each role. I got some interesting results, specifically who they nominated for leadership roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jean Findley-Williams:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I coach a community based team in Louisiana. Our team currently ranges in age from “almost 9” to 13 years old. This is the first year that we have not had anyone “graduate” from the team due to age. Next season, however, we will have at least 3 members moving on to high school. Two of those members will move on to our local FRC team and return to us as mentors. The third team member has expressed an interest to join our new community based FTC team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have very few options for FLL teams currently in our area. This means that we have constantly have parents who are contacting us inquiring how to ensure their child joins. When we do have openings, we hold recruitment camps where our returning team members are able to work directly with possible “candidates.” They develop all kinds of activities that involve not just building and programming a basic bot, but also involve team building challenges and very brief presentations. Returning team members rotate among the “candidate” groups so that they can meet everyone. We have also developed an application which involves students writing a short essay about why they would like to be on the team, what would they like to contribute and what they would like to learn. The team also has a few questions about the FLL Core Values included. At the end of each recruitment camp, returning team members submit a list of who they think would be a good fit to myself and my husband. We also all review the submitted essays together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As coaches, my husband and I develop an initial list of potential candidates that takes into account team member feedback, our observations and the essays. We then invite those students back for another meeting in which all of our returning team members and mentors (former team members) are present. During that meeting, my husband and I run the team building activities, present different programming and fun presentation challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following that meeting, our team then votes on who they would like to invite to the team. It can sometimes be a long process, but it works for us. It can sometimes be a leap of faith on our part, but I love the ownership it has instilled. It’s still a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Mark Nicolussi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I coach a school sponsored team, so I try and get the school to select a prioritised list of candidates based on primarily on interest and dedication, and then I invite from the top of the list until the slots are filled. It’s not the greatest system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Managing Your Team in a Shared Space</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/07/Shared-Spaces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Managing Your Team in a Shared Space" /><published>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/07/Shared-Spaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/07/Shared-Spaces.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from Simon Ward:&lt;/b&gt; How do teams manage the table and models between meetings? I’m guessing “leave it set up” is the best option. But what if space is limited, or it’s a shared room? We have this space (my classroom), but it’s a shared room. How practical is continually setting up/putting away models? I’m trying to weigh up time spent setting up / putting away vs. risk of other classes tampering with the set up of models, and putting the table out of action for the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/SharedRoom.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo Credit: Simon Ward&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Stephanie Ozenne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a permanent setup in my basement, and the primary challenge is that neighborhood kids regularly play there when I’m not present. Telling them not to touch the models didn’t help much, but laying a bed sheet over the whole table actually helped quite a bit - out of sight, out of mind, and it’s really obvious to others if someone is messing with the table. Maybe that would help?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jeff Hagan:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the setup that John from FastCats rigged up: he built a false top for his game table that stands a few inches above the top of the walls. He just has to tip over the taller models, put the false top on top, and suddenly the table can be used for other things between practices.   I can’t remember exactly how tall his was, but the general idea was to make it tall enough that most of the models every year wouldn’t have to be moved to put the false top on… but every year, there were generally a couple that are a bit too tall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Evonne Reynolds:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we get our own rooms but previously we had to set up and take down every time we met. The kids got really good at it and any of them that got there a couple minutes early would go ahead and get the models out to set it up. Taking it down at the end of the meeting wasn’t too time consuming either once they all learned where each model needed to go (we had a couple deep totes and a long shallow tote and certain models fit in each one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Mark Nicolussi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our room is shared - the table stays up but we have to tear down the field pieces and lock them away after every practice. After a while it becomes a pretty quick process - 10 minutes for set up, 5 minutes for tear down&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jason Baber:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting it up and taking it down is actually a plus: the kids will be faster at spotting things that may not be reset correctly in a tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jean Findley-Williams:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have always had to share a space so we have always had to set up and take down. Our team members are quick with it and it helps them to become well aware of spotting any inconsistencies. When they go into robot design judging in our state, there are often models not set up right or pieces out of place on purpose to see if the kids will notice. Our team is always quite quick with this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, because of the constant storing of the mat, it does show wear after awhile and will eventually begin to have lots of nice curves and bends. The team has to program around this which puts them at an advantage when it comes to the variability we sometimes see with challenge sets at competitions. We appreciate the familiarity the constant set up and take down affords the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/SharedRoom2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Carrie Koepke:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet at a gaming store. Our table is hidden under a false top/lid that is placed directly on the walls. Every meeting the boys reassemble the table to begin and remove anything that breaches wall height at the end. It has been an extremely good way to begin/end meetings and encourage some mega-table-familiaritiy. The models travel to and from with the robot and spare parts (also good team building as they load and unload the car).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/SharedRoom3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Debugging Tips</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/06/Debugging-Tips.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Debugging Tips" /><published>2017-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/06/Debugging-Tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/06/Debugging-Tips.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;. One of the participants asked a great question about how teams debug programs. Lots of great ideas shared below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from 
Francis Cariño Belizario:&lt;/b&gt; How do you all debug programs? I think collecting some of our teams’ favorite techniques in one place could be really helpful to new teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Debugging.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Stephanie Ozenne&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when the robot is behaving badly, the first thing my kids would do is inspect the program carefully - it can be easy to enter “12” under motor rotations instead of “1.2” and that makes the program look very different than you expect!
After that inspection, they would make sure they have the correct program downloaded and that they’re not using the “recently run” menu on the bot, which can sometimes throw you off (especially if you’ve recently changed the name of the program!).
After that, they’d check all the wiring and make sure the connections are tight. If a sensor is misbehaving, looking to see if it’s working in “port view” can be helpful.
If the program is &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; not working, they would insert “wait” blocks or sometimes insert a sound block just before or after the part of the program they suspect is doing something strange. Warning: Once my team used this method to make sure a sensor was seeing a line and stopping on it correctly to follow that line. They left the sound block in for a few weeks. When they went to take it out, the robot no longer would stop and find the line correctly! They determined that in the time the sound was playing, the robot had “settled” after it’s stop. Inserting a wait block for the same amount of time that the sound had played restored the expected behavior.
I think once or twice, we have disconnected large chunks of the program “off the beam” to see earlier parts of the program run alone and then add blocks back if the behavior goes back to what we expect.
That’s what I can think of off the top of my head. What do your teams do when the robot is suddenly behaving strangely to find the problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Joseph Gillen:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I insist our programmers label each section of a program with a comment text box–ex, “this block robot turns 90 degrees towards the weight machine”. They can also use it as a “scratch pad” to jot down changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the first question they ask if something goes wonky is, Is it a hardware problem or a software problem? What changes were made?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battery level is also big. Last year they had a heavy bot, which they noticed was a big drag on the battery and the robot would act differently on a full charge vs. a nearly depleted battery. They now check the battery charge often and make sure they ALWAYS charge it when not in use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Sara Hart Chisholm:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most times it’s a hardware problem for us - loose connection, to a loose wheel. Our team has learned to inspect the robot well before jumping to the conclusion that it is the program - especially if they have only been tweaking the program&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Ruth Ann Francis:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My team’s first step is to run the program again so see if the behavior is repeatable. If it’s not, it’s likely something mechanical (wire rubbing on tire or something dragging on the mat) or something with the set-up. If the issue is repeatable, it’s more likely to be a software/programming issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they check to make sure that everything is correct with the robot - right program run, all sensors and motors properly connected and reading correctly, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they check the program. What was the last thing changed? We try to make only one change at a time so that the debugging is easier. Were the correct ports selected? Are the motors going the right direction? Do the values make sense…like the 1.2 vs 12. Are the units correct? (Always check your units! If my structures professor in college taught me anything, it was that once your units are correct, you’re more than likely over halfway there….but, ya know, with something of a Brooklyn/Indian accent.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we still can’t identify the problem, we undo the last change and try it again. If it works, it’s something in the change we made. If not, it’s something with the robot that we missed and it might be time for a reset/reboot (If I’ve learned anything from the programming alpha geek at work it’s that many problems can be solved by rebooting…I also sometimes wonder if he’s not taking that time to fix the thing he realized he screwed up with the last update someone asked him to make. In any event, it often works.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we still can’t figure out what’s wrong, then we start pulling big chunks of code off the beam and adding them back, one or a few at a time until we can figure out what’s wrong (almost always it’s that someone wasn’t paying enough attention when they did one of the troubleshooting steps above). Often times I relate a trouble shooting story from work. More often than not the issue could have been solved by better documentation. (One of these seasons my team is going to trust me that everything is easier when it’s properly documented and actually do it. Until then, I’ll keep telling my stories and sighing exasperatedly and they’ll keep rolling their eyes and promising to update the documentation right away and keep it current and then get distracted talking about the latest super hero movie or video game.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Swati Gupta:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Battery level check&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wire connections check/verify in Port View,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check program: run the myblocks only , select and run specific blocks: tell kids to comment and keep it modular (My Blocks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Travis Smith:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travis Smith A lot of people don’t know this, but if you connect via bluetooth and press the “play” button at the beginning of the program (instead of on the brick) then each block will be highlighted as the robot executes the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Francis Cariño Belizario:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We go to our program, divide the program into the first block and the rest, run the program, add the next block, and so on until we see which part is wrong, fix it, continue coding and testing step by step&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn . One of the participants asked a great question about how teams debug programs. Lots of great ideas shared below.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Family LEGO Night: Fundraising Tips</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/05/Family-LEGO-Night-Fundraising-Tips.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Family LEGO Night: Fundraising Tips" /><published>2017-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/05/Family-LEGO-Night-Fundraising-Tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/05/Family-LEGO-Night-Fundraising-Tips.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from 
Jennifer Francis:&lt;/b&gt; Our team is looking at hosting a family Lego night as a fundraiser to buy an extra team robot/computer. Where would we find or how could we get a large amount of Legos to sustain such an event? Does anyone have any suggestions or has anyone done something like this that can offer some tips?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/FamilyLEGONight.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Michael Risch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you near a LEGO store at all? The lego club used to involve builds with giant boxes of LEGO. They might be willing to let you host your night there, using their LEGO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the PTO idea. The problem is that if you are mixing people’s LEGO, folks will be unhappy. Do you have a Barnes &amp;amp; Noble near you? I’m assuming not, but they also have builds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depends on how many kids. At the LEGO Club, 20 or so kids would each build using a single 30x30x30 box (no idea how many pieces fit in there)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Seshan Brothers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the local AFOL (Adult Fan of LEGO) group/LUG (LEGO User Group) in your area might let you borrow LEGO for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Shelby Davis:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also buy bulk Lego on eBay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Katie McCann Kelley:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FYI: The LEGO Store will sell you cases of LEGO Bricks. For example: A case of 2x4 bricks in one color. They also can have single simple machine motors and a battery packs to sell. They are not on the floor- you have to ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Swati Gupta:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think beyond Lego for a Lego night. For example there are Lego candy , Lego moulds with which you can make Lego chocolates , play dough Lego and much more… give them moulds and play dough and let them make lego bricks and then stuff out of it… you can order Lego complaint bricks may be, they will be cheaper.. ppl can bring in some model made out of Lego from their home based on Hydrodynamics theme and you can have a contest of that. Have a big piñata of Lego shape…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Maureen Reilly:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a family night at school with “pocket LEGO” and gave each participant a small bag with 6 bricks and a tiny baseplate and did different timed challenges “build a rocket” “build a dream city” “build an amusement park ride” etc. Yes you can combine with friends… LEGO crayons are great to make and take too w/LEGO molds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Scott Mengle:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also try Craigslist. I know someone who got 40 lb of mixed stuff for $50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Jean Findley-William:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past three years each team member researches and develops their own Lego game or challenge and supplies their own Legos as needed. When a child participates in one of the challenges, we give them tickets that they can then redeem at the end of the night for trinkets that we get donated. At this year’s FLN they had a lot of fun with several buildings challenges, a Lego brain puzzle, some Lego minute to win it challenges, remote control soccer bots, an art bot, a cookie icing bot, and Duplo Bridge weight challenge. Everyone kept with their own Legos that they brought for the event. Here is a link to images from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.family-lego-night.bayoubuilders.org/page&quot;&gt;Bayou Builders’ Family LEGO Nights.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Janet Goff Glaze:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try Toys R Us. They host Lego building days and get thousands of small kits in for kids to build, they always have hundreds of left over kits! You can ask them to donate them to your group?? My husband is a manager there &amp;amp; his store always gives away the extra kits!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Erica Morrill:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some good ideas for additional activities &lt;a href=&quot;https://sunflowerstorytime.com/2014/03/07/lego-family-night-2/&quot;&gt; here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really liked the idea of a Lego Family night! I thought we may include a bake sale with ours. Here is my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pinterest.com/ericaannem/lego-family-night/&quot;&gt;Pintrest site&lt;/a&gt; with some of the ideas I found for food items and activities that didn’t require a lot of LEGO.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Transitioning From FIRST LEGO League to other FIRST Programs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/04/Transitioning-From-FIRST-LEGO-League.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transitioning From FIRST LEGO League to other FIRST Programs" /><published>2017-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/04/Transitioning-From-FIRST-LEGO-League</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coachcorner/2017/08/04/Transitioning-From-FIRST-LEGO-League.html">&lt;p&gt;The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/FLLShareandLearn/&quot;&gt;FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Question from 
Francis Cariño Belizario:&lt;/b&gt; Any of your FLL team members also part of an FTC team? Any transition stories?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coachcorner/Transition.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Gloria Gibson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No–although my 4 team members on FTC are all under 14 yrs. old and could be doing FLL–they choose to move up and challenge themselves. It’s not something I recommend for everyone, but when you have some kids that have succeeded in FLL it makes sense to take the next step sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Joseph Gillen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have our FLL teams up until 8th grade, then start FTC in high school. We’re only in our second year of FTC, but the kids with FLL experience are clearly the leaders. We have done it no other way, but this has worked perfectly for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Faith Knudsen Bongiorno&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Double check, students can only be on one roster per season is my understanding from FIRST. We ran into this question of students doing both FLL and FTC last year in SC. My son just transition to FRC for next season. He did FLL from 3rd-8th grades. He looked at both FRC and FTC. He choose FRC because of the mechanical design opportunities. His new team is working on STEM outreach over the summer and fall. It is clear who are former FLL members versus students who have never involved in a FIRST program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Charles Angel:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are in the process of our first transition. Our team of 10 FLL kids won state and advanced to Worlds last season. Only one officially aged out, but we decided to move 7 of them up. We did a three week Summer training with them and saw great interest and motivation / excitement with the new set of challenges. Some of our rookie FLLers this year are old enough to do FTC, however, you can see a difference between those with FLL experience…so we want them to gain some confidence and experience in FLL. This is our first FTC team, so it is a work in progress and we will have more information about the transition in the future. I will be curious to hear and see others input on this topic&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response from Francis Cariño Belizario:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all replies. I asked because when we did this three years ago, not only was the scheduling a major issue due to conflicts but the biggest problem for us was the transition from “visual programming” to “text programming”. And although we were one of only two middle school teams against 14 high schools, we still won an award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was just introduced to Blockly and highly recommend it as an aid to help FLL kids transition to FTC with regards to proramming.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Various</name></author><summary type="html">The following discussion is quoted from the Facebook Group FLL: Share &amp;amp; Learn .</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Butler/Passion/1/img/3.png" /></entry></feed>
